I don't know.
OK, welcome.
Welcome to the fifth lecture on deep learning for NLP.
And just make me sure that this is working.
So this is the case.
OK, cool.
Happy to see you again.
Just a few feedbacks I got from last lecture.
So thanks a lot for the feedback, by the way.
And so there is an interesting mixture of feedback
on the pace of these lectures.
Some people saying it's too slow,
and some saying it's too fast.
So I'm afraid the truth may be somewhere in the middle,
and it really depends on what you already know
and what you don't know.
So yeah, so if you, unfortunately, you
cannot skip it.
We're fast forward here.
So just be patient and try to keep up.
And if it's too fast, then I would
suggest you just go to YouTube then
and watch the lecture again maybe and go on your own pace.
And if you have any questions, just, so this
is like the first feedback.
I hope it will make everybody, well, not happy,
but at least a little bit happy.
And the question was about the Übung,
so the exercises and the homeworks.
If you can get any advice or any help on that, yes, absolutely.
So there's contacts for the tutors on the Moodle,
or you just, you know, you can DM them on Discord
or get in touch with them.
And there could be on-demand consultations with them
if you want.
So feel free to approach the tutors
and feel free to address them with any question
you might have.
Great.
OK, so today's lecture is entitled Text Generation,
Language Models, and Word Embedding.
So we are so far considering text classification.
And now we're moving to text generation,
but the boundary is kind of not really the chart.
OK, so the story so far was we talked about last time
about nonlinearity and multilayer perceptron
in the end, and also some how to embed
categorical features.
But we're going to spend a little bit of time on that,
because I guess it's really central to deep learning
and NLP.
So the thing with the nonlinearity,
and give you an example why the nonlinearity
is central to actually good representation learning.
So everybody remembers this?
What is this?
It's a log-linear model for, well, this
could be like binary classification,
because here we are outputting.
We have a categorical, sorry, excuse me.
We have a scalar label here, which is 0, 1.
And we're plugging into the features, into the model,
multiplying by weights and bias.
And here's some nonlinearity, which could be, for example,
sigma.
OK, so this is good.
And this works well for cases which are
so-called linearly separable.
So linear models works for cases,
for classification cases where you can separate your training
instances by a line.
What it really means, so here's a couple of, I guess,
cool visualizations coming from the Playground TensorFlow.
I really recommend go there and play around with the data.
So just to explain what we're trying to do here.
So we have a task, which is a binary classification.
And here we see the data set, which is very small.
Here is a bigger one.
Here we see how we have two features, basically.
So two dimensions.
So this is the x vector is of dimensionality 2.
And one feature is this x.
And the other feature is on this x.
And we see blue and red dots defined by their feature.
So feature value here, this is one red dot.
And it has feature value such and such.
And the other class, the blue ones, are mostly here.
So they have different features.
Everybody's with me?
Feature representation?
OK, so they have numerical values, these features.
If these were words, they would be maybe 0 or 1
for binary 1-hot encoding.
Or there could be also real numbers between maybe 0 and 1.
So we have these feature projected in two dimensional
space.
And what we're trying to do is to separate them,
to classify them into the learned decision rule,
to separate them into blue and orange.
And after you run this, after training,
there's like 176 epochs, which you can run in a browser.
And it will learn there is a line between these two classes.
And it achieves 100% accuracy.
So the test loss, they call it the loss.
So the lower, the better.
The test loss is 0.
Yeah, so we reach 100% accuracy.
Why is this?
Why we call this linearly separable?
So we can draw a line between the two classes,
so a line in two dimensions.
There is a line which separates these two classes,
so instances from one and the other.
If we were in the three dimensions or more dimensions,
it wouldn't be a line.
It would be the so-called hyperplane.
And hyperplane is always a plane which
is one dimension less than the surrounding space.
So in three dimensions, hyperplane would be a plane.
In four dimensions, hyperplane would be,
I have no idea what it would be, so some kind
of linear function.
But in two dimensions, it's a line.
In one dimension, it would be just a dot.
If we have examples on one dimension, left and right,
we would find a dot, like a one point, which
kind of separates these two classes
if they are linearly separable.
Everybody's with me on linear separation?
Why is this the case?
This is nice.
And linear models can tackle that.
This is cool.
Unfortunately, in reality, most things
are not linearly separable in the feature space we know.
So for example, a task called exclusive or,
we have the same setup, blue and red dots.
But now, these blue and red dots kind of occupy
different parts of the space.
So here, we have the red dots.
And here are the blue dots.
The problem is, if you run, OK, and maybe I
should say something about this thing here.
So this is basically a linear model.
There is no hidden layer anywhere.
So this is just features transformed by,
as we have here, this model.
So basically, the same thing.
So we have the features.
There's some transformation and bias.
And that's it.
And no, this is like a sigmoid.
So this is the same thing.
x1, x2 features.
There is this multiplication implicitly.
And then we map it to the outputs.
Unfortunately, linear models, I mean, well, not linear models.
I mean, can you draw me a line between these two classes
so it separates them with some OK-ish accuracy?
Well, there is no way to do.
I mean, you can do like that.
You get 50%.
You can do like that.
This would be 50% accuracy.
I mean, there is no way to draw a line
to get some meaningful accuracy which is not random.
Is it clear?
Yeah, so that's bad.
So OK, so what can we do about it?
How can we make this model more expressive?
What can we add something to the model?
Yes?
We can add a function.
We can add a function?
OK, that would be cool.
Which function and where?
For example, some logarithmic function
so instead of a straight line, we have a curve.
We can, OK, so you say you can add some curve somewhere.
Yes.
Yes, that might be.
But you would have to kind of transform the features in a way.
You can do this.
You can transform the features.
But we learned that in deep learning,
you learn a presentation of the features.
So you learn some mapping to some other space.
So there is something which is much,
which could be better suited to learn better
representation of these features,
to map them somewhere else.
Yes.
Non-linear function?
We can add non-linear function.
OK, yes, non-linearity, I'm with you because obviously,
it is a non-linear for a reason.
Yeah, yes.
We can add more parameters, I would say.
More dimensions.
Yes.
All right, OK, so you're again in the feature space.
That's fine.
That's doable, but we have some maybe.
We can add it in layers, exactly.
Let's add a layer, OK?
So because a layer is basically a mapping from one space
to another space.
And maybe in the other space, the features
will be better, more separable, OK?
So that's a good question.
That's a good approach.
So let's do something.
We stack it.
We add another transformation and another layer.
So and this is, we're adding here another linear layer here.
So this was our first model, right?
And we're plugging in here another transformation,
another linear map.
So we're mapping from the hidden state to the output space,
right?
This is what we had last time.
So stacking linear layers.
And we will see that stacking linear layers
is still a linear model.
We said it last time, but now we can also demonstrate it
exactly.
So basically, there is just two linear transformation,
which is, in the end, again, a linear transformation.
So if you do it here in this kind of playground,
and we're adding one hidden layer here,
but this is still linear, so there
is no non-linearity here, it still
failed to learn anything meaningful.
Because at the end, it's still trying to find a curve.
Sorry, find a line.
So stacking linear layers after each other
doesn't save you because it's a linear model.
And here we have another proof, like a visual kind
of visualization of that.
So this is not a good idea.
So we need to do one more thing here.
And somebody said it like, who said it?
Non-linearity.
I guess so.
So what we need to do to plug into here
is some non-linearity after this layer.
And this is the non-linear function here.
Oh, sorry, after the first layer.
So this is the non-linear function,
which is applied element-wise.
So we're plugging here some non-linear transformation
of our second projection space.
So what are the typical non-linear functions?
We have, last time, I guess, we have
ReLU, which is taking a maximum, or it's basically
such a function.
So it's 0 for 0 values.
And then it's just a linear.
So this is ReLU.
And another one, very typically, is hyperbolic tangent.
So it's two exponentiations.
And it's basically squashing everything between, I guess,
minus 1 and 1, roughly, I guess.
Oh, sorry.
That should be 0.
OK.
So we plug in this function in there.
And it's going to make wonders.
Because then, even if we add a fewer neurons
in the hidden layer, it will exactly
learn this kind of mapping.
It will learn that the space is now, in the latent space,
is kind of now projected into something
which is linearly separable.
And at the end, in this space, there
is a line which kind of distinguish them.
And here, we're mapping back to the original feature space.
So in the feature space, we have these kind of weird shapes.
And in the hidden layer, it's a linear function
which can kind of distinguish these points, the red
and blue ones.
So we can, with non-linear function and one hidden layer,
we can solve the exclusive part problem, for example.
Any questions?
Well, I have one.
So where do you see, where would you
find XOR function in NLP classification?
Like XAOR, like either or those.
Will you find some example of that,
where this is a real issue in, let's say,
classification with words?
Yeah, and how exactly in sentiment analysis?
Do you have any idea?
I have one.
I think it's true.
Sure, OK, yes.
But I think you're taking a different angle,
because we're talking about the features.
Like where do you find the features
that have these properties?
Like both of them either true or both of them either false
and not the other way around.
Any idea?
Maybe just like sentiment of negative.
Sentiment of negatives, you're close.
OK, so I guess this could be an example.
So we have here basically a vocabulary, only three words.
OK, so I'm not laughing.
It's not a real example, but it might happen.
So we have just three words in our vocabulary,
and the words are not, bad, and good.
And the features are binary.
So either we have the feature is there in the text as one,
or the feature is not there as zero.
And I visualize here as a three dimension.
So here basically is dimension of good.
So here is zero.
So the good is not there, and good is there.
And here, the bad is there, and not.
And here, not is there, and here's nothing.
So we have three features, and there
are several interesting combinations.
So for example, here, so can you visualize this 3D space?
In here, we have a combination of not good,
because the bad feature is zero here.
So we have not good.
And here, we have combination of not is one
and bad is one, which corresponds to not bad.
And if you just project this on a plane,
so I try to draw a plane here, which is this projection.
So this blue thing is this projection.
We would have this X error problem,
because we have in this area instances which
are good and not bad, which corresponds
to the positive sentiment.
And here, we have bad and not good,
which corresponds to the negative sentiment
of the labels.
How can you draw a line here?
Well, you can't.
So that's the point.
So this one potential example of having this exclusive
or in the feature space for text classification.
And obviously, we need to solve with some non-linearity, which
would be MLP with non-linear function in between.
OK?
Any questions?
Good.
OK.
So let's move on.
So this was like a recap from last time,
but I wanted to really stress the non-linearity
and the linearity, how important concept that is.
If you stack linear layers, that's
not going to solve your problem.
The second thing we had last time
was the embeddings of categorical features.
And we're going to spend some time on this today as well.
So just to recap, we have these learned.
So we are doing, what was it, language identification, right?
Six different categories and vocabulary.
And we said that this matrix W is a learned representation.
And each row, basically, in this learned representation
of the matrix corresponds to a particular word, a unigram.
And it gives us some dense representation of this word.
Because on this original feature space,
these are just one-hot encodings.
And by this projection, we are projecting them
into something which is not that big.
So how big would be the, OK, how big is the vocabulary,
typically, again?
50,000, yes?
10,000, 50,000, 70,000, right.
So we are compressing a 70,000 one-hot encoding
into a six-dimensional vector.
So it has different properties, but it's
a dense representation.
And it might have nice properties
that maybe two words are kind of similar in this latent space.
So basically, here, so this is our multilayer perceptron.
So this is the first layer.
And then this is the second layer.
And here, after this first layer,
we have this nonlinear function.
And in the first layer, this W1, this
learns representation embeddings of the categorical features
index.
So we had it last time.
And it's going to be a topic today and in the next lecture
as well.
So learning representation, this is
a key part of deep learning and learning good representations.
So whatever you do at the end, be it classification
or a generation, it's always like classification
or probability distribution prediction.
It's nicely separable.
Great, so today we are moving into,
I'm sorry, any questions to this part?
All right, so we are moving to language models
and also word embeddings a little bit.
And we start with the language models.
And for language models, you unfortunately or fortunately
need some probability theory a little bit.
And I guess it's never too late to refresh
a little bit of probability theory.
So let's jump into that and have it done.
So OK, a quick poll.
Who hates probability theory?
Fair enough.
Who loves probability theory?
OK, so OK, I'm not going to ask you why do you hate it?
No, serious.
That's a serious question.
What makes you feel awkward about probability theory?
Any ideas?
I'm really curious.
It's not very intuitive.
OK, that's true.
Any other why people hate probability theory?
Everybody uses different notation.
Everybody's using different notation.
Yes, yes.
Yes, I second that.
Anything else?
I failed an exam.
You failed an exam?
Oh, man.
I failed so many exams.
And you know, that doesn't mean yes.
But there was a reason why you failed.
Right?
Anyway, so last opinion on why probability theory is kind of
not the nicest course.
Anything except options.
Yeah.
OK, you can think about it.
And you know, at the evening thing, you're like, well,
maybe it's not that bad.
But I completely second the part like everybody's
using different notations.
And this is exactly if so because if you
do like high school probability theory,
you have all these like all random variables.
And then you go statistics.
And you have like, oh, everything is Gaussian.
And then you go to machine learning.
Like it's like everything is categorical random variables.
There's no even random variables.
They're just probability distributions.
And they call it like, oh, what is this?
And then you have like really hardcore, I would say,
measure theory kind of mathematicians saying like,
well, everything's integral and expectations anyway.
And you feel like these are different worlds.
They're the same thing.
But everybody's using different kind of notations and stuff
like that.
So that's why I think it's also important to kind of have
a refresher here on the notations
we're going to be using.
So we have categorical random variables.
We had it already before, like different categories.
And there's no ordering whatsoever.
So maybe a categorical random variable
is something which we observe as random
and want to reason about the probabilities of these things.
So the first word in a sentence, for example,
we call it capital letter and W1, for example.
So now we're using notation.
Well, it's not a matrix.
It's a random variable.
Oh, that sucks.
OK, so just be aware it's coming from a different kind
of broad limit.
So we have the first random variable.
And this could be one of those words from vocabulary.
OK, it's random.
But we have a probability distribution
over these random variables.
And the probability distribution is saying,
well, OK, what is the actual outcome
of this event of this random variable?
And what is this probability?
And the probability is something between 0 and 1.
So for example, what is the outcome
that the first word is equals to d.
And it has some probability.
And we put basically probability distribution.
We distribute the overall probability of 1
to each of these categories over the vocabulary.
OK, everybody's with me?
There is one property we need to take into account.
This is everything sums up to 1.
So if you estimate these probabilities,
it has to sum up to 1.
So far, so good.
And then comes the notation.
So we're using different notations.
And you will see.
So this PR is actually very nice in LaTeX.
So you just write PR.
And it renders this thing.
But people are using also.
And here we're saying, OK, the random variable
equals to some outcome.
So there's a value.
People are also using just PW1 or just P of the word and so on.
And this can get very confusing and messy.
And you just misuse notation.
So be aware of that.
Eventually, there is a random variable
taking some of these values of the categories.
Any questions so far?
Or any suggestions?
Are we doing something which you've never seen?
I'm not sure.
But the data is not independently distributed, right?
The data isn't independently distributed.
We are not there even.
We're saying there is a one random variable.
And we say, for example, this is the first word.
And the event would be, OK, well, I have a pack of first.
I don't have a pack.
Here's the first words of the sentence.
And I'm going to grab one.
And it's the word the.
That's it.
That's what we're doing.
We don't have a second word.
We have nothing like that.
We're just saying, oh, there's a random variable.
OK?
There's no independence whatsoever so far.
OK, another question?
Good.
So then we have a notion of joint probability distribution.
And this could be, for example, probability
of the word the at position one and the cat at position two.
And basically, it's again, we're using this.
I'm sorry.
Where's my hair?
We're using this notation because eventually,
probabilities or events are sets.
And everything comes to set theory.
So there's just a set intersection.
But people are using comma as well.
And we're basically saying, OK, I know.
I'm grabbing here.
What is the probability the first word, the,
and the second word, this cat.
And we multiply them together if they're independent
or don't if they are not because they are not.
But anyway, so this is like joint probability.
And we also see the notation with comma.
And since there is no distinction between what
comes first because these are sets and there's no ordering,
we can also write the same like start with w2 and w1 and then
w1.
So these are equivalent because there
is no ordering of these events.
Well, sorry, random variables.
Everybody's with me?
OK, good.
Then we have conditional probability.
And this is basically a definition of that.
So for example, a probability of cat at position 2
given that we saw d at position 1.
And we're using this pipe here.
So w is something, w1, w2 is something,
and w1 is what we've observed kind of.
And we kind of divide these two probabilities.
So the joint divided by the observed variable.
Any questions?
Conditional probability?
Yes.
So we're conditioning.
OK, so if I saw something already,
there is something I've experienced already.
So I'm thinking, based on this information
I got from this observation, what
is the probability of the next event?
So if I saw d at the position 1, it kind of
changes the probabilities of the next word.
Because if I saw, for example, i at position 1,
then the next word would be probably most probably m
or will and so on.
If I saw, I have a sentence, and the first word is i,
then the probability of the second word
would be maybe higher for m and then will and do and so on.
I mean, this makes sense.
After i typically comes something from these words.
While when the first word was v, then the second word
will be most likely, I don't know, something else unknown.
The man, the cat, and so on.
But none of those, because the m is very unlikely.
And what's the probability that the next word is given?
And then I'm thinking, what's the probability
of the next word given the first word?
OK?
Good.
Any other questions?
I hope that's not the reason why you hate probability theory.
But OK, so one last slide and we're through it.
So then we have independence of random variables,
and then two random variables are independent if and only
if their joint probability is the product
of their probabilities.
I don't know if you're actually going to use it here,
but it's important to know.
OK, independent random variables,
you have to know that.
And then we have also conditional independence,
where two random variables x, y are conditionally independent
given something observed if and only
if their joint condition is product
of these conditional probabilities.
Maybe you don't need this one at all.
But independent random variables you should know and remember,
because they are all over the place.
Yes?
AUDIENCE MEMBER 2 And 1.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 3.
And that's correct.
Yeah, and here as well.
Yeah, fine.
Yeah, thank you.
Now this is correct.
Anything else which is bad on these slides?
OK, good.
Nobody noticed.
This is really because I use it already once,
and now I say, oh, of course.
So they didn't pay attention.
Good, you do.
All right, so this will like probability refresher,
and this is all you need.
Now let's move to language models.
And we'll start with something which
is called classical language models for a reason,
because language models mean different things nowadays.
But at the end of the day, they mean the same thing as well.
So what is language models, and why do we care about it?
So the goal of language modeling is
to assign a probability to sentences or sequences
of words in the language.
So for example, we might ask, what
is the probability of seeing the sentence,
the lazy dog bark loudly?
Why do we want to know this?
Like, why do we care about the probability
of a sentence in language in the first place?
Is it of any use?
Maybe.
I'll give you another example, and then I'll
let you think about it.
Also, we want the language model to assign
a probability of a given word or a sequence of words
to follow the sequence of words.
So for example, what is the probability of seeing the word
bark after seeing the sequence the lazy dog?
So we have the lazy dog, and the next word
would be, oh, bark, or maybe something else.
So what is the probability of bark?
So now, why this is interesting at all?
AUDIENCE 2.
Are phones complete on phones, for example?
I would say complete on phones, for example,
because every time you type something,
and it gives you the next sentence, next word,
and you just type the next word, the next word, the next word.
And they're also sorted, I guess, right?
I mean, you have the most likely and second most likely
and so on.
Any other idea why a language model might be good?
AUDIENCE 3.
Maybe if you are generating text,
you want to know which type, which word,
like, happen together.
Yeah.
If you're generating text, you want
to prefer sentences which are more likely in the language.
Yeah, that's correct.
It's kind of the same with the suggestion for typing,
but you have to do it manual.
And if you're generating text, we come to that later.
You can use it, definitely.
Yes?
AUDIENCE 4.
Text, but text, and sentences with both of them
are more expressive, or it's given more context.
Oh, this is interesting.
OK, for text classification, the sentences which are less likely
are more important.
Huh.
Like, the area, the post-coding, I guess,
or some subject of physics or something.
OK.
That's interesting.
Yeah, that could work.
I mean, you can use the probability
to infer something about the training data,
and then you might want to maybe filter your training
data based on the probability.
So filter out the common examples
and adding some outliers in your model, maybe.
I didn't see that much, but it's, yeah, why not?
OK, cool.
Maybe for text comprehension, when a sentence is given,
and the word was not understandable,
because it was pronounced poorly,
because it was written falsely.
OK, yeah.
That's what is most likely the worst part of the information.
Yeah, exactly.
And if you put it a little bit farther,
you can use it basically for speech recognition.
And it's basically where it has been used for decades
in speech recognition, because typically, now,
it's everything is like one model in a row.
But before that, you had transferring,
I'll get to, transferring from acoustic signal
to some set of phonemes or some subword units.
And then you want to reason about,
like, what is the most likely sentence in this language,
given these set of phonemes?
And then you have to rank your predictions based
on their probability in the language.
And the language model would give you
the rank of the probabilities.
Yeah.
I forgot.
Word similarity.
Word similarity?
Yeah.
I forgot the context of the word.
But otherwise, I'm confident.
But you need probability of sequences for that.
I don't know.
I mean, it makes sense what you're saying.
But I'm thinking, like, whether you need a language
model to kind of assess that.
OK, any other point?
Yeah.
Language models for POS tagging?
Not language models, but for example,
let's say we were to do a word mark,
but we're going to say it's a musical.
We would look at another, for example,
to give a probability for the next word you would have.
Sure, yeah.
You can, yeah.
So like, you have transition probabilities between words
and multiply by the tags.
And you're in Markov model stuff.
OK, yeah, this is not really like language models.
Because language model is basically
just a sequence of words.
But the ideas from language models
are kind of similar to the Markov models.
It's correct.
Another one, I saw, yes.
Sorry, can you speak louder?
Sorry.
Geometrical structures?
Yeah, maybe, yes.
You can reason about similar structures
in terms of their probabilities in language.
That's correct.
OK, yeah, so very good.
Language models is a thing.
Basically, nowadays, what you see in ChetGPTN,
all these models, this is basically a language model.
It's not a language model in the classical sense.
But it's just doing predict the next word thing.
Given the context, just give me what's the next word.
And you have a probability of the next word.
And you pick maybe the most likely one.
And it generates the next text.
This is basically the same kind of underlying idea
of language modeling.
That's why also these transformer models are also
called large language models or language models.
Because they don't give you necessarily
the probability of the sequence.
But they give you probability distribution
of the next word, maybe, or generate the top next word.
So that's why language model is really central to NLP.
And then let's have a look at a formal definition.
So we have a sequence of words.
And I'm using a small w.
And this is a sequence, 1 to n, which
is just a concatenation of word w1, w2, and so on.
So we want to estimate the probability of the sequence,
which is null.
And now we are kind of misusing notation.
Because it's a joint probability of word at position 1,
at certain word of position 2, and so on.
So we're sloppy in notation.
We should kind of write this really precisely.
So what is the joint probability that the given
word is at position 1?
The given word is, sorry, this should be w2.
The given word is position 2, and so on, so on, so on.
So like joint kind of probability distribution
of all these random variables, where each random variable
means what is the position, what is
the word at certain position.
So typically, when we have this large joint probability,
we typically factorize it into a product.
And here, we're using very nice factorization,
which is left to right factorization.
So what we're going to do is that in order
to write this joint probability, so this is a name, basically.
Factorization has a name.
And it's called also the chain rule.
But not the chain rule as we know,
but the chain rule of probability.
So you can factorize the joint probability distribution
into a factor of conditional probabilities.
And it comes from the definition of conditional probability.
So here, we're saying the probability distribution
of the whole sequence is a product
of these conditional probabilities.
And here, we're starting with something very awkward.
We're starting with what's the probability of given word 1
given this symbol s.
And this symbol s is just a starting symbol of the sequence.
So we're saying, OK, given the starting symbol of the sequence,
what's the probability of word 1?
Then multiply by, OK, what's the probability of word 2
given the start and first word?
What's the probability of word 3 given the start, word 1
and word 2, and so on and so on?
So this is one way, how can we factorize this large joint
distribution?
Why this is useful?
Why are we factorizing from left to right?
Exactly.
We only need the words we've seen before.
And there's something special about language.
We write left to right, and we also think left to right,
speak left to right, because for everything
you need to know so far, you've heard it before,
because you don't have to look in the future, because you
don't see the future, mostly.
So this is interesting, because the language is kind of like
left to right thing in writing mostly,
and also in conceptual thinking.
Good.
So this is great, but is there any catch here?
So this is nice factorization, but still, maybe, is it,
are we getting any better than just this up here?
Is this any better in terms of complexity, or model size,
or whatever you want?
Is there any catch?
I mean, we can factorize this thing, but did it help us?
Yeah.
Yeah, we can compute the probability
of the whole sentence, but OK, but maybe, yes, you're right.
Yes.
Would it be very specific possibilities,
like you can only generate text, but you don't
have to see the code?
Not really.
I don't think so.
Maybe I don't understand what you're saying.
Is that you're trying for the last sentence?
The last, yes.
The last sentence of text, but everything that came before
would, like, there probably wouldn't be a vector in there
that would?
Exactly, yeah.
Exactly.
So this is basically too big to make some good estimates
of any probability, because you would have to see this sequence
before in order to estimate the probability
of the next token, right?
Was it what you were trying to say?
No, I'm talking about the sentence,
just like, at some point, the probability will be 0.
Yeah, exactly.
At some point, the probability will be 0.
OK, so this is the part.
I mean, basically, we turn the problem of n random variables
in the problem of n minus 1 random variables,
so it's not of much use.
I mean, this is awful.
Why is it awful?
Well, because of the complexity, and we get to that,
and the zero probabilities as well.
Yeah, that's a good point.
So we need to make some simplification.
And the simplification will be, because here, we're still
depending on the all previous words.
If you have a sentence of, like, 40 tokens,
you still need all of them to factor in,
which you need in order to understand language.
You need a long kind of dependencies.
For example, in books, how to depend on it.
In books, the dependencies are quite long,
because in one chapter, there's introduction of a person.
There's a name.
And 60 pages later, you have to remember the name,
kind of in order to make the distance and understand.
Well, we're going to simplify it in classical language models,
because despite factorization, this is the issue.
The last term still depends on all the previous words
of the sequence.
So we're going to make a so-called Markov assumption,
k-th order Markov assumption.
And you might have seen Markov assumption
in many other contexts.
We're only saying that the next word depends only
on the last k words.
So we're saying, well, OK, this probability of the i-th word
doesn't depend on all the previous words.
It only depends on the previous and the k previous words.
So I'll show you an example in this slide.
So for example, if we have the sentence,
so the starting bold, the cat sat on the,
and then we want to model probability of the token W6.
We're position 6.
And we have second order Markov assumption.
Then we're going to turn the whole joint or condition
probability based on depending on the whole sentence
into basically probability of this sentence
given the previous two.
Right.
So we only take the two previous tokens to depend on.
So this is a simplification, right?
I mean, why should it work?
So like, it works kind of, but it doesn't really work?
Exactly.
Yeah, that's a good point.
That's a good point.
Can I, OK, I'm going to quote you.
What did you say?
It doesn't kind of, it kind of works,
but it doesn't really work.
Yeah, that's true.
It kind of works.
But obviously, if you just cut the context,
it doesn't really work.
But it mostly works.
Yeah, that's the goal.
So it works for many reasons.
So the k order would be something between,
I don't know, like 2, 3, 4, 4 maximum.
So 4 orders, so we call it also n-gram.
So n-gram language model, so 2-gram, bigram language model
or trigram language model.
It works surprisingly good, although we kind of
ignore the whole long dependency stuff, right?
So because also in language, mostly we kind of
work locally most of the time.
So it works.
And obviously, it will fail for reasons
where you need longer dependencies.
It will work also like computationally,
because how can we estimate these probabilities?
OK, well, this is the point.
Like probability, well, how do we know the probabilities?
How can we learn them?
This is an interesting question.
So how do we learn the probabilities?
How can we estimate the probabilities of, for example,
let me say, how do we find the probability of this?
OK.
So any data, I think, is counted, basically?
We're counting, yes, exactly.
We're counting, and there's another very fancy operation,
counting and dividing.
Yes, we're counting and dividing, exactly.
So it has a fancy name.
Do you know a fancy name for that?
It's called maximum likelihood estimation, basically
counting and dividing.
So in order to estimate this conditional probability
of word, the position i, given the previous context,
we're looking at a sequence of the whole sequence
and the number of occurrences.
So this is number of occurrences.
And divided by the number of occurrences
without the last word.
And that's it.
That's how we estimate the probabilities.
Sounds easy.
Is it easy?
It's super easy, actually.
You can really implement it.
Just go through the corpus and counting and dividing.
This is really cool.
But then the question is, as you mentioned before,
what if we hit 0?
So there is no occurrence of the denominator.
What happens?
Dividing by 0, bad thing.
So what can we do?
Because it might be we just don't see a certain,
I mean, the longer the n-grams go,
the less chance we have that we kind of encounter it
in the training data.
But maybe it's a valid, I'll get you, it's a valid sequence.
It's a valid sequence, but we just don't have it
in our training data.
Because maybe there's like, there is a, I don't know,
there could be a, what could be there?
A name, like a surname.
Yeah, so there's a sequence like Angela Merkel went home.
Sorry for this example.
I don't have any better.
Angela Mueller, OK, there is a sequence,
Angela Mueller went home.
And your model never saw this foreground,
but it saw like Angela Merkel went home like 1,000 times
or something like that.
But you have a 0 occurrence here.
So what can we do about it?
Somebody was, sorry, go ahead.
Add 1?
Why would you do that?
I mean, you could have like a basic, but maybe,
like a, maybe it's all like five.
You had machine learning before, right?
Or, yeah, OK.
So how, OK, so what's the name of what you're just saying?
Yeah, there's even more, there's an even cooler name for that.
I trust you.
I mean, come on, what's the name of that?
You would use it?
Yeah, it's MLE, it's, yeah.
There's, it's a different concept.
But for this smoothing, this is smoothing, it's correct.
It's also something else.
OK, good, I got you.
It's a Laplace smoothing.
And it's also, it basically gives you
prior in your quality model.
So you have prior, and this MLE is kind of posterior,
and you would kind of get like fake counts in your model.
What could be the priors?
Dirichlet's, yeah.
Sorry for dating this to, I mean, I was just, I was just
checking, sorry about it.
But yes, you're right.
What we're doing is that, well, we don't need,
we don't need a 0.
We don't like the 0.
So we say, OK, let's add some fake number, maybe 1,
or maybe something smaller.
But 1 is typically the value of choice.
So add 1 smoothing.
And we just, you know, add plus 1 here,
and here we multiply by the number
of words in the vocabulary.
So it's kind of saying, we're kind of faking observed data,
but it gives us no 0 probability.
So then, basically, our model can give us
probability for any sequence we encounter.
OK, smoothing.
Any questions?
Good.
So how can we evaluate language models?
That's a good question.
So we have a language model.
Again, what is a language model?
What is it?
It's saying, what is the probability of a sequence?
Yeah, so what?
I mean, how can we evaluate language models?
So let's say I give you two language models.
And tell me which one is the better.
Sorry, louder.
Like, an easy solution would be to sit down with people
and say which one feels more natural.
Sit two people and say which one feels better.
But the model is just a table with parameters of probability.
Let it generate and tell us which one feels better.
But what if they generate different texts?
Then we can generate a lot of texts.
Do you volunteer to do this evaluation?
I mean, it would take a lot of time, right?
But OK, this is fair.
I mean, human evaluation is always an option.
Can we do something else than a human evaluation?
Would you like to let the model generate text?
Then we could compare occurrences of words in that text
or actually naturally written text.
You let generate the model of text
and you would compare what is generated to other texts.
Like letter occurrences, word occurrences, things like that.
Yeah, I think you can do that as well.
Yeah, that gives you something.
Yes.
So I have a list of, for example, sentences or texts
that are missing words.
And the output has to predict the missing words
and the one who is going to get the accuracy score.
Yes, yeah.
OK, you're getting somewhere.
So you're saying you keep some test data
and you will measure something like accuracy on the test data.
OK, yeah, that's a good approach.
We can do something even simpler, I would say.
And we can split a data set into,
so there's a fancy word for evaluating language
models called perplexity.
But basically, let's have like n sentences in a test corpus.
So we have training corpus and you learn the probabilities.
And then we have test corpus of n sentences
and each of them has a uniform probability appearing 1 over n.
So we have sentences and they are uniformly
distributed in our test corpus.
So this is one kind of assumption.
Then, if you remember from last lecture,
cross entropy, if you don't, this
is a formula for cross entropy.
So it's a logarithm of our 1 over probability
from our model times the probability of the truth.
So the truth here is the 1 over n.
So this is this one.
And the logarithm is 1 over the probability of the sentence
assigned from the language model.
So this is what the language model is saying
is the probability of our sentence.
And we're summing up all these sentences.
So again, we have n sentences in train data
and we go through all of them and compute
for each of the sentences the probability of the sentence
by the language model.
Makes sense, right?
So the language model is trained and should
give our sentences, which are real sentences,
high probabilities.
So what is the maximum here we can achieve
of this probability of a sentence?
Theoretically, what's the maximum probability?
It's 1.
Yeah, well, we won't get 1 because we
would have only language with one sentence only,
which is always probable.
So it's not the case.
It will be less than 1, which means, OK,
so here's a question.
So this might be maximum 1.
But what could be the logarithm of this thing?
Does it have any minimum or maximum?
Yeah, so the minimum of this logarithm
would be 0 if this were the maximum probability.
It won't be always maximum probability.
It'll be something.
So it's bounded from below.
Which means the whole thing, the lower the better.
Because we want our model to say,
yeah, this sentence is probable in this language.
It has some probability.
It has non-zero probability.
And the higher the probability of the sentence
because it's a real sentence, the better.
So this is how we are alloiting the model.
Or we're comparing two models.
And if one model is saying, well,
this sentence is actually pretty probable for this language,
then it's better than the other saying, oh, no, no.
Sorry, this is not a sentence of this language.
Why?
Because these sentences are actually
real sentences from the language.
Because they are in our test corpus.
So everybody's with me so far?
Great, we're going to do a little bit
arithmetic operations here.
So what we're going to do is to plug the 1 over n
before the sum.
And the rest is remaining.
And the next, what we can do is just
get rid of this ugly fraction in this logarithm.
So what is the logarithm of 1 over something?
Not you, not you.
I know you know.
OK, so what is this?
It's a negative, yes.
OK, so we have this negative.
And we've seen this before.
This is the cross entropy.
Yeah, this is what we had last time.
This is the cross entropy we had last time.
Basically nothing new.
And then we turn it into perplexity as the power of 2.
So 2 power cross entropy is basically
perplexity of language model.
So typically you see this in a textbook.
And so this is ugly formula.
I have to remember.
2 power, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
No, it doesn't mean anything.
It's just a cross entropy and it's 2 power.
OK, yes.
Why did you say 2 to the power?
2 to the power?
Because number of results is 1 to the power of 5.
No, there is a meaning which I forget exactly.
So there is a meaning why 2 to power,
it tells you exactly how many different words kind of.
I'm not sure.
I have to double check that.
But there is a meaning why you can use basically
a cross entropy.
But the perplexity has a meaning in the count
of the different words which you kind of expect
on each position.
Something like that.
But I'm not 100% sure.
But it is a meaning, like interpretation wise.
Any questions?
Yes.
Maybe we need to test for wrong sentences as well,
because that would just require very little language.
Yeah, wrong sentences, how you test for wrong sentences.
So we have to create wrong sentences.
Yes.
The same.
Yeah, you typically do.
Typically, you don't do that.
Because for training this language model,
for counting and dividing, what you need?
Do you need any training data?
So what's the training data?
What's the training data for training this language model?
So again, counting, dividing.
Let me come here.
What do you need for this?
A lot of sentences.
Yes.
Do you need anything else?
So compared to, for example, sentiment analysis or machine
translation, what do you need for this?
So do you need any labels?
No.
Do you need anything else except for a raw text?
We just need the raw text.
This is great.
We just take a plain text and cut it into chunks,
and then counting and dividing.
That's all we need.
We basically, we don't need any human intervention here.
We just take a text as it's written,
and we're counting and dividing and learning a language model.
This is great.
So then we also take it for, we take
another part of the corpus, which is kind of just
a free text, like news part, whatever you find on the internet,
and run it on there.
So we don't really core up the sentences for a language model.
At least it's not typical.
Maybe somebody is doing that.
I don't know.
OK, great.
So we have language models.
They're great.
So we have these are N-gram classic language models,
counting and dividing probabilities.
What are the shortcomings?
OK, shortcomings of N-gram language models,
we have one already.
I'm going to reveal it right away.
So all these long range dependencies, we need to see.
So for example, to capture dependency
between the next word and the word 10 positions back,
we need to see a relevant 11-gram in the text.
So we need to see the exact sequence of 11 tokens,
which you will rarely see.
Why?
Because it's just extreme.
Because you need, if you have 7,000, sorry,
50,000 huge vocabulary.
So we have 50,000 positions or 50,000 options at first,
times 50,000 in the second word, times 50,000 in the third word,
times 50,000 in the fifth word, and so on.
So it's basically exploding.
The space of possibilities is just endless.
So to see a particular 11-gram, it's almost impossible.
Super unlikely.
So yeah, that's, if you need to model this,
we're kind of, we're screwed.
So this is one thing.
Another is, it's kind of like lack of generalization
across context.
So for example, if you observed during training
black car and blue car, it does not
influence our estimates of the event red car
if we haven't seen it before.
So it doesn't generalize around context.
There's no, these are just categorical kind of things,
and they have no notion of similarity.
So they don't help us in estimating
other things that are related.
OK?
Great.
So we're moving on, and what could be better
than counting-based language models
will be narrow language models, obviously.
So what we want to do is, again, the same thing.
Given a previous context, previous words,
we're going to get a probability distribution
over the next word.
We want to find what are the probabilities of each word
from vocabulary for the next word given the previous ones.
OK, so we can build a neural network for this, right?
Why not?
So the input will be the k-gram of the context,
so the words w1 to k.
And the output is the probability distribution
over the vocabulary, v, for the next word, wk plus 1.
OK?
Everybody's with me on it?
This is kind of crucial, so I'll give you
some time to think about it.
Any questions?
Yes.
It doesn't have to do anything with the weights
in the network at all.
It's just saying, if I have the output of the network,
so there is a network, and there is coming
a vector of size of the vocabulary,
and I'm going to put probabilities for each
of them, and I'm going to put the probability
distribution over the word, right?
And they all sum up to 1.
That's it.
And this is just what I'm predicting, basically.
So I have a question.
I don't know if you have the word, the probability
distribution, the next word, so how about the QNN
tolerance condition, conditional probability,
or just in general?
In general.
Well, it is kind of conditional probability.
You're right.
It is kind of conditional probability.
I want our model to make this probability of k plus 1
given v to k.
Yes, that's what I want our model to do.
How the model is doing that, it's my decision.
I can train n-grams by counting and dividing,
or I can say, well, let's build something more complicated
like neural network as long as it takes the input
and produces the output.
It's kind of like interface.
And I'm changing implementations.
Like one is n-gram, and one is neural.
Eventually, all of them produce this kind of distribution
over the vocabulary.
OK?
For the labels, we just do as we did before.
We just cut a part of the data and saying, well,
up until here, sorry, from your perspective,
so left to right.
So up until here, this is the context, and this is the label.
I'll come to that later, how to train it.
OK?
Any other question?
OK, great.
So we're going to build a neural network.
So then there will be some interesting thing
in the network.
And this is like, I want to spend, again,
like two slides on that.
This is the embeddings, embedding layer.
So we talked about it last time and today as well.
And I'm going to show a clear example of that, hopefully.
So our input are categorical features, right?
Because we have words, and we represent them
with one-hot encoding.
So there are categorical features and just zeros,
and there's one.
And there's zeros, and there's one.
And they have no notion of distance and so on.
So for example, words from a closed vocabulary.
It is very common to associate each possible feature,
so each word in the vocabulary, with a di-dimensional vector
for some dimension.
So maybe, I don't know, maybe in 50 dimensions or 100
or even 1,000.
But something smaller than the vocabulary,
because the vocabulary size is typically bigger than 50,000
words, roughly.
And what we're going to do is, we're
going to take these vectors for each word.
So each word is associated with a vector, right?
And these vectors are also parameters of the model.
And we can train these parameters jointly
with other parameters.
So basically, we stitch these vector embeddings of words
into the network, and they will be
trained as any other parameter.
And then, how can we map this symbolic feature values,
for example, word number 48, to di-dimensional vectors?
This is basically by performing a lookup layer,
or embedding layer, lookup layer.
So the parameters in this embedding layer
are the matrix W, which is the size of the vocabulary,
times the dimensions of the embeddings.
So for example, this would be a matrix W.
And here, this is the size of the vocabulary.
And this is the dimensionality of the embeddings.
And then, we're saying, for example,
so the indexing is for word at position 48.
I'm just going to slice here at position 48.
I'm just going to take this row.
And this is my representation of the word at position 48,
which might be a word cat, for example.
And I'm using this kind of slice by picking up
from this matrix.
So everybody's fine with this notation?
Like, this is slicing in Python, or in NumPy.
Everybody is familiar with that?
I'm saying this row and all the columns.
And also, we had before, if the symbolic feature is
the encoded as one vector, the lookup operation
can be implemented as size as the multiplication x times e.
Oh, sorry.
This is not matrix W. It should be e.
But anyway, W or e.
So it's the same thing.
OK?
So the matrix, this is one matrix.
So e.
And if I have one odd vector, how does it work?
So I have one odd vector here.
This would be the word.
And at position 48, there is one.
So if I multiply this with this matrix, what I'm going to get
is the 48th row.
It's a lookup operation by multiplication.
Does that make sense?
OK, good.
So what if, so OK, embedding layer,
how does it look in the model we had before?
So let's make it very explicit here.
So so far, before we had this thing.
So this was our multilayer perceptron.
Everybody's with me.
So input features, first layer, then second layer, and output.
Or this would be like the hidden layer, and output layer,
and the loss, and the examples.
OK, so this is, we've seen it before.
So now what we're going to add is a couple of operations.
So for example, this is a network
which takes three words.
And the embedding size is 50.
So here, I'm having three inputs.
And the examples here are the black dog.
And for each of the words, I'm going
to look it up in the embedding matrix.
So the lookup operation is basically
what we had on the previous slide.
So it's the multiplication, or just picking up
the row of the matrix, or multiplying
by the one of the vector.
So from this matrix set of parameters,
I'm going to look up the embedding for the word V.
So the output will be a vector of size 50,
because I have 50 is the dimensionality of embeddings.
I'm going to do the same thing for the black.
So I have another vector here of size 50.
In the dog, I have another size of 50.
And I'm going to concatenate them together.
So concatenation, what was that again?
So I'm basically stacking them up for each other.
So making this one vector of size 150.
So this is the output of the concat.
And then the only thing I'm doing,
just putting two in this multilayer percentile,
nothing else.
I created basically from three words concatenated embeddings
of three of them.
Any questions?
Oh, a lot of.
That's great.
So this is important.
First, second, third.
OK, start.
In this picture, is W also the same than E?
No.
So in this picture, no.
OK, so here W was a generic parameters.
And the E was the embedding matrix.
So this could have been also E here.
This would be better maybe.
But here, these are different parameters.
So E is a matrix here.
And these are weights and biases here.
You were second.
I hope you understand that by converting to real numbers,
you get told that the important ordering on the embedded
embeddings, you can just avoid this by concatenating?
Or?
OK, here, there's an ordering of these words.
So this is the first.
Yeah, OK, I didn't say that.
So this is like word one, word two, and word three.
So there's an ordering.
So if you concatenate them after each other,
it naturally makes sense.
First word, second word, and third word.
Good.
And our question was, yes.
Yes, so where the embeddings?
So this is an operation.
So there is no parameters.
But the parameters is the matrix E.
Exactly, where does it come from?
That's a great question.
So you can train it.
As any other parameters here, you
start with some random initialization.
And let your model do, I mean, this model is done.
We don't know what the model is doing.
But it will be doing something.
And through backpropagation, you will learn some embeddings
as well.
Yeah, so this is the idea, exactly.
Yes.
So can you explain the embeddings by the things
like what are the things that people are
going to see if there's a 50 or 100?
Like the dimension of the embedding, it's, OK,
so it's black magic.
Black magic in terms of hyperparameter.
So it's like empirical kind of constant you set up.
It's like learning rate or number of hidden layers.
So you say embeddings should.
So the standard embeddings from, for example,
Word2vec, which we'll be talking later on, is 300 dimensions.
Why exactly 300 dimensions?
Why not 256?
It would be much cooler.
So there is no clear value of that.
Yes.
When, I mean, it's about a slide ago.
But we had the embedding with the languages.
In that one, every column corresponded to a language.
But is that instead of the embedding dimension one?
No, no, no, it was the embedding of dimension six.
I remember what you mean.
Should I go back?
Or yeah.
But the question is, is it OK?
Yeah, the embedding dimension was six.
But it was six in the context where each column was
corresponding to a language.
Right.
But then how?
What is it here?
No, no, no, I know what it is.
Actually, it's just about that.
If there are six columns and for every column
it's a language, then for every language,
it's the embedding dimension is one?
Or is it still six in some way?
Well, here we take, so we can look at it.
So OK, so there is a mapping from words to languages.
And we say you can look at this matrix from different angles.
If you look at this from the columns,
then each language is represented
as a column in this matrix.
And it has some properties.
So you can maybe cluster languages together.
If we look at rows, then each of the words
has a representation distributed across these languages.
And you can also find maybe similar words
because they behave similar in all these languages maybe.
Yeah.
But here we have exactly what these columns are.
We know exactly.
And there are six of them because it was just
one layer linear model.
Here, we have 50 dimensions.
And we have no idea what they mean.
They're mapping basically the one-hot vector
into something which is a hidden layer representation, which
will be again mapped here to something else
and then projected to our kind of linear space at the end.
So for each row, for the other, is for each row,
zero all over just the language and then just a number
for the language that they were?
No, no, no.
It's some real numbers.
OK, so it's still a six vector.
Yes, yeah, yeah, yes.
Exactly.
Yes, it's just a real numbers vector,
which kind of gives you like different properties
of this word in different languages.
But here, we are projecting a word into a dimensionality 50
without actually saying what is in these dimensions.
We don't say what is there.
It should learn something, right?
Any other questions?
OK, so I have a question.
We said everything has to be differentiable.
So how do you differentiate it?
What is the partial derivative of lookup or concat?
I mean, concat is maybe the English word.
Part of the network, or we can just
differentiate it as we do with other layers.
Exactly, yeah.
You will differentiate.
You need partial derivatives of the function with respect
to the children or the arguments.
Yeah, but if this is like x squared,
then you know what's the derivative.
But what is a lookup?
What is the partial derivative of lookup?
It's kind of tricky, because it's
not a mathematical function.
It's just a kind of function.
Yes?
You said that lookup is x times our embedding matrix.
So this is just a collection.
And you can differentiate it.
Exactly.
It's like basically will be 1 for one of the rows,
and 0 for the other.
And that's fine, yeah.
Exactly.
Yes.
I have to check the case of trying to adjust the weights
with this w to do this.
So why would we need the-
But how do you know you will update?
What is your L to maybe here?
And this would be at position 1 and 3.
This is what you need to know in order to update the matrix.
Sorry, not W. Excuse me.
I'm coming back.
Matrix E at position 2 and 4.
How do you find this partial derivative?
Because you need this partial derivative in order
to update this matrix at E.
So you want to update E?
Yes.
You want to learn it, actually.
You want to learn these parameters.
These are trainable parameters.
So apparently, it's like-
It's given.
It's static.
Yeah.
It can be, but you can learn it.
And it's maybe better to learn if you don't have anything
to start with, you want to learn it here.
So this is like trainable parameter.
And then you basically need to find this derivative.
And it's just basically using the derivative
will be 1 for the particle input.
You had a question?
I have a question.
That is, you said, like, we have the tool.
And based on it, we know which row we should select.
And then this is the part of the data that would be trained.
Exactly.
Yes.
OK, are we good?
Sounds great.
So back to the narrow language model.
So we want to build some prediction of probability
distribution over the vocabulary for next word given
the previous words.
So then we're not going to do some-
Well, we're going to use some very similar architecture,
even like the same architecture as here.
For each word, each input word is
associated with the embedding vector
through this V function mapping.
So it's going to be VW now is a word embedding dimensality.
And we're concatenate for each of the word.
We're going to concatenate it in this vector x.
So for each contextual word from 1 to k,
we're just going to stack them together after each other.
So this is basically what we had here,
the very same architecture.
OK, and then we have this x vector.
So this is the projection of the features,
sorry, for the embeddings concatenated after each other.
And we're going to plug it into the multilayer perceptron
with one or more hidden layers.
And this is exactly the same architecture we had before.
So we're going to basically use this
as the projection of the word through the embeddings.
This is the concatenation.
And this is the first hidden layer.
And this is the second layer put through the softmax here.
And softmax is giving us what?
It's giving us probably the distribution
of the output vector.
So the output dimension is basically
a size of the vocabulary.
And basically, this is in equations what we had here
depicted, more or less.
So here, this is outputting r to size V vector.
And the loss is typically we're going to use,
I think I have it here.
The loss will be cross-entropy loss.
I have it on the next slide.
So this is the formalization of the model
we had on the depiction.
So is everybody fine with that?
Sounds good.
OK, so now where to get training examples?
OK, good question.
So where did you get training examples
for the standard classic language model?
We just do the corpus unannotated.
And we just simply do it same here,
like take word n-grams or k-grams
from a plain text corpus.
Like let's scrape the internet.
And we take the first k minus 1 words and use it
as these features.
And the last word is used as a target label
for the classification.
So what do we need to specify here is the vocabulary.
So we need to build a vocabulary first,
because this will determine how big the vocabulary is.
Basically, what are the units we're trying to learn?
And these are typically tokens, but could be also subword
units, as we talked about a couple of weeks back.
And we train the model using cross-entropy loss.
So cross-entropy, so we have softmax.
And after that, we match one probability distribution
predicted by the model and the true probability distribution.
Well, the true probability distribution
is just basically 0s and 1s, because we
have one encoding of the word, the gold standard word.
So this is not really probability distribution.
It's just one at the position where the true word lies.
And we are making cross-entropy.
Any questions?
OK.
So let's talk about some advantages and limitations
of neural language models.
And if you compare it to the classical language models,
like the count-based, then when we add more context here,
well, if you add more context in the Ngram language models,
you have to multiply it again by the scale of the vocabulary.
I mean, if you go from bigrams to trigrams,
you have v times v, and again times v,
so 50 times more parameters.
This is exponential growth, basically, of the parameters.
While here, it roughly goes linearly.
So if you add more context, it's a roughly linear increase
in the number of parameters.
So it's great.
So you can make maybe a larger context.
However, the size of the output vocabulary
affects the combination time.
So we have the vocabulary size is 50,000 or 70,000
because the softmax at the output layer
requires an expensive vector-vector multiplication
with a matrix, like the number of hidden dimensions
times the size of v. So if we had a matrix,
OK, hidden dimensions could be, let's say, I don't know, 200.
So we had a matrix 200 times 50,000.
Oh, that's a huge matrix.
So multiplying this matrix is quite expensive.
Yes?
AUDIENCE 2.
Is the local matrix kind of?
Well, here, you're in the hidden layer.
So you have a full representation.
And the vector is full representation.
And you have to multiply with the full matrix, basically,
because you're projecting to the vocabulary.
So you cannot do lookup here because it's not one-hot anymore.
If I'm coming back here, what's coming out of here?
So here, it was one-hot, one-hot, one-hot.
But since this part, you have basically a vector.
So you have to multiply the vector by the matrix
to project it.
So it's a huge matrix.
And then also, if you remember Softmax, so what is Softmax?
How was Softmax again?
e to the power of the item divided by?
No, no, no.
OK.
Exactly.
You have to do it.
So it's e, let me see, x i over the sum
for all i's until the size of the vocabulary.
Oh, this is awful.
Exp x i.
Maybe this should be j.
So you need to, if this is 50,000,
you need to do 50,000 exponentiation and sum it up.
And exponentiation is costly.
So that's why this is really costly.
And there are solutions to that.
We don't go into details.
There's like hierarchical Softmax or noise contrast
estimation.
I guess this one will be relevant later on for Word2vec.
But we don't talk about it today.
So there are some pros and cons of these neural language
models.
Any question or comment?
OK, cool.
So we have language models, and we can generate text.
This is great.
And you already mentioned that as a use case.
So how can we generate text with language models?
And now it doesn't matter if it's a neural language
model or count-based language model,
because they have the same interface.
Like, give me probability distribution
over the vocabulary for the next word given the previous words.
So what we're going to do is that when we start,
we start with the start symbol, s.
And we want to predict the probability distribution
over the vocabulary condition on the start symbol, s.
So OK, what is the probability of word 1 equals to something
given s or equals to something else?
And then this will be like size of the vocabulary, right?
So this will be like huge probability distribution.
And for each word, we have the probability.
And then we will, from this probability distribution,
we'll draw a random word.
This will be the first word of the sentence
according to the predicted distribution.
So how can we draw a sample from this kind
of categorical distribution?
Well, there's something.
I mean, you can take the maximum probability maybe.
So or whatever.
Yeah, you can take the maximum probability word.
Why not?
Or maybe some others.
So you pick a word.
And then you continue predicting the probability distribution
over the vocabulary condition on the start symbol
and the first symbol.
So then you're saying, OK, what is the probability of w
2 given w 1 and s and so on?
And you repeat until you hit another special symbol,
the end of sentence.
So this is something we need to put into the vocabulary
as well, right?
Because if we forget the end of sentence symbol,
then we will never stop.
So it has to terminate somehow.
And this will give you pretty decent,
I mean, depending on the language model.
Even with N-gram language model for trigrams,
it will give you plausible sentences,
plausible sounding sentences.
If you train a super, super large language model,
narrow language model like GPT-4,
it will give you pretty decent sounding sentences.
But that's it.
You're predicting the next word given the previous ones.
But it's learning quite a lot of things.
OK, any question?
Yeah.
How do you condition the model on the first and the second
word?
For example, don't you have to train a whole new model?
You're saying here, these are relatives.
So let me see.
Sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry.
Well, these are relative, basically.
You don't start.
You say the previous, I don't know, 10 words in a sentence.
It's my context.
And that's it.
You only take a limited window.
So you don't have to start.
Well, you have the same model.
And if you're generating the first word,
you're kind of putting all the sort of zeros
or some padding symbols at the beginning.
And then once you progress in the window,
you have your generated tokens already.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah.
OK.
It's also called autoregressive modeling,
autoregressive generation.
OK, another question?
Where are we?
Here.
Good.
So there's also alternatives to sampling words.
So maybe you don't want to take the most probable word
at each step, which, well, if you do that global,
it might not be the best kind of sampling strategy.
So you might want to do something like Beam Search,
where you basically generate top k candidates at each step.
And given these top k candidates at each step,
you generate another top k candidates at each step.
And then you take the most probable one.
So this is like a standard breadth-first search.
And the beam size determines how much you
need to store in each step.
The point is, when we do this, yes?
I thought we are picking random words from the two.
Yeah.
Yeah, well, picking random word, I mean, basically,
you don't have to.
You can pick random word if you want to be random.
But you typically pick the most probable one.
Where is that?
Draw a random word.
Yeah, maybe the random, it's not really.
Draw, yes.
I mean, OK.
Yeah, conceptually, if you draw a random word,
which is following some sort of distribution,
you're most likely hit those which are more probable.
But you have some randomness.
Or you can say, I'm just picking really
with the most probability, like for sure.
Or you can say, I'm sampling from top k,
like top 10 words, maybe.
I'm sampling from them, determined by the distribution.
Yeah, there's different, yes.
I mean, this is not really correct.
You're right.
Thanks a lot.
Yeah.
So and here, when we do this kind of language model,
and we update the parameters, so we propagate back to E,
then each row of these E learns a nice word representation.
And also, each column of W2 here,
it learns also word representation
because W2 is projecting to the vocabulary size.
So each column here is also something
we did in languages, kind of.
So similar.
So the matrix had six columns, and each of them
had something more language.
But we are now projecting into words again.
So each column of this matrix will have something learned
about each particular word.
And we're going to use them for word embeddings.
Which brings me to almost to the end of this lecture.
Right.
So the word embeddings.
So option A, we can initialize the embeddings matrix E randomly
and learn during our supervised task.
So this is what we are talking about.
Like, you can learn it from scratch.
Or we have some pre-trained word embeddings
from some other tasks, from maybe tasks
for which we have a lot of data, like language modeling.
And for example, we can use a self-supervised learning.
So we create label data for free using the next word prediction
objective.
And we plug our word embedding matrix
into our another supervised task.
So for example, we learn the word embeddings here, the E.
And then we can plug it into another task, which
is not predicting the next word, but maybe predicting
sentiment of the sentence.
But we are using the same learned representation,
which are kind of already giving a strong signal about the words
or the embeddings.
And the embeddings have some features,
such as that similar words have similar embedding vectors.
And we're going to learn how to build nice word
embeddings with some famous algorithms in the next lecture.
OK, any questions?
So takeaways.
Language modeling is essential part
of contemporary natural language processing.
So basically, everything we see so far,
transformers and so on, in fact, GPT,
are sort of language models.
And they're self-supervised, because we create training data
for free, just next word prediction.
And for this, we need no labels, just unlabeled data.
And these neural language models, as we saw before,
they learn embedding soft words, which
is super helpful for downstream task.
Any questions?
Sorry, yes?
So E as a metric is a word embedding metric.
Yes.
So Ws are not considered as a word embedding?
Yes, but then, depending which one
you pick for your downstream task,
we'll call them embedded matrix.
But both learn something about each word,
but they learn different things.
And these algorithms utilizing them,
they use one or the other.
What is different about what they learn?
What is different what they learn?
Well, they are in a different position of the network.
So they have different kind of, here,
you have the full context of all the words
for predicting the next word.
While here, you have just basically
the error of the forward pass and error back propagation pass.
So they have different information, like essentially.
What they learn is something different,
because it depends on the task and depending
on all the other parts.
They're not learning the same thing.
But E also takes the context into account, too.
E takes the context into account through the propagation.
It's just one word, and looking up here,
but it learns the error of the task
and propagates back through the whole thing.
And W, same, but it's just on a different place.
Yeah.
All right.
OK.
Yes, you have a question.
Hopefully.
It's different about the learnings than the training.
I think we'll talk about it next time.
It's fine.
All right.
OK.
Thank you.