And
now
we should be ready to go.
Okay, good.
So good afternoon, everybody.
Again, welcome to the third lecture of deep learning for an LP.
Today we have like, super equipment so everybody can hear me better
than usual, and I'm still recording on zoom as well.
So we just start with a, so thanks for your feedback, by the way.
And here's a couple of things I want to address.
So microphone.
Okay.
So that's solved.
If it's better.
I'm glad to hear that.
Some people ask what was the connection of last lecture to NLP at all?
And I have to admit, I didn't make it clear enough, but today it will be really
clear.
Why are we actually interested in minimizing functions and only all these
mathematical things.
Okay.
So let me just address this today.
Apologies.
Some people ask me for whether I can stream the thing like during, uh,
actually recording and live, whether I could stream it on zoom.
And the answer is not really, I'm sorry, because it's just, it's getting too
complicated.
It's like streaming, recording this microphone, that microphone and all these
presentations.
So if you can't really see what's on the screen, open up your, your slides and
you'll follow.
It should be fine, but I'm not planning to stream that.
And I don't think the internet actually could work like for streaming here.
True.
Ad-Rome.
I'm not sure.
So sorry about it.
Some people are actually thought that lecture two was either too boring or too
hard.
And it's kind of, it's really, it's interesting because that's the point.
I mean, we have really like diverse background here and what are the, what's
the required background knowledge?
And I, I can't, I can't really tell.
I mean, we need some little bit of programming, little bit of
mathematicals, kind of not be scared of math, but what exactly it
means, like which courses and so on.
It's hard to tell.
So we have a mixture of different backgrounds.
What I'm trying to is to have everyone on board, like really trying to get you on
board, even though you didn't study computer stuff or you didn't study like
deep, deep learning before machine learning and stuff like that.
So, so sorry.
I mean, you have to be selective as well.
And if it's boring, you can leave.
That's fine.
You cannot skip it here live because it's on YouTube on YouTube.
You can skip it.
Okay, good.
So there is one, one point about a life questions.
I'm asking you whether we should have, we could have like an app and maybe be like
online questions and you can address us on the phone.
It'll be awesome.
I would love to do that.
I would love to have all these questions, but I don't know.
I mean, it's getting again, a little bit complicated, like
technically it takes quite a time.
So what I want to say, if you have any questions, what, if you feel
shy to ask, there's, there's nothing like a stupid question, like ask whatever
you want to ask and don't hesitate.
It's fine.
Right.
Because as I said, like people have different backgrounds and different
kind of prerequisites and knowledge.
So feel free to ask anything.
I will leave more time, maybe on some, some detailed things that you can think
about it, but the app life questions, something I considered, but for technical
reasons and a lot of preparation time, I haven't really integrated it yet.
Maybe something to do in the, in the future.
Okay.
But otherwise I really appreciate your feedback.
So I had like 12 responses, which is great.
I would love to have a hundred, but maybe next time.
Great.
So what are we going to do again?
The title of this lecture, let me just get rid of this ugly thing here.
Get away.
Bye.
Well, no matter.
So what I, what are you going to talk about today is the binary,
binary text classification, right?
And now we're getting finally into NLP.
And what we were trying to achieve today is that, well, we're going to work
with these super example, super easy.
Well, to some extent, easy example task, which is binary sentiment
classification into positive and negative.
And if you remember from the first lecture, when we showed a couple of
tasks in an LP there was this IMDB data set.
So this is an example of binary classification.
They can move me and predict whether it's positive or negative.
Right.
And we have this, these reviews, which are either short or long.
And today we're going to learn a, quite a simple, but still powerful
supervised machine learning model, which we also know as logistic regression
or maximum entropy classifier.
But in fact, it's already a sort of single layer neural network.
So this, we'll building up from scratch really to deep learning
in NLP and the, all the architectures that are coming step by step.
So this means this is an essential and important building block
of deep neural networks.
Okay.
This is what we're going to address today.
There's one premium spot here in the first row.
If you're not afraid.
Well, you will see everything then.
And if you, if you sleep here, that's fine as well.
We had somebody slept here last time.
And that's fine.
No, I mean, it's after lunch.
Come on.
I mean, the mensa food is not good, but still the food.
So it makes your brain kind of.
Yeah.
So, okay.
But before we jumped into this task, so binary classification of movie reviews.
What are the actual challenges of a natural language processing?
And we should actually talk about them.
We haven't talked about the challenges.
Why NLP is a different from, I don't know, like computer vision.
So there is a one thing which is ambiguity and variability of human language.
So language is highly ambiguous.
If you look at this example and compare, I ate pizza with friends
and I ate pizza with police.
If they look, they look the same on the surface, but in very different things.
So there's some ambiguity here.
This is syntactic ambiguity.
Right.
So you cannot just replace one with the other and they, they are similar.
Not at all.
They mean totally different things.
Uh, language is highly variable because the core message of I ate pizza with
friends can be expressed as well.
Friends and I shared some pizza or the pizza was eaten by myself
and my friends and so on.
So there are so many ways to say the same thing.
So this is the high variability.
And we, as humans, we are great users of language, but we are kind of
formally understanding and describing the rules that govern language.
No linguistic is kind of the science of trying to do so, but, this is
a hard task, but we actually, we use language like very freely and we understand.
So what should we do about it?
Well, we have supervised machine learning.
Which is going to save, save us for nature language processing, because
the best known set of methods for dealing with language data so far, it's something
along supervised machine learning algorithms.
So the supervised machine learning algorithms, they trying to learn
patterns and regularities from a set of pre annotated input, output pairs.
So we have some pre annotated, maybe by humans, maybe just by
scrolling, scraping from the internet.
We have some data and input output.
So what, what input output will be for the, um, sentiment
classification on IMDB?
What's the input.
What is the input for us here for the sentiment classification?
Text.
It's a text.
Yes.
And the output will be yes or no.
Yeah.
Or maybe positive or negative.
Exactly.
Input output.
And we have plenty of them and we're using machine learning to, to try
to build such, um, such algorithms.
Which means that machine learning SLS problems were a good set of rules.
So we can kind of hard code it like saying if there is a word such and such and so
on, but it won't scale for this domain because annotating the expected output
for a given input is relatively simple.
So you read your review and you say like, yeah, it's positive.
Sure.
Okay.
Positive.
Uh, so it's easy to create data training data and hard to write rules.
So this is where machine learning will help us, but language is
actually even more challenging.
So it's not like everything is shiny and nice because natural language has
properties to make it even more challenging for machine learning.
And there are three points about language.
Which are hard.
So language is discrete, compositional and sparse.
And I'm going to address each of them in detail.
So language is symbolic and discrete because we have the basic elements of
written language, which are what is it?
Characters.
Yeah.
And the characters form words that you know, objects or concepts, events,
actions, and ideas, and many other things.
But these are discrete symbols, which means that words such as hamburger or
pizza, they each evoke in us sort of like a mental representation.
If I tell you pizza, it does something in your brain and you see maybe the pizza.
If I tell you men's a food, it evokes certain thing in your, in your brain as
well, but these are distinct symbols.
Right.
Well, meaning is external to them.
So they don't carry any meaning.
The meaning is interpreted in our heads.
There's no inherent meaning in these words.
And there's also no inherent relation between the hamburger and pizza, which
can be inferred from the symbols or letter themselves, right?
I mean, hamburger is just a couple of letters and pizza is a couple of letters.
But looking at the letters, you can't do anything about it.
You can't say they're similar, right?
If you change one letter, you get something similar to pizza, but it won't be that
pizza.
It doesn't work.
It's just two discrete symbols, completely independent in their form, which in their
written.
So if you compare this to, let's say something like color in machine vision or
acoustic signals, these are continuous, right?
So you can use a simple mathematical operation to convert a colorful, full color
image into grayscale.
Right.
And you can compare two colors based on their properties, such as huge hue and
intensity.
So these are continuous and they carry the meaning by themselves.
And you can just run a function on them to create something similar or something new
that you can compare.
This can be done with words because there is no simple operation to move from the
word, for example, red to the word pink.
Right.
I mean, you can learn, you can move from pink to red in, let's say, computer vision
or by graphics by manipulating the values of these pixels.
You can do that objectively, basically.
But here in language from red to pink, you just need to know and you have to look up
it in dictionary and stuff like that.
So this is like what makes language different.
This is the discreteness.
Okay.
Any questions so far?
Everybody's with me that this is more complicated than we think, like how to get
from red to pink, because these are just two different things.
Okay, great.
Then the second part was that language is compositional because we compose letters
to words, to phrases, to sentences.
And the meaning of the phrase can be larger than the meaning of the individual
words, and they kind of follow some intricate rules.
Examples, we know like multi-word expressions.
New York are two words, but their meaning is maybe more than just New and New York
together or Luke something up, phrasal words, Luke up, Luke something up is
something different than Luke something and up.
It's just different meaning.
Right.
Idioms even worse.
Kick the bucket.
Who knows what's kick the bucket is?
To die.
Yeah.
Up to die is different meaning than compositional work to kick the bucket.
Like if you, if you don't understand the idiom and just literally translate
a thing like keep the bucket.
Why?
Makes any sense, but composition makes a different sense or blue chip.
Who knows what's a blue chip?
It relates to stocks, but not yet.
This is like stocks, which are kind of safe to invest in.
Yeah.
Like the winner, like today's, I don't know, Google, maybe blue chip.
But it's not, if you know what blue and chip is, it doesn't tell you anything.
What a blue chip is together.
It's like a different meaning.
So this is the composition.
So to interpret the text, we need to work beyond the level of letters and words
and look for, the segment sequences of words, such as sentences
or even the company documents.
And we, as humans, we do that.
We understand this compositionality for machines.
It's kind of tricky.
Right.
And the last one is data sparseness because the combinations of words
before meanings goes basically to infinity.
So there's so many ways you can say so many things and we get never, never,
ever enumerate or possible valid sentences, for instance.
I mean, there's basically infinity amount of possible sentences.
Morphological language, the way you build words, almost infinity.
So there's no clear way of generalizing from, for example, from one sentence to
another, or even like defining the similarity between sentences that doesn't
depend on their meaning and the meaning is unobserved, right?
So the meaning is somehow you have to interpret the meaning and then you can
say whether sentence A is similar to sentence B, but looking at just plain
characters, well, it doesn't tell you like the, their similarity, maybe, you
know, flipping words and stuff like that, but it's just a proxy.
It's not like a true similarity.
So, and the point here with the sparseness is like, even if you
have like a huge example set, we are very likely to observe events that
never occurred in the example set.
And there are, that are very different.
So the number of combinations you will see in training data,
it's just never exhaustive enough to see everything.
And most of the time during, when they train a model.
So in the next year, you will see there's new words.
Now, no, now a personal nouns, for example, models trained before COVID-19
were very completely useless when COVID-19 hit for like better sentiment
prediction, for example, or trend prediction, because there was a new word.
Which was everywhere, but nobody knew the word before.
So it's just never exhaustive enough to see everything.
But nobody knew the word before COVID-19.
So language evolves and is sparse.
Okay.
So these are the three kind of like biggest challenges.
What makes language a little bit hard?
Any questions to that?
Or any other personal experiences why language is hard?
Whoever worked on language already.
Great.
Okay.
So let's move on.
We have the, we have the scene set up.
Now we're want to move to supervised machine learning on text data.
And now we're getting a little bit too mathematical notation because
we're going to use some functions.
So, okay.
So we're going to use scalars, vectors, symmetries.
Now here, I kind of assume you know a little bit of linear algebra.
So you know what a vector is and you know how to multiply or matrixes and
you know how to multiply vector and matrix and matrices together.
Okay.
If this is not the case, look it up.
It shouldn't be rocket science, but you just need to practice
a little bit, all these things.
So what we're going to use is a lowercase letter for scalars.
So scalar is just a number one, two, five, and so on.
We're going to use lowercase, bold letters for representing vectors.
Right.
So these, can you see the difference here in the slides?
I guess so.
Right.
So these are vectors, these are scalars.
And we're going to use bold uppercase letters for matrices.
So these two are matrices.
So matrices are basically two dimensional arrays.
And well, this is how we decided to do this for, you know, for this lecture.
And you will see many different ways of how to write a scalar, a vector of matrix.
So maybe in physics, you would see maybe something like this would
be a vector or many other things.
So this is always like complex dependent.
So we're going to use this kind of sort of notation.
And so vectors have elements in there and we're going to use this
parenthesis and the index operator of vectors of matrix that, for example,
bi here in the in this index operator is the ith element of vector b.
Right.
And the same for indexing matrices, we're going to have i and j will be like the
ith row and j column of matrix w.
So this should be standard.
Yes.
If there is, if there will be any task, like you should write a vector in the
exam, I'll make it either explicit or I just will accept like a common sense thing.
Right.
Yeah.
How wide?
I mean, if you can draw the difference on the exam between lowercase bold
and lowercase, non-bold good for you.
I mean, I'll be super happy.
Right.
The thing which I see on exams, like people really can't even write in capital
letters, even like explicitly ask.
Right.
So I'm asking for you.
So exam, okay.
You can practice for exam.
Only thing, the only thing which really matters for the exam, learn how to write
in comic sounds because otherwise we can't read it.
I'm sorry.
You know, and I put it on the first page, right.
In comic sounds, you sort of something like capital.
So you can use anything you want.
Then, I mean, we'll be explicit about it because this is like, you know, this is
saying context dependent where, where you are.
Yeah.
Any other questions to the notation so far?
Yes.
Second, all zero index or one index.
I don't think we care actually here.
I mean, we use, I think there, we're going to use like one index.
Yeah.
One like mathematical is from one.
That's a good point.
But typically we don't really care because we're multiplying them together and then
it doesn't matter if you start from zero or from one.
Okay.
Any other questions so far?
Let's move on.
So then we're going to have a sequences of vectors where we use also like the, use
the index, but not in the parentheses, but just like that.
So X one period, annual sequence of vectors, X one, X two, and so on.
So it's basically an array of vectors sources, set of vectors.
And we're might be concatenating vectors together, which will be denoted like that.
So we want V2 and this is where you take one vector and add another, you know, at
the end of the other and end up with the other vector.
Yes.
So question here.
So, and the next stop is coming to be, we're going to use row vectors.
That's a great question.
Great timing.
I mean, if you read that before, if you didn't read it before, this is great timing.
Where were you sitting last time here?
So you're the guy who always, you know, it's like five seconds before and
asking the question is coming.
Yeah.
I remember you.
This is cool.
Okay.
It looks like we practice that, right?
So like this bridge to the next topic.
We're so there's so many notations, but we're going to use, and maybe a little
bit like unorthodox, we're going to use we're going to use row vectors.
So vector is basically a list.
So here's an example of, you know, dimension five, and this is our vector.
So it's a row vector, which is simply lists or one year of numbers.
Typically mathematics, you will see like, oh, vector vector is a column vector.
No one, two, three, four, five.
And in a text you would write, oh, X T I'm sorry.
X is one, two, three friends post.
This would be like on a line.
We're going to save this effort and we're going to just use pretend
these are just row vectors.
Okay.
So this is a decision design choice we're using.
What's the, okay.
Concatenation versus two vectors.
So in the concatenation, let me just delete that.
No, no, no.
It's just, it's basically saying if you have like vector, so X one is one, two,
three, and X two is four and five, then their concatenation X one X two is going
to be just one vector one, two, three, four, five.
We just take them after one each other.
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
Any other questions to the notation?
Great.
So multiplication example here.
Yes.
Okay.
So we're going to be multiplying vectors and row vectors and matrices.
And here's an example.
So we have a vector of dimension D in it has some meaning, which will be clear
later, but you know, as some dimension.
Then we have a matrix W, which is also the in times the out.
So two dimensional matrix basically.
And we have vector B of dimension D out.
And we're going to compute the output Y, which is this, this equation.
So what we're going to do is we multiply the vector by matrix and add another
vector, okay, so in a year, the example is that for these actual numbers, like
dimension in a three and dimension now is two means that we're going to take this
vector X, which is three dimensional.
Multiply by three times two matrix, which gives us what, what is, what will
be the output of this computation?
What will be the dimension?
You multiply vector by this matrix.
So three vector times three times two matrix.
What's going to be the result?
Yeah.
It's going to be a vector of two elements.
Exactly.
And then we're going to add it to this vector and we can, you know, add two
vectors together if they have some dimension, then we end up with this two
dimensional vector while I'm using the in and the out, as you see here.
So the end will be the input here.
So the input dimension, which will multiply by this matrix to the output
dimension, which is here too, right?
This is the output of the, of the multiplication.
And then we're just summing up vectors to get this.
Any question to this, what we are doing?
Because typically, so typically you can have multiplication of
matrices the other way around.
So you would also, you can also write X is the W, the matrix times X plus B.
And I think like in mathematics, you actually write this, like you start
multiplying first matrix by vector, which is also fine, but then you have to
pay attention to these two dimensions, whether it's a row vector and column
vector, and we're using this kind of little bit unorthodox thing because
this is coming, typically this is coming in.
So this is a vector coming in.
Then you have the matrix, which has the, so in times in times out and out, and
you end up with the out dimension.
Right?
Yes.
Question.
Is it correct?
Three rows and two, because you take, how do you multiply vector by matrix?
This one with this one, plus this one with this one, plus this one with
this one will give you the first.
Then you go this one times this one, plus this time times this one, plus this one
times this one will give you the second one.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I I'm almost sure that this is correct.
Like 99% sure this is correct.
Multiplication of a vector by matrix.
And you might have different kind of internal representation of multiplication
of matrices and vectors, which is fine, but this has a meaning actually.
You have a vector.
Okay.
This is interesting point.
So you have a vector and multiply by a matrix.
What are you doing?
What is it?
You have a vector, which might be a vector.
Sorry.
Yeah.
It might be, let me just reiterate, which might be a vector in a, in a space.
And you multiply by a matrix.
What is it?
Sorry.
You were, you were first like behind you.
Okay.
Yes.
So you first.
It's a linear transformation.
Yes.
It's a.
Well, in a way.
Yeah.
But I, it is some, there is some weighted sum exactly because you do
linear weighting.
So it's the same thing, right?
It's a linear transformation, right?
What does it mean?
What is the linear transformation?
Exactly.
It's a projection.
You're projecting from one space to another space.
This is the core of linear algebra, basically.
So there's some basis in there.
And so you can go really wild about it, but basically here we have this vector.
And by multiplying by this matrix, we're projecting this from three
dimensions into two dimensions.
What could be a projection of two or three dimensions into two dimensions?
What is it?
If this is linear.
Yeah.
Like a computer game.
Exactly.
You just put like three worlds into two, two, two, you know, two dimensions.
How do you do that by projecting through a matrix?
Nothing more.
And also it's a linear, linear transformation.
So it's a linear map.
So there's some properties as kind of like the distances are kind of
preserved and scaled and stuff like that.
So that's why we're doing this.
Like we're taking it as an input vector.
I want some output vector.
So I'm multiplying by projection matrix and then something comes out.
Okay.
Great.
Any questions to that?
Sounds perfect.
So let's move on because we might have even, yeah, okay.
There's one.
We can simplify things.
So here we are going to have the output dimensions going to be of dimension one.
So we want to produce a scalar.
Right?
So now the input vector is still the same.
So we have three dimensional vector and multiply by three times one
matrix, which gives us what?
So this time, this gives us a scalar.
Yes.
Which we then add to another scalar and get a scalar out of it.
Right.
And we can kind of make it easier.
This, because this is a very nasty matrix, like three times one.
Oh, that's ugly.
So we, we kind of use the dot product here instead and transfer transform
this matrix into a row vector.
So this will become basically this.
And here we have two row vectors and this operation is the, the dot product.
It's basically taking each element multiplying together and summing up.
Right.
So the dot product of two vectors is you iterate over all elements and just
multiply the, multiply the values of the positions.
So everybody knows the dot product.
If not, then look it up, but there's nothing, nothing shouldn't
mean nothing complicated about it.
So here we say, yeah, okay, let's, you know, let's make a dot product and
to get a scalar and then there's a scalar.
So these two things are equivalent.
But this is just much easier to write because you don't have to hassle with
these, you know, three times one matrix.
Okay.
Is it clear enough?
Any question?
Good.
So these are the basics that I think this is the, the only thing you need from
linear algebra for deep learning actually, how to multiply vector by matrix.
And that a matrix is a linear transformation.
It has a meaning.
Linear transformation as a meaning.
Okay.
So then we have the mathematical foundations here, which we will need
today and let's move to supervised classification setup.
So what are we trying to achieve today?
Actually, was it a binary classification of reviews?
Right.
Okay.
So we're going to build a function around this and we're going to, so typically
we restrict ourselves to search over specific families of functions.
So something where we say, yeah, the function from the input to the output.
Couldn't be anything.
It could be something where we say, yeah, maybe just a, maybe
just a linear function, right?
Why not?
So when we restrict ourselves to sort of like a class of functions, we're
putting there some inductive bias.
So we're saying, well, only certain solutions are important.
Okay.
So let's move to a high dimensional linear functions now.
And all this is very awful slide.
I'm sorry about it, but let's, let's go through.
So what will be our function?
It will be from some input dimensions to some output dimensions.
And we're gonna, oh, we've seen this before.
So our linear function is already what we've seen before.
It's a vector times a matrix plus another vector.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this is our linear linear function.
So we write it as FX or here FX with the parameters, very explicit
here, like the, the W matrix and the B vector.
Okay.
So this is our linear function is basically multiplying a vector by some
matrix, which is a projection, and then adding some, something here, some, another
vector, okay.
Oh, good.
Everybody's with me.
Linear function.
Vector times matrix plus a vector.
It's very simple.
It's a, it's indeed a like very simple mapping, very simple function.
And here, so, okay.
We call them the X is the input and the matrix W and B are the parameters.
So we call them the parameters of this function.
And here we have put the explicit parameters here, right?
So we're saying, yeah, this is parameterized by V and B.
Okay.
So the output of this function will be something projected and little bit shifted.
And okay.
Back to the parameters.
We denote them with this very ugly thing.
So what is, what is this ugly symbol?
Anyone recognizes this very ugly symbol here?
It's theta.
Yeah.
It's a big, large theta in LaTeX.
Okay.
So this is theta.
It's very fancy machine learning, like parameters is theta.
Whatever is in there.
So our theta here, our parameters are W and B.
And now we want to, yes, you have a question.
What's the difference between the parameters W and B?
What's the difference between W and B?
Well, so they, they have different, well, they are all, both are parameters of the
function of the linear transformation.
Only they, the W, W is a matrix and B is a vector.
This is the only difference.
That's the only difference.
It's just parameters of our function.
I don't think so.
So parameters means either parametric function.
What could be another parametric function?
Well, I don't know.
Something which is not linear function.
Okay.
So, Gaussian distribution, who knows Gaussian distribution?
So it's parameterized by mu and sigma.
Like the mean and the standard deviation.
These are parameters of the function, right?
So, and then the function depends on these two parameters.
If you write the Python function, you put parameters in there.
There could be anything.
One could be an array and or it could be a string, whatever.
So it's the same thing.
Okay.
And the goal of learning is to find such values of W and B that our function
is doing what it's supposed to do on a collection of input values.
So these are the inputs and these are the outputs.
So basically for each input, it should produce the expected output.
Right?
So we want the function to take text, which is positive and to spit out positive.
That's what we want to do.
And we're going to model this with this linear function.
Right?
And we want to learn such a parameters of the function that the function is doing
or the prediction is doing what we want to do with.
Is it clear enough so far or anyone struggles with this formalization?
Great.
We're going to make it much easier in the next slides because we're going
to focus on binary classification.
So here the input will be still some high dimensional vector, but
the output will be a scalar.
So it changes our function from the previous one.
Like this W is not another matrix anymore, but it's just a vector.
And this is what we had before again, like linear.
So the product was some offset here.
Okay.
So this is our, this will be our binary classification
linear function for today's task.
So, but okay.
So for binary text classification, for text classification, our input is
in the form of nature language text.
Where do you see nature language text here?
I don't, I see X and this is like a vector.
It's kind of how, what should we do?
Okay.
Well, this is one problem.
The other problem is that the labels we are having positive and
negative are two categories, but our Y, our open to the function is a scalar.
Right?
So what shall we do about it?
Well, this is simple.
This task, we're just going to say that we're going to map
these categories into zero and one.
So we're going to say maybe like negative will be zero and
positive will be associated with one.
This is our arbitrary decision.
So it could be the way, the other way around.
Why zero and one?
Why, why, why should we, should zero and one?
Any idea why is it so?
Exactly.
It's just this convenient.
It's not the easiest way.
It could be like minus one and plus one or zero and a hundred, but zero and
one is just mathematically convenient.
So it will be, you know, it will play out easily then in the calculations.
So now we have to talk about the first problem, right?
I mean, how to take nature language text and plug it into this,
this input like vector.
Oh, okay.
So numerical representation of nature language text.
It's going to be a little challenging here.
So we need to transform text into a fixed size vector of real numbers, right?
So this is our setup.
This is our function.
Vector in scalar out.
So this is solved, but we need a vector in which is this function.
So we need, we need this thing, but what we have is the text.
For example, one of my favorite movies ever now here, see the typo here.
So there's no white space.
Jesus, people are terrible in writing.
The chef's Shawshank Redemption is a modern day play.
Is a modern day plastic and a blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And another like a hundred characters.
So, I mean, they have different lengths just to begin with.
Like one, one review is just, you know, 20 characters.
And that is like five to 50 pages long, maybe.
So we need to transfer it into these words.
We need to transfer them into the, into a vector.
How shall we do that?
So there is one, one thing we need to talk about.
And we need to talk about what is a word, right?
What is a word?
So it's a matter of debate and linguists.
It's not always clear, but for us, so let's start with some very simplistic
definition that words are sequences of letters separated by white space.
Fair enough.
So, but then this example, like dog comma dog, question mark dot
period and dog parentheses.
These will be different words, right?
If you just split them by white space.
So maybe, maybe this is not like the best definition ever.
So then let's do better.
Words are separated by white space or punctuations.
Yeah, this is much better.
So we would solve this and the process of splitting text into these
words, it's called tokenization.
So we split it into so-called tokens based on white spaces and punctuation.
And the thing is like in English, the job of the tokenizer is quite simpler, right?
So we have like words, white spaces and punctuation and you cut them
into tokens and call it a day.
So Hebrew and Arabic, anyone speaks Hebrew and Arabic here?
Yeah.
Can you split the text by white space?
Most of the time.
Okay.
So this is like, so, so, oh yeah, let's see.
So who speak Chinese here?
Can you, can you split a text by white spaces?
Yeah.
So I would say like 1% of the time it will work.
Maybe.
So why exactly?
So in China, I don't speak Chinese, but I kind of believe what they're saying
that there's no white spaces in Chinese.
So how can you split a verb?
Yes.
Is it?
Is it like one character corresponds to one word?
No.
Yeah.
It's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like,
it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like, it's like,
yeah, sometimes.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
It's complicated, right?
Okay.
So that's why.
So now, okay.
Let's, let's forget words and come to tokens.
Okay.
So this is complicated, right?
Tokens.
Um, and then the symbols cat and capital C cat have the same meaning, but
there are the same word, but depends or something like New York is two words or
one, so we're going to distinguish between words and tokens.
And the output of the tokenizer is then by definition, token and something which
is, which has the meaning and you can find maybe in dictionary will be, will be
words, but keep in mind that we will use these terms word very loosely and we
will interchange with tokens, right?
So kind of, we ignore all these tiny little details from linguistics and
say, ah, it's a word or token or tokens mostly, but the reality, the story is
just hard, right?
As we just saw.
But anyway, we want to really tokenize Chinese texts.
We want to tokenize Arabic texts and stuff like that.
So let's, let's start with it.
So let's start.
How can we, so the goal now what's what's what's the problem again?
We want to turn text into a vector.
Okay.
So we know what the words are tokens are.
We can tokenize text.
This is great.
So let's start, let's start building vocabulary.
So we, we take a training data maybe, or some other data and we
build a fixed sized static vocabulary.
And how can we do that?
Maybe by tokenizing some training data, right?
So you're basically take your training data, which is a hundred thousand
documents, you tokenize it, and then just take all words you found, put them
into a set and call it the vocabulary.
Sounds good.
Sounds good to me.
I mean, this is how typically things have been done or are done.
So the typical sizes of the vocabularies are yeah.
Roughly 20,000, a hundred thousand words.
How many words are in the language?
Like how many words are in, I don't know, uh, English.
Distinct words.
600,000.
Yeah.
I trust you.
It could be like that.
Yeah.
It could be more in like, depending on what word is, is it a lemma or is it
with suffixes and you know, things like that.
If you tokenize training data, yeah, you kind of ignore all these nuances.
And then typically you, you would pick like the most common words, like what
are, you know, for the vocabulary, like most common words, 20 to a hundred
thousand words, and then you basically maybe sort them, maybe not.
So here are just alphabetically sorted.
And this is, um, a vocabulary of the most common 3000 words in English.
And each of them is associated with the index here.
We're using one indexing.
So the first, you know, at position one, we have this word
position to the word and so on.
So this is our vocabulary.
We try, you know, we, we use it from, uh, from a training
corpus by tokenizing.
Okay.
Any questions?
So we need a tokenizer and then we can build a vocabulary.
And then once we have the vocabulary, we can take the document and for each word
in the document, we can look up a vector from this vocabulary or build a vector
from this vocabulary and combine them together.
So here's how it goes.
It's called back of words.
Let's forget about this formula first.
Let's start with the example.
So we have a sentence, a cat set.
So we tokenize it into a cat and set.
These are three tokens and we have this vocabulary, you know, 3000 words.
And there is a, a is a position one.
There's even cat position 852.
And maybe there's set a position somewhere.
I don't know, somewhere 2,179 maybe.
So now for the word cat, sorry for the word a, the first word of the document, we're
going to look into the position of the vocabulary where this word, where the word
is, so a is position one, and we're going to, we're going to put a one into this
vector and the rest will be zero.
So it's called one hot encoding or one hot vector, because there is just one, one
position, which is sort of hot, like on or one, and the rest is called like zeros.
I think it's coming from some electrical engineering, maybe the term.
Anyway, so one hot encoding.
So then we take the second word, the cat.
Okay.
And find where the cat is in the vocabulary.
So it's a position 852, which means it will be all zeros except for position one at a
five, two.
So there's, will be only one.
And the same we'll do for the set, which is somewhere at another position.
So all zeros and just one.
Okay.
So this is how we get one hot encoding for each of the words.
Any questions?
Yes.
Say again.
Like the size.
Oh, no, no, no.
The D is the length of the document.
So this is document D.
Okay.
Let me just come back to the formula here.
So we are, we are.
Well, the, the, the formula will be clear on the next page, but here we, we are first
looking in these, these vectors.
So we looking for each of the word of the document.
We iterating.
So the I is iterating over each word.
So here it will be one, two, three.
And we're looking out for each of the word, the one hot vector from the
vocabulary, does it answer your question?
Okay.
You have a question.
I don't think I understood your question.
So like, instead of writing one zero, like one, one, and two, two thousand,
999 zeros, which I just write like zeroes and months.
I just write these zeros and months.
So they just recurring to like the characters, like, you know, look it up.
Like the number.
And then you, you have, you can just a number you would just write.
Okay.
You would say A is A is one.
You would say, okay, so here I'm going to use different color.
Yes.
This would be like one, this would be like a 85, two, and this would be like a two,
one, seven, nine, this is what you propose.
Okay.
This is a good idea, but the problem is that you're putting some sort of, you're
putting this into one scale, which will make it, make it somehow ordered or
comparable, I mean, these are discrete things.
So there is no, their, their distance is always the same.
There is no notion of similarity.
While if you put them into just one scaler, you're, you're imposing some
sort of ordering of these words or, or, you know, there may be there to call
they're closer in this, what I mentioned.
How do you know?
We don't know.
So you basically start with this one open coding, right?
So this wouldn't really work then in the models we're trying to do,
because these are distinct categories.
You have to kind of put them each into one dimension.
Yes, you have a question.
One of the important things here is that the distance is always the same.
Yes.
So the distance, okay.
Who knows Hemming distance?
Well, Hemming distance.
Okay.
Very few.
So Hemming distance is basically how many, if you have these two, so
how many bits are different?
Right.
So what's the Hemming distance between these two words?
Two.
Exactly.
What's the Hemming distance between these two words?
Two again.
What's the distance between these two words?
Two.
Right.
So they have the same distance to each other.
And there is no notion of similarity at all whatsoever.
This is a feature and a bug at the same time.
Feature because it's simple, bug because it won't work as we want.
So we will find better solutions, but this is like the most basic thing.
Yes.
You just, you just proceed as usual.
You just have multiple words.
I'll get to this, the full back of words in the next slide.
Yes.
Oh, the order of words.
This is interesting.
Okay.
Let me come, let me go to the next slide and then we'll talk about order of words.
Because then the, we take the average back of words, which the first
Because then the, we take the average back of words, which the formula was,
we're kind of summing up all the vectors.
So here we say, okay, this would be like, so the sum will be one zero zero.
Then it will be one somewhere.
Zero zero.
Then we'll be one somewhere and all the zeros.
This will be the sum of the three vectors.
Right.
And we're just dividing by the, by the number of tokens here, which is three.
So here the size of the document is three, which will gives us the final.
One third, very many zeros, one third, very many zeros, one third, very many zeros.
This is the final thing.
And there's two things we are discussing.
One is the ordering of the words.
So what will be the difference between a cat set or a set cat?
This makes no sense, obviously, but what will be the difference
in the final representation?
None.
Yes.
So you basically, by this one-hot encoding or average back of words, we're just
throwing everything into one bag and don't care the, you know, which
word comes after which one.
Okay.
Is it a good thing or a bad thing?
It's a bad thing.
Well, I, I, yes, I would say yes.
I mean, it makes no sense linguistically.
Empirically, it works really well as a feature for so many classification tasks.
You will be surprised.
Okay.
It makes things so much easier because it's basically throwing
everything into the bag.
So then there was a question who asked like the repeating words.
Yes.
So if you had like a cat set, set, set, then you would count.
So this would be like the last word again, you would kind of twice.
And basically this will change to one, one over four, one over
four, one over four and one half.
Okay.
Good.
Any question to this?
Yes.
Can you work with PolyVersion in your future projects, not to
filter or, to use the olhos tool.
Because if you can, if you can, especially in the half block
of language that they need and mostly with the limited resources,
which is really important nowadays, when we're learning concepts
and things like this, and any way that you can open up different
tools to make completely different concepts, which is really
important. And then you, if New York, if New York were one token,
you would represent it as a 0, 0, 0, 0 position of New York, this
one and 0, 0, 0, 0 until the end of the vocabulary. Okay. Yes.
Yeah, I don't think you, I don't think you would, you would have
it like that. I don't think so because of the ambiguity, like
why? So the idea is vocabulary is basically to have the, like the
lowest kind of, it should be like perfect. So if you, if you go
from left to right by the characters, you hit the end of the
vocabulary of the token or the length, the longest sequence of
characters, which corresponds to the word in the vocabulary. It
shouldn't make sense like that. Okay, good. Yes. Yeah, absolutely.
The method has proven to everything, which has something to
do with linguistics, like negations. Of course I was happy.
I was not happy. Well, not, I know how would you like, you can
make an example where the ordering really makes a huge
difference. Obviously. Yeah. Negation is one of them. The
movie was good. The movie was not good. You throw it into one
and then yeah. Well, what's yeah. Not good or good. Yes.
But second misspelled words. Well, misspelled words is like
how we build your vocabulary. So yeah. So, you know, misspellings
is like, you have the same word twice in the vocabulary. One,
one's is misspelled and one is one is correct. This is a
trouble you first, you second.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. That's a, that's a good example. Exactly.
Yes. Okay. You are second.
It's imaginable that there are tokens that won't be in the
vector so that we leave out words that are missing.
Exactly.
So I didn't look it up. Okay, good. Good for you. Good for
you. Don't look it up. Don't spoil it. So there's words in
language that are so okay. Words in language are unevenly
distributed. There's a things called zip slow, which somehow
says like there's exponential decay in the distribution of
the common words. So most there is a lot of words that are
missing. So there's a lot of words that are not even
distributed. So there's a lot of words that are not even
so most there is a large sort of tail of the distribution of
rare words. So most words are somehow at beginning, they're
mostly used and there's just words that are rare. And there
are a few kind of just used very rarely, but they're there.
So this is the long tail of distribution. Okay. So as I
said before, when building the vocabulary, we use the most
frequent words and all others represented by an sort of like
unknown, unknown token. So we use you and K or maybe OOV,
which is out of vocabulary. So here are example of the most
common 3000 words, we would kind of extend the vocabulary
with this extra token, you and K would we maybe at the end or
maybe at the beginning doesn't matter. Right. So we just say
we have an unknown token in the vocabulary. And now it means
if you're trying to do one encoding and you find a word.
So you tokenize a text and there's a word, which is not in
your vocabulary, you're going to say, well, it's an unknown
word. So you're going to use the vector for the unknown. Okay.
Does it make sense? Yes.
Right. Yeah. Yes. Maybe. Yes.
Yes.
Good. No, no, no. I mean, it's really cool because it makes you
think like what, how to solve it. And this is exactly what
people are doing. Yeah. This is, this is really cool. Yeah. I
like it. Yeah. So if you don't, yeah. So, okay. Exactly. So in
the unknown, back to the problem, and then we'll get to
the solution. The problem is like a machine translation. So
we translate from a sequence of words into another sequence of
word. And if your input sequence of words, you find like
unknown word, how do you translate it? Like I, so tell me
what's your name? Luis. Okay. What's your surname?
Mulle. Mulle? Sorry, man. Mulle. Mulle. Okay. Mulle. Very
nice. Because this is, this word is not in my dictionary.
I know Mulle, but it doesn't, it's not a match. So it's Mulle.
And I would say, oh, good morning, Mr. Mulle. I want to
translate it to, sorry. Yeah, exactly. And I want to
translate it from, from English to German. But I'm parsing the
input sentence. Good afternoon, Mr. Mulle. I would take it good
afternoon, Mr. Unknown, because the word doesn't exist in my
vocabulary. Okay. So what I'm going to do, I'm going to, I'm
going to translate into, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
yeah, it's bad. So what I, what I can do is like to take these
unknown words and just copy paste to the output. It works
most of the time for names, places and stuff like that, but
maybe there's a better way. Okay. So let's, let's go into
subword units, right? So we're going to use the thing called
byte pair encoding, and there's a procedure and how to build
your vocabulary from, from the smallest units ever. And I guess
it goes really along the lines you proposed. So let's take the
words in the corpus and split into characters and we can take
the original space with a special space character, right?
So we basically split everything into characters and this will be
our initial vocabulary. So we have vocabulary only by
characters, no words. Then we'll find the most frequent pair of
characters and merge it and put it to the vocabulary. So we're
fine. What's the most common pair of tokens, sorry,
characters and merge it and take these bigram of characters
and add it to the vocabulary. And then we're going to repeat
this for a very many number of times. We're going to be
merging the most common things after always updating the
vocabulary. And each of these steps will increase the
vocabulary by one thing and, you know, beyond the original
inventory of single characters. So we're building from subword
units and basically growing the words. I'll show you an example
and it will become much clearer how it works. When this is done
over large corpora and maybe then with multiple languages as
well, so maybe, you know, all the Wikipedia languages, the
byte pair encoding actually will help you prevent auto
vocabulary or OOV quite a lot. It's very helpful for machine
translation. Why is it so? So let me show an example.
On a toy corpus. So we have a toy corpus. It was like this fat
cat with the head is in the cave of the thin bat. And we split
it by characters and this is the white space, right? We use this
underscore for white spaces. So this is the first step. And now
we put all the characters to our vocabulary. So D H I S and so
on. And now we find the most common, most frequent, um,
bigram of characters, which is the T H. So right? T H here,
one, two, three, four, five, six. And we're going to merge
them into a single token. So we add T H to the vocabulary.
And now using this new one, we're going to merge them and
done. You basically repeat the same thing. So what is now the
most frequent bigram you see here? We have DHS one, one unit,
one token. Okay. So we're going to find, Oh, maybe a N T is four
times here. So the most common thing is a N T and we're going
to merge them again into the single token and put them into
the vocabulary. So here you see, we merge 80 here, 80 year,
uh, 80 year. And there's one more, which I can't find.
What? Yeah. Thanks. Four times. And let's go again. Okay. So
here in the next one. So this is the previous example. Now,
Oh, the most frequent bigram is now D H E. So, which is a year
and year and year. And we're going to merge them and add this
to the vocabulary. And okay. This is the next step. So we are
at the word already. You see, we are basically coming to very
frequent words based from single characters. So we're building
the vocabulary really from scratch. So after this process,
we have in the vocabulary, all these characters, right up until
here, then these bigrams, but then actual words starting to
emerge because they're very common. Yes. We have a question.
Exactly. Uh, when you, okay. I didn't put it there. Um, when
you, when you hit your, uh, size of the byte pair encoding. So
you would say I want typically 50,000 maybe or a hundred
thousand, similarly to, to the vocabulary, but now you have all
the subword in it's in there. Okay. And every question. Yes.
No, no, you keep it everything there because it happened as a
bigram in the training data. So you keep everything and you just
grow to birds, which are very common and you, and you, you
end up with birds. Any other questions? You had, you had a
question. Uh-huh.
Exactly. Yes, exactly.
Maybe. Yes. Yeah. You say like, well, I want a BP by 50,000,
maybe units. And then you start basically this process first,
second, third.
Yes. I mean, this is like, yeah, you don't care after, after you
finish this, this vocabulary, this by pair by pair subword to
vocabulary, you just, you don't need a subword. You just, you
just, you just, you just, you just, you just, you just, you
just, you don't need a text. It's just for learning. You are,
you had a question.
It might be even like whole sentences, but it's, it won't be
the case empirically. It could be like you grow that longer
over tokens that, that you will, you will end up with maybe like
longer sentences, but it's, it's not the case actually. So it's
not really the case. Maybe, maybe because you just tokenize
before and ignore the whitespace. I'm not sure.
That's, that's correct. Yeah, that's correct. I think byte
pair. I'm not sure. I have to, I have to double check. I don't,
I don't know whether by per needs pre-tokenized text. Yeah.
Sorry. You had somewhere in the back and then you
inefficient. Why?
What do you mean by a lot of space? You mean like the back
of words is inefficient because you have like a large vectors?
Yeah, that's correct. But what is large? Yeah. So sure. I mean,
a hundred thousand dimensions input vector. How large is the,
okay. Computer vision, image pixels, MNIST. How large is the
vector? 70, 80 something times 70, 80 something. So 16,000
bits or not bits, 16,000 pixels. And it's small. So it's
relative. So times three. Yeah. Okay. All the RPG. You had a
question. Yes. But yeah, yeah, that's fine. That maybe you don't,
maybe you don't need it. I mean, yeah, you don't actually need
it. Yes. You have a question.
Yes.
Whatever.
Right. Yes. It's possible that you split up words that are kind
of, you know, that happen, you know, that are often you might
end, you know, ending up splitting them. That's the,
that's the risk. That's true. But you can make it bigger. Let
me show you an example. Okay. Like a real. So here is the
byte per example train on. So this is like 49,500 steps of
BPE. And this is how you split a sentence using BPE, the
relationship between Obama and, and here the word was Netanyahu,
which wasn't apparently in the training data for BPE. But it
learned how to split it even like a little bit like it makes
a morphological sense after syllables. And then the worst,
the rest are just, you know, words and punctuation, which is
in the, in the vocabulary again.
Might be split up.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yes. Yes. Yes. But it would be the same thing
if you take like, if you take 50,000 words, like just
tokenized words and sort them, you will be surprised what's in
there. Like very weird words, because how many words you use
per day, like different words, 200, 300. So 50,000 is a lot
actually like 50,000 words in language. If you know, you know,
like learning 50,000 different words in language is quite
a lot. It's, it's really, it's a huge, like, it's like long
tail, very rare words. But the advantage of that is that you
split words that kind of you can translate them easily. And if
you know, it's, yeah. Any other question? Yes, you.
So if I understand this correctly, it's more about
like tokenization? And there's still new font-type encodings?
Yeah, well, because we are talking about like, you know,
token tokens, and you said, yeah, well, everything is
tokenized, split by words. No, actually, I mean, you need to
really, if you do something later on with, you know, we'll
see models like BERT and transformers that use sort of
input tokens, but these are subword units. And it's
important that you know, to take it into account, because you
can use these subword units as the input for the linear
function as well. You can use just very simple unknown words
as well. So this is just a different flavor how to
transfer text, which is a stream of characters into
distinct units, which are tokens. Okay. Another one here
is the so a variant of byte pair encoding is sentence piece
encoding, sentence piece, encoding, sentence piece
tokenizer. And it works like it takes actually the whitespace
also into account, which would maybe help us with the New York
thing, I guess sentence piece would kind of take a New York as
one as one token, very likely. So it adds here the underscore
for the for the white space, and then builds the you know, the
same iterative process. And then the splitting would be basically
non that's non destructive. So it's like lossless
tokenization. Because here you can reproduce this back to the
text. Here, there was some tokenization before and you
know, it's a it's not maybe one to one because between these two
words, well, there was probably a whitespace. But here, yeah,
who knows, it shouldn't be any whitespace with sentence piece.
You have the whitespace very explicitly here. So it's a
different variant. It's very popular one. So if there's
tokenization, you should know sentence piece tokenization.
Okay. Any other questions tokenization? Now we kind of
take a, you know, tangent a little bit, but it's I think
it's really important to know that's just if you cut into
words, yes.
How do you how do you do exactly the tokenization when you if
you have the sentence piece, vocabulary, for example, you
start looking into the longest sequence of characters which
are in your in your sentence piece. And in the worst case,
what would be like worst case if you have, if you don't have
the word in your sentence piece vocabulary, what would be the
worst case of splitting the text?
Single characters, exactly. Because we have the single
characters, we started with the single characters. So even like
the super weird words, you can tokenize into characters, it
will be hard time then for the models to learn something
meaningful, but who cares? So there is nothing lost.
Like this up here. This is typical to this. This is how is
byte pair pericoding implemented in the original
paper. So you would add these two special characters. These
are the word splits. So when you split a word, you add these
two ampersands here at the end, because Netanyahu is one word,
and you split it into three tokens. And you say you signal
here by this that you're splitting basically the word
into sub subword units.
Sentence piece works differently, because it it
doesn't have these, these ugly ampersand characters. It just
takes even like whitespace at the same time, you know, just
put special characters, there's no tokenization before in
sentence piece. And it's learning basically just from the
characters for the byte pair, we just we've we had to tokenize
it first by whitespace. So there is subtle differences. I can I
would I would suggest you to read this paper like sentence
this this one, this is there's very clear example how this
works and what's the difference? Okay, you have a
question.
So the two options are do this like or or just take the
whitespaces and everything like consider a token everything
that's converged by whitespace. Right? If I don't see the
advantage of this alternative.
Yeah, okay. So you don't see why this should be better than than
something else like the token, because here you don't have the
unknown problem. You don't you don't have like, you don't have
unknown, you don't have all the everything will be represented.
But I'm going to take a lot of no words and the word word. I
don't want to split it into space. Okay, I'm going to lose
more than win.
Yeah, well, in the simple example of this one of the
encoding, there's no really, I don't think there's like super
advantage of using, you know, sentence piece, and sentence
piece, tokens that I'm on their side, but then later on for, for
machine translation, for example, and using transformers,
the input will be much better, because there is some
compositional of these words which are split it, and you can
translate, you can learn something about translation of
these pieces as well, even though it's not in your training
vocabulary. That's, that's the point, like, it's shaky
explanation now. But believe me, this is this is helpful for
machine translation quite a lot. And then it has been adopted to
everything. Like sentence pieces, now the tokenization for
everything you do with transformers for a reason. Okay.
Good. So tokenization vocabulary, it's covered
every everybody's with me. Good. So what are you trying to do?
Okay, we okay, we had to transform text into fixed size
vector of real numbers. So we made it. We have now the back of
words tokenized. The tokens could be really like words,
whitespace, or it could be subword units, fine. And the
dimension is in is the size of the vocabulary, right? So it's
some people consider it huge, like 50,000 vector, but this is
this is fine. Okay, so I'm thinking what to do next.
Because I don't think we'll cover everything I tried to
cover today. But let me give a shot. Like in the next 15
minutes. So the goal, okay, binary text classification. So
movies, right? We want to what do we have, we have this
function. Okay, we know how to convert text into a vector. This
is great. We have this linear function. What was that it was
this. This is our linear function. So we're gonna
multiply the input by some matrix and some something else.
And the output will be a scalar, which is 01. Right? So
everybody's with me on that. Okay, cool. This is what we
wanted. So we have this linear function. And now, coming back
to lecture two, we're going to pack everything together. And
what we say, like, what's the only thing, every function we're
working with, when we want to try to minimize something is
that we need the derivatives, like every function has to be
differentiable. So what is what is derivatives of this function,
this linear function with respect to the parameters, so
the parameters are W and B. And this is super simple, actually,
this is our beautiful derivatives. So the partial
derivative of this function with respect to any of the parameters
is just, why is it so? Because the partial derivatives of this
with respect to W1, you treat this x1 as constant, so this
will be x1 and the rest will be constant, which is zero. Okay?
Does it make sense how we do these derivatives of this
linear function? If not, look it up from last time, or just look
up how to do the differential derivatives of multivariate
functions, and you'll find it easy. The same with what's
derivatives with respect to B. So everything else is zero and
B will be just one. Okay, so we can differentiate this function,
this is great, it will be helpful later. I mean, maybe not
clear now why, but we have a function which is a linear
function, a mapping from a vector of back of words into a
number, and we can differentiate it. Okay, cool. Now, the point
is, so we have this function, right? So this is our function,
linear function mapping, and the range of the function is
unbounded. What does it mean? Well, what comes out could be
anything from infinity to minus infinity, right? I mean, this
could be anything. But the problem is, each example label
was either zero or one. I mean, this was our design decision, we
said like, oh, let's put it, negative will be zero and
positive will be one. So there's just one and zero. The point is,
well, how to reconcile this? How to make this somehow
compatible? Because we want our function to predict something
which is either zero or one, but now it's predicting something
from between minus infinity to plus infinity. So it's unbounded.
What can we do about it? Okay, you first, you second.
You can define some thresholds, they can decide on this certain
threshold value that's zero.
Oh, you, okay, you can say it's threshold and if the threshold
is over, then you would say it's one, it's a zero. It's actually
a very clever idea. You can maybe take like, if it's
positive, it will be one, if it's negative, it will be zero.
Okay, yeah, that's possible. And I think it's actually, if you do
it like that, you'll end up with a preceptron. So yeah, it's very
clever. And same. Okay, good. Yeah, you can, you can do some
thresholding functions saying, what's the problem with the
thresholding function? It's under, there's no problem,
actually, it's fine.
Yeah, define the threshold. Yes. Okay, yeah. But if you can say,
well, it's gonna be in zero and what's positive will be one and
what's negative will be zero. Why not? Any other idea how to
transform this? Something which outputs minus infinity plus
infinity is something which is going to be zero or one. You
first, you second.
Yeah, you could add some set. Also threshold, but you could
add some area of uncertainty.
Oh, you can add area. Okay, good area of uncertainty. How would
you do that?
Maybe randomize one area. So you get some noise from data.
I wouldn't go into noise of data. I wouldn't. Oops. I would
I wouldn't go there. I mean, randomization of data. It's nice
if you do if you do differential privacy. So if you want to
randomize data, come to my group. And you know, we can talk
about randomization, but I wouldn't go there. You had a
brand new softmax. Okay, so you know, softmax already, will it
work here for a binary output for just one single scalar
softmax is something else. Well, it will work. Yes, I guess it
will work. One over it will be it will do something but maybe
not what we really want. Exactly. Anyway, sorry, you and
then I'll go over. Yes.
saturation function. Okay, what is it? Oh, yeah. So you would
somehow make a function which does this mapping by itself.
Yeah, okay. Exactly. So very popular function here is the
logistic function or sigmoid function, which is takes a real
number and outputs a real number and takes any real number as
inputs and produces exactly values between zero and one.
This is this is a saturation function is what you want. So
we're mapping through the sigmoid function, everything
into into this interval. Okay. There's other functions, but
this one is like the mainstream sigmoid, like mapping everything
into between zero and one. And it has this form. And I really
want you to know this. Okay, sigmoid, you should, you should
know, see what if you say like, I had deep learning for NLP and
ask what's the sigmoid? I'm not really sure the formula I can
look it up. No, no, no, you have to know this. Okay. So what is
it? What is interesting on this function is that it has a it has
a meaning. And I'll come to the meaning later on. But maybe the
first thing we put a sigmoid there. Okay, so we had this
output of this function, and then we put it through the
sigmoid. So what do we what do we have to know about a sigmoid
function as well? If we want to plug it into something, some
minimization, what do we need of the sigmoid? What do we need to
know? We need to know the derivative of this function.
Exactly. Yeah. So little bit of homework, derivatives, blah,
blah, blah, we end up with something which is very nice.
Actually, the derivative of the sigmoid, it's the value of the
sigmoid times one minus the value of the sigmoid. So there
is the computation will be like, easy, because you know the value
already. And there is no extra, you know, exponentiation on
whatever. So this is very nice computation. It's very
convenient. Okay, so we have this sigmoid, and we're going to
plug everything together. Okay, any question to the sigmoid
function? So yeah, anyone? No, it's clear. I mean, we're taking
everything and plug it between one and one and zero, zero and
one. Okay. And it's nicely centered around zero. And it has
this beautiful derivative, which means at any point we have
derivative. So here, the more to the right you go, the derivatives
will be zero. And here the derivatives will be zero. And
here the derivative will be roughly one and so on. So it's
nice later, you know, differentiable.
Is it computing the sigmoid function itself is being
quantified? So you need an exponentiation?
You need just one exponentiation. So what is, how
do you compute exponentiation? What is, what is, okay, what is
what is x of x? How do you compute this?
It's e to the power of x, but how do you compute e to the
power of x?
Approximation?
Yes, which is?
Series?
Yes, it's a series. Okay. So we're going to have a sum of.
Yeah. Okay. I guess it's one plus x over n, n from n is zero
to infinity. Is it somebody, somebody can look it up? Is it
correct? No.
No, wait a second. This will be a limit. n goes to infinity.
This is correct. And there's a sum and it's different. It's,
it's okay. The sum will be, what is it? K over k to n over n
factorial, right? Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So you can, you can do
either one of those. Right. So it won't be, it will be hard.
So this is easy and we have this as well. Yes. You have a
question.
Why? Okay. The question is why, why did I put t here? Right.
What is t? So I put t here just not to confuse with anything
else because it's just a function which takes real and
outputs real. The actual input will be, thank you for the
bridge, will be the output of our linear function. Okay. Yes.
Thank you. This is great. It's really like, you know, it's a
dialogue. Exactly. So here let's, let's put it into, into
computational graphs. So what, what we had so far, this was
our linear function, this vector input times the vector plus an
offset. And now we plug it into the, into the sigmoid, right? So
this will be the parameter of the, the, the input of the
sigmoid. And we can build it as this computational graph,
which was beautiful. And if this is the same, oh, actually,
this is a very same, you know, computational graph we had in
the last lecture. You basically, each node is a function and has
some, some arguments. So this is a function of the linear, this
is the linear function and the inputs are the vector X, the
vector of the parameters and here the, the offset of B coming
here and the output of that goes through, through the
sigmoid and coming out this, this Y hat. Why is it the hat?
We're because this is the prediction. This is not a true
label. True label is just the Y. This is Y hat. So it's not the
same thing. It's like the prediction, right? Oh, this is
cool. So we have this computational graph. I'll finish
in three minutes. Okay. Now what do we need to do? Okay. So we
have this output of the sigmoids and we are doing the binary
classification. So what's coming out of the sigmoids is
values between zero and one. So how do you know, like, what is
going to be zero, what is going to be one? Yeah, we're going to
use a threshold. So somebody said your threshold as well. I
mean, we have no threshold as well for the, for the sigmoid.
So we're going to say what's coming out of here, if it's
bigger than 0.5, it's going to be one. And if it's smaller than
0.5, it's going to be zero. If it's exactly 0.5, we throw a
coin, something like that. No, well, it's arbitrary decision.
It could be like greater than equal. So why is it so? Okay.
Well, let's come back to this sigmoid function, right? So here,
yeah, it makes sense. Like this is an odd function. And now
just in the middle, we say, oh, here's the cut. So if it's
larger than 0.5, we're going to say it's one and it's zero
otherwise, right? It makes a lot of sense. But now there's a
very cool thing about a sigmoid because it's not, you know, if
we had like a threshold in function, which would be like,
oh, I can use colors. Maybe here, here would be, and then a
step and here. So this would be like one and zero. Yeah. This
is threshold as well. So if it's bigger than, oh, it makes
no sense. I'm sorry. No, no, no. Let me just roll back. I'll
cut it off from the video. No, no, no, no. So this is nice
because it has also the value of this y hat as a natural
interpretation. And it's saying as the probability of
prediction is equal to one given the input x. So again, the
sigmoid output here is the probability that y is one given
x. Does it make sense? If I'm coming back to this slide, if
I'm here, it's telling me, yeah, it's like 80% probability
that I'm, you know, I'm close to one and 20% probability that
I'm close to zero. So it's like natural interpretation is
conditional probability. So the output is like, oh, given the,
given the feature vector x, the probability of, you know, the
output being one is this output. So you can use it for decision,
make a cut after half point five, or having also like
confidence of the model a little bit. Right? So if the value is
something like 0.55, the model is not really sure. If it, if it
outputs like 0.99, then the model kind of knows.
The value will be zero. So the value of the sigmoid will be
zero. Oh, this, okay. So it's coming zero coming in. So the
value coming in will be zero here and you end up with 0.5.
Yeah, that's possible. Yeah, exactly. I mean, you can do, you
can make like arbitrary choice. You say either, yeah, it's a, so
it could be greater or equal to 0.5, then it's one, or it could
be 0.5. It's going to be zero. It's up to you. Or you say like,
I can't tell you can play around with the value. Okay. Any other
question? Okay, good. So a small recap, I mean, there's more, but
it will, we'll do that next, next lecture. So let me just
recap what we had before. Oops. And there's just a slight
rush. So tokenization is tricky. Language is tricky as well. I
mean, language is tricky and tokenization is tricky because
what's a word and how do you define it? And so on, but it's
important. We learned the simplest representation as a
back of word features. So this is something you should kind of
take away with you back of word features. This is like the most
simple thing of representing language, throwing into a bag
and making vector out of it. And we learned that we can do
binary classification as a linear function of words and
the sigmoid over that. And this is something we learn next time.
Any other questions so far? Good. Thanks a lot. See you in a
week.