Welcome to Deep Learning for NLP lecture four.
And today's title is Text Classification 2.
And we're finally coming to deep neural networks.
Great, but we actually didn't really finish last time,
as I thought we would finish on time.
So let's call it a, well, I think,
let me just get it up here.
Get away.
We didn't finish the full lecture, which was basically
a glitch in the screenplay, because I
thought we should crack everything,
pack everything into a lecture.
But I guess the discussion about back of words and subword
units and so on was kind of crucial.
And I'm glad we spent a lot of time on that.
So let's finish today what we didn't finish last week
and then move on.
So where did we finish last time?
OK, so what did we do?
We did some, what was that?
Binary sentiment classification, right?
So we had reviews or something like that.
And we tried to build a classifier for whether it's
positive or negative.
So how did we map the labels, like positive or negative?
Anyone remembers from last week?
What did we do?
So we had positive and negative, but we
need numbers, because we're working with functions.
So how did we map them?
Yes?
You mean the logistic regression?
Well, the got labels in the first place.
We had a logistic regression, which was part of the model.
But what did you do with labels, like positive negative?
You did one and zero.
Yeah, one and zero, exactly.
So zero for negative, one for positive, arbitrary decision.
This is great.
And we're representing the input text as something.
There is a term for that.
Anyone remembers the beautiful word?
Yes?
Back of words.
It's a back of words or the average back of words, exactly.
And we use some sort of functions
to map the back of words into the 0 and 1,
which we want to predict.
So what was the function?
Anyone remembers what the function was?
It has a special name and special properties.
Yes?
We had a sigmoid function at the end of this complex function.
Not complex, complicated function.
We had a sigmoid to put everything into 0 and 1.
But the main kind of building block of that was,
we didn't have activation functions really yet, I guess.
We were doing something from linear algebra a little bit.
So what was that?
Gradient descent.
We didn't touch gradient descent at all last time.
Sorry.
I don't remember, actually, if we touched that.
We will touch it today.
Yes?
Yeah, the threshold function was kind of a sigmoid function.
Like sigmoid is mapping anything from minus infinity
from infinity to these two.
Yes?
Yeah, we had this linear transformation.
Exactly.
So the core was the linear transformation or projection,
linear projection.
Yes, come in.
We have, again, premium seats in the first row, last row.
So it was the linear transformation, exactly.
It was the main building block for taking
the back of words or the vector and map it
to some low dimensional space.
So the linear function and then followed
by the sigmoid function to map an arbitrary range from minus
infinity to plus infinity into numbers between 0 and 1.
So here's the thing again.
So we had this, the x was the vector of these back of words.
And we had this weight vector, basically, in this case.
This is the bias.
And we squeeze it through the sigmoid function
and get the final prediction, which is
a number between 0 and 1.
And we also had this, you have a question or you're, no,
you don't have a question.
OK, sorry.
Yeah, no worries.
And this is the computational graph of this function.
So what it means is that the x is the input.
And this is basically a constant here,
because we don't want to do anything with it.
I mean, this is given.
The text is given.
We extract the back of words.
And we can't change it.
What we want to change are these parameters, w and b,
which we want to make such that what's coming out of here
is doing what we want it to do.
So for texts that are negative, it gives us 0's.
And for texts which are positives,
it will give us the 1's.
And here we have this function.
This is the linear mapping.
So OK, sanity check.
So we are mapping from large dimension to small dimension.
What is the input dimension of this function?
What is the input dimension of this x?
Sorry, what is this x dimensionality?
What is it again?
So we have back of words.
What is the dimension?
AUDIENCE 1.
One by the length of the vocabulary.
It's basically the length of the vocabulary, exactly.
So this would be the size of our vocabulary, exactly.
It's a vector, so it's not 1 times.
We don't have to make a matrix.
We don't have to make it complicated.
It's just a vector, a bunch of numbers.
And what is the output of that again?
What is the output of this sigma?
What's the dimensionality of that?
A number is equal to 100.
Exactly, it's a scalar.
It's one dimension.
It's a scalar.
So we are basically mapping from super high dimensional space.
What vocabulary size could be?
I don't know, 100,000, for instance, into one dimension.
And in this one dimension, we squeeze it
through the sigmoid function to get the decision rule.
OK, this is all good.
And I guess we had this decision rule as well last time.
So basically, we're saying what comes through the sigmoid,
if it's larger than 0.5, the result, we say,
I mean, we're basically rounding.
So if it's bigger than 0.5, it's positive.
Or the prediction is not 1.
And if it's smaller than 0.5, it's 0.
And then we have this nice interpretation,
which gives us basically the conditional probability.
So we can interpret this as a probability
of being prediction 1 given x.
Yes, you have a question?
Like, the probability of sigmoid of f of x
equals the probability of 1?
No, no.
So the sigmoid of f of x is exactly
the probability of the prediction being 1,
given the features.
I'm almost 100% sure this is it.
Like, this is a value, right?
I mean, this is something in between 0 and 1,
the output of the function.
Let's call it, we have y's.
Let's call it z.
So z is a number.
And then it corresponds to this.
Is it clear now?
Cool, yeah, thanks.
I had a typo on this slide last week anyway.
OK, good.
So so far, so good.
Everybody's with me.
Any questions so far?
This is great.
So we have a linear model, where we have a linear model
plus some non-linearity.
And we were to find the parameters.
So we want to find the best parameters, which
kind of give us the, yeah, what we want to do.
Like, predicting given a new vector or a new text,
when we tokenize it and do the back of words thing,
we want to predict what is the classified
to negative or positive.
And how can we tell the model what's, you know,
are you doing well or are you doing not well?
On these training examples, we introduce the loss function.
So it's a crucial concept in machine learning.
Deep learning is a loss function.
So basically, it's saying how much, so it's quantifying.
It's saying how much loss is suffered.
Well, it's not suffering.
It's telling you basically how much loss
we obtain when predicting this prediction y hat,
while the true label is y for a single example.
So basically, if we have a binary classification,
the loss function, which is parameterized
by this y hat, which is the prediction,
and y is the gold standard data or data point,
it's from a tuple of these two into real numbers.
So the loss basically gives us a real number.
And the loss should have some properties.
Namely, the smaller the loss, the better,
the closer the prediction should be together.
So it should be like positive number.
It should be maybe, well, it doesn't have to be positive,
but at least it should have a minimum.
And when the minimum is hit for these two things,
they should be, this should be the correct prediction.
So if, for example, y is 1 and y hat is 0.999,
the loss should be very low, because they
are very close to each other.
So any questions so far to the loss?
Like what are we trying to achieve with that?
We're trying to basically make it as small as possible
for one example.
So which means then, giving label training set.
So now this is about like one single example,
but we have a training set, which
is a sequence of n training examples with x and y.
So the input, so to say, features and the labels.
And we have this notion of loss per instance
and parameterized function fx.
So what is our parameterized function fx again?
Oh, parameterized functions looks terrible.
What is it again?
This is our linear function and the sigmoid.
So this is the function we're mapping the input
to the output.
We define then the corpus y loss.
So it's basically for all training data
with respect to the parameters, theta
is the average loss over all training examples.
What does it really mean is that, it's
very simple at the end, we iterate
through all the examples in the training data.
So we have n training examples and we iterate through all
of them.
And for each of them, we compute this per instance loss.
So basically what is here is the prediction, so y hat.
And this is the got label for this if example, if example.
And we compute a loss.
As in the previous, what I showed, like 0, 1 and 0, 9, 9,
9 would be like per example loss.
And then we just sum them together
for the order training data and take the average.
So this is the average loss per corpus.
Any questions?
OK, this is great.
So we have a loss.
And we say the smaller the loss, the better we kind of
mimic the gold standard labels.
So does it ring a bell?
What should we do?
Why do we care about the loss actually?
Why is it important?
Why do we need to have some function as a loss
over the training data?
We can minimize it.
Exactly.
We want to minimize the loss.
We want to make the loss as small as possible
on the training data.
OK, this is a great question.
So we want to minimize a function.
Does it ring a bell now?
Can we minimize a function?
We can use the gradient descent to minimize a function.
This is great.
OK, cool.
Wow.
We talk about a lot of functions.
And last week, we talked about all the linear functions.
What do you have to know?
What the properties all the functions
must have in order to be kind of minimizable the way
we know with the gradient descent?
So all the functions must be continuous.
And then we can minimize the function.
OK, so we can minimize the function.
Or continuous, yes, which kind of is a different term
for being differentiable.
They don't have to be continuous because you
can make exceptions.
But they have to have derivatives
with respect to everything what's coming in.
Because if we know the derivatives,
we can compute what?
The gradient using the very famous technique of?
The back propagation, the chain rule, the back propagation.
Exactly.
And now we say, oh, OK.
So I can actually use back propagation
to compute gradient over all my training instances.
And through doing this, I will minimize my loss function.
Wow.
This is great.
This is machine learning.
Basically, this is it.
This is deep learning.
One thing we need to talk about, what is this loss function?
Yeah, what is it?
This is very abstract.
What is dl?
I have no idea.
We'll talk about it later on, typical examples
of the loss functions.
But so far, so good.
So we can take the loss function and take
training as optimization.
So this is the loss, very fancy l here of the theta,
very fancy terms for parameters.
I mean, so the question here is, is it OK,
like so many mathematical terms or not?
I mean, do you like it?
Do you hate it?
Or it's fine?
Who hates it?
Who hates slides in LaTeX with mathematics?
That's fine.
I mean, raise your hand.
I'm really curious.
I like to write it.
I like the way it looks in LaTeX, actually.
So I like writing it.
It's really like, I do research for writing papers in LaTeX.
OK, I shouldn't put it on record on YouTube, but it's true.
OK, so I mean, you can describe it in many different ways.
But the mathematical formulation is kind of,
it could be precise most of the times.
But we're misusing notations here.
But anyway, so everybody's fine with that?
Everybody understands what we're talking about?
I'm trying to take it as also explaining
like what all these things are.
OK, good.
So we have this loss for the training data set
with n examples.
And the training examples are fixed.
So this xy are given, and the yi's are also given.
And we want to set the values of the parameters.
So no matter what it is, it would be typically
the w's and b's, such that the value is minimized.
So the final formal kind of definition
of this minimization would be, we
want to find such parameters with this tiny hat.
So the hat is like, it's not the truth, but sort of almost.
We're trying to predict.
As the minimum of these parameters,
so where this complicated function,
this is a complicated function, right?
This is a really complicated function, actually,
because it's an average of a sum of a loss of,
here will be a linear transformation
through sigmoids.
So it's kind of complicated function,
but we can still work with that easily.
And we want to find such parameters, such data,
that this function will be at a minimum.
Whether it's global minimum or local minimum, it's a question.
Typically, global minimum is great,
because then we really know we're at global minimum.
If we have the function, if they are fully convex,
you can find, so it's like a bowl,
you can go to the minimum with stochastic gradient descent.
But deep learning of deep networks are not really such.
So they're kind of very nested functions,
and you will mostly reach a local optima.
But this is good as well.
So this is what we're trying to achieve.
So we want to minimize the function.
And we use the techniques we know already.
This is great.
So now coming to the question, what
is this loss, what is this thing?
So let us show a simple loss called the logistic loss,
or also binary cross entropy.
And this is something you should know, OK?
Even like the formula, you should kind of
know, because this is so central to many things.
It looks complicated, but it's not,
because we will show later.
It's coming from actually a concept from probability
theory, from KL divergence between two distributions.
And it's just one kind of incarnation
of that for the binary task.
So we're taking these y's.
OK, sanity check, what is this y?
What is this?
The true label.
Thank you.
What is this y hat?
Yes, again.
The predicted label.
Second?
Exactly.
This is what's coming from the network.
OK, so this is logistic loss.
And in order to optimize this function,
we need to have, again, one thing.
Every function which we plug into the complex functions,
the complicated functions, we need one thing
to work with that, with stochastic gradient descent.
What do we need?
It's a nice function, but it's not complete for us,
because if I tell you, implement it in your network,
you're missing one part.
What do we need?
We need a derivative, exactly.
So what is the derivative of this function with respect
to the y?
No, y hat.
I'm sorry, y hat.
This is the input, because this is constant.
So what is the derivative of that?
I don't know.
I look it up, to be honest.
I was too lazy to kind of compute by hand.
But at the end of the day, it's because
of all these logarithms.
So it's kind of nice.
It's basically this kind of fraction.
So you don't have to remember this derivative.
If you're stranded on a desert island,
you would come up with this derivation
if you really have to build a neural network there
by your own order.
So I'm just saying, well, it's a nice function.
The derivative is not really complicated.
So we have the derivative of this logistic loss.
Great.
So now coming from the conditional graph we had so far,
now we have the full computational graph.
So again, this is the input.
This is the parameters, w and b, so the weights and the bias.
And then we have this linear function.
What is this sigma again?
Yes?
The sigmoid.
Sigma sigmoid.
OK, good.
It's a good hint, exactly.
So it's a sigmoid.
And then we have this loss function.
And the loss is taking the prediction
from this function and taking also the gold standard label.
So and now I already kind of revealed the secret here.
How can we minimize this function?
OK, any question to this computational graph?
Is it clear for everybody?
It's very simple, I would say, but it's a building block
of, I would say, deep learning.
So if you see a neural network, you
would see something like a graph,
but in very many different flavors.
So I'm using this kind of very simplistic
function-oriented graph.
But I guess it's clear.
Any questions?
Good.
So we minimize this function by gradient descent
and back propagation.
And now we're coming to a very famous kind of algorithm
for training these models.
Although this is not, well, this is still not
like a deep learning model.
It's like one layer binary predictor,
so logistic regression in a way.
But we're going to use this stochastic gradient descent,
so online stochastic gradient descent.
OK, so this is something which looks maybe a little bit
complicated, but let's have a look.
So what do we need for this function,
for the stochastic gradient descent?
Again, we need the function which
takes the input and the parameters
and produces the output.
Well, what is this?
This is the training data, right?
So we have n examples and n labels.
And we have this L. This is the loss function.
Loss function, OK.
So and then we're going to do with,
as in the standard kind of minimization,
we had it with just simple functions, not
these complicated graphs.
We're going to continue while something,
while we're still going lower, lower, and lower.
So maybe a number of steps or just we don't,
we hit some local minimum and we stop.
So some stopping criteria are there.
What we're going to do is we sample a training
example from the training data.
So we sample, we just randomly choose one.
And then we're going to compute the loss on this example.
So what is this loss computing?
What is the output, again, of this loss?
It's going to give us a number.
Loss is giving us a number.
It's a number, right?
Should be positive real number.
And then having computed this number, this loss,
we take our computational graph and compute
the gradient of this loss function with respect
to all these parameters.
What does it mean exactly is, let me come here.
So we run this sort of forward pass
where we compute a loss.
So we have this loss.
So everything is computed.
We know all these values of all these nodes.
This is very similar to what we did
with the computational graph in the second lecture.
Looks maybe more complicated, but it's the same,
conceptually, the very same thing.
So we compute all these outputs.
And then we're going to start from here and ask, OK,
what is the gradient of L with respect to L is 1.
So this is how we start.
And then we're going to come back.
What is the gradient of L with respect to sigma?
L with respect to sigma.
And what is the gradient and so on, so on.
And we end up here when we do this back propagation,
basically.
We end up here with, what is the gradient of L with respect
to b.
And here we'll end up with, what is the gradient,
partial derivative, the gradient of partial derivative,
the same thing, of L with respect to this vector,
so each of these things.
And this is what we want.
We want to find the partial derivatives or the gradient
with respect to these things.
We don't care about the input.
It's a constant.
We don't change the input, obviously.
We only care about the train of parameters here.
So the first forward pass shown here, we compute a loss.
And by doing computing the loss,
we compute all the outputs intermediately.
And we store them in the nodes.
And then for the back propagation,
we're going to reuse them for computing the gradient.
So once we get the gradient, which is basically
a vector of partial derivatives.
So this gradient is kind of nothing else than 2b.
And then this partial derivative with respect to w1.
And w2, and so on.
So these are the parameters.
These are all the dimensions we get.
So we're in highly dimensional space.
And now we're going to take a step
in the opposite direction of this gradient.
So this gradient, it's actually, this
is how we denote them.
But in reality, these will be numbers.
This will be a vector of real numbers.
And the gradient size, so the gradient is nabla.
So the gradient size is the number of these w parameters
plus 1, which is the bias.
So this is the number of, this is the size of the gradient.
And this is the multidimensional space of the parameters
when we are moving ourselves.
Once we compute this gradient, we take this eta.
Is it eta?
Yes, I guess so.
Eta, which is the, what is the eta again?
What is this thing we're multiplying the gradient?
The learning rate, exactly, the learning rate.
Thank you.
We multiply the gradient, which is a bunch of real numbers.
And we moved the parameters, which
is, again, a bunch of numbers somewhere else,
where we get smaller loss.
And repeat until we can't do anymore.
So I'll let you digest it, and if you have any questions.
Great, any questions?
Yes.
What does online mean?
Online, OK, this is a great question.
Let me, thank you.
Any other questions before I answer online?
So everybody is happy with it?
Yes.
Why is it in the form of a vector?
Oh, yes, so why is it in the form of a vector?
It's just a bunch of numbers.
It doesn't matter.
So it's the gradients.
I mean, if you look at it like that,
they are kind of separated, because here you have,
oh, you don't see, OK, sorry.
Like that.
You have the, so this is a matrix.
This is a number somewhere in your code somewhere.
More than.
This is a vector.
This w is a vector, because you're
multiplying vector by vector, a dot product, and plus b.
So these are somewhere, but in fact,
from the mathematical perspective,
you're minimizing a function in dimensions
which corresponds to the number of the parameters.
Because if you minimize one-dimensional functions,
as function as we did before, you
minimize in just one, basically, one direction you find it.
If you have like, what is it, banana function
was two dimensions, and you find a minimum in two dimensions.
Here you have w plus 1 dimensions,
and in that, you're finding the minimum.
You're finding the spot of these parameters
where the loss will be minimal.
So it's a kind of large number of parameters.
And you can see it as a vector in this high dimensional space.
At the end of the day, it's just a bunch of numbers.
OK, yes.
What is the shape?
It's a very awful one.
So the point is, it's hard to visualize first,
because you have like, you rarely have two parameters.
This could be, well, how much parameters
you need if you have like, vocabulary of 10,000 words.
So how many parameters you will train here?
10,001.
Yes, say 100.
OK, so we have like, let's say like, 101 dimensions.
No, no, no, no, no.
So what you're plugging here is a bag of words.
And the dimension of the bag of words
is the size of the vocabulary, which
could be even if it's 100.
OK, let's say it's 100.
So V is 100.
If you multiply this with another vector,
this vector dimension has to be 100 as well.
And this is plus 1.
So you have like, 101 dimensions to optimize.
So you are in a 101 dimensional space,
finding a place in this 101 dimensional space
where you have minimum of some loss.
It's easy to visualize if you had like, two parameters.
So you have like, one word and one bias.
Yeah, so you have like, two dimensions.
And you see like, maybe the banana function, whatever.
So you can visualize it.
But there's no way how to visualize 101 dimensions.
Right?
How does it look?
So some people try actually looking into that,
how the surface would look if you project it down
to fewer dimensions.
And it's not a nice surface.
It's kind of very bumpy.
And there's a lot of settles.
Like, everybody knows what a settle is in two dimensions.
I don't have a picture here.
So if you have like, mountains here, and here is go down.
Like a settle in the mountains.
Yeah, if you go, you know, if anyone's
hiking in the mountains, who's hiking in the mountains?
Right, OK.
So you go up, you go to the settle.
And you have two peaks on the sides, and you just
go to the settle to the next volley.
So you had a settle.
And typically, also these functions
are in deep neural nets.
When you find the minimum, it's not really
like in the volley, the minimum.
It's typically some settle point,
where you have zero gradient, because it's
kind of flat on the settle.
But it's not like optimal, because you can still go down.
Sorry, I didn't get a question.
So well, you know that you minimize the loss.
And your function with these parameters
will give you the best prediction for your training
data.
And at the same time, it will give you, like,
best prediction for your test data
if they come from the same distribution.
Does it make sense?
OK, we can take it offline.
But any other questions before I hit what's online?
Let me come here.
OK, it's not the case.
If so, just, you know, you can talk about the lecture.
It's online, because here on the line 4,
we're taking a single training example.
We're picking a random example from the training data.
And it gives us only a rough estimate of the corpus loss,
because we're trying to minimize the corpus loss for all training
data.
But we just pick one single training example at a time.
That's why it's online, because you can proceed,
take out one example, compute a gradient,
do the step, pick another example, and so on.
So it could be used when your data is actually
coming online from somebody just sending you a new label data.
You pick one at a time and learn a new kind
of set of parameters, OK?
Good.
Is it a good thing or a bad thing?
I mean, what's the advantage or disadvantage
of having this online thing?
What could be the advantage?
Quick update.
Yeah, quick update.
Yes, quick updates.
Basically, you can basically streaming data.
If you have any streaming data, so you
can update on the streaming.
OK, any disadvantages of that?
It will take longer when you do the data set.
Exactly.
So mini-batch is the keyword, right?
So you've heard the word mini-batch.
It's great.
Yeah, it will take a lot of time.
Just do this backpropagation after every example you see.
Because it's kind of complicated computation.
I mean, complicated.
It's just a lot of computations.
And maybe there's a better way.
And also, the point is, you're taking a single training
example.
And this example could be kind of bad
and gives you the wrong direction in the gradient.
Because you want to go to the minimum
in this high-dimensional space.
And this particular example is kind of misleading you
somewhere else because it's just bad or somehow out
of distribution, whatever.
And that's maybe not what you want.
So instead, you can do better estimation of this corpus loss.
And you're going to use something called, right?
You can use mini-batch stochastic gradient.
So this is the algorithm for training neural nets.
Mini-batch.
So how does it work?
We have the same kind of setup.
So we have the same neural network, the function,
the training data here, and the loss.
And again, we iterate while something, something.
And then we're not picking just one example, one training
example, but picking n examples at a time.
Where n could be, yeah, something between 1.
If we had n1, then we are back to the online gradient descent.
If n is more than 1, then we get this batch.
So mini-batch, it will.
It's a batch sort of, or if it's small,
we call it mini-batch for some reason.
I don't know.
And what you're going to do here is that you compute the loss
for each example in the mini-batch, as we did before.
And then you're going to basically make
the average gradient.
So you're basically, for each example,
you take, you divide it by the number of samples
in the mini-batch.
But at the end of the day, what this thing is doing
is that we're getting the g hat is
the average of the gradients for each example in the mini-batch.
OK?
Yes?
So after the loop is done, the thing?
g hat, yes.
This is a lot.
It's like hat g.
It's going to be what?
So exactly.
This will be the average of the gradients for each example
in the mini-batch.
Why is this here?
Yeah, because it's, right.
It's a great question.
Because it's going to be, what we really want to do
is to kind of, if you program it naively,
you would collect the gradient vector
for each of these examples in the mini-batch.
You get a gradient 1, gradient 2, and so on.
And then you would do the average,
like sum them up and divide by number of them.
Yeah.
If you do that, you need n times more space
to store the gradients, right?
Because you need, well, you need a gradient
for the first example.
It's a vector of numbers.
You need a gradient for the first example here,
for the second, for the third, for the fourth, up to n.
Why?
Because I've got some gradient.
Oh, right.
You can sum.
Yeah, that's correct.
Sorry.
You can sum them together and divide by n.
Yeah, that's the same thing.
OK, yeah, you can do that.
I mean, this is basically doing it in line.
Yeah, I got you.
Overflow?
No, I don't think so.
I think it's just a design decision.
Like, it's maybe faster just to divide them
and sum them together.
But you can do it afterwards.
Yeah, sorry.
Is it summed up first and then divided faster than like this?
I think it depends on the implementation.
I don't know.
I think, I mean, mathematically, it's the same thing.
There might be differences somewhere.
Yes, you were saying?
Why is the minibatch thing faster?
You still have to calculate the gradient for each of the-
This is a great question.
So why is the minibatch gradient faster than just doing before?
Because at the end of the day, you
have to go through the computation loss and gradient
for each example anyway.
I do have an answer for that.
I'll come to that later.
Any other question?
You were something?
You were asking as well?
The same.
I was about to say that we need to focus on the migration.
Thank you for spoiling that.
OK, yes.
OK, good.
So I'm going to address this.
Any other question to the minibatch stochastic gradient?
Yes.
Which one?
The stochastic?
Because stochastic means you're randomly sampling the batch.
Right?
This is it.
I mean, here, it's stochastic because you're
sampling your- choose randomly one example
from the training data.
Here, you're sampling a batch of training data.
Yeah.
And does not have to be always the training data.
No.
And it's a parameter.
Yes, exactly.
I'll come to that on the next slide as well.
So we have two questions.
Any other question?
Which is- yes?
What's our starting weight?
The starting weight?
Where do you start?
What is our parameters?
OK, so how would you set up your parameters?
What is the W?
So you start from scratch.
What is the W's, and what is the B's?
So I would say the good default could be all 0's.
Will it work?
Actually, I thought about it in the car now,
and I think it will work.
It won't break.
I think it will work, but just the first iteration
will give you a 0 in front- I mean,
after the first kind of stochastic gradient step,
you will end up something somewhere else.
I mean, there is no local minimum, maximum
in the 0 parameters.
It's just a point, right?
But typically, what we do- so I need to double check.
I was really thinking about it, like whether I shouldn't put it
to 0, but then why not?
Typically, we sample them randomly.
Random, and there is some kind of- from which distribution
uniform between something and something?
Initialized randomly the weights of your model.
OK?
So random.
Could be- but I think 0's could be also fine.
Maybe you have 0 multiplications,
which gives you a little information
than having some random numbers, so it's maybe
better to start somewhere else.
But I don't think it will break the 0's.
I have to double check, though.
NRPS.
I don't think so.
Why should be there a 0 gradient?
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, I was sitting in the car, and it's like, yeah,
there will be 0 gradients.
No.
Why should there be a 0 gradient?
Because you compute a loss and the gradient- I mean,
show me the proof.
I mean, maybe I'm wrong.
So I would need a piece of paper as well for this.
Anyway, any other question?
Before we move to these two questions,
like what is M, and why is it faster or better?
OK, let's move on.
So the mini-batch size can be something between 1
and the full data set, right?
Typically, what's the driving factor of the batch size?
Sorry, I have a new phone, and I can't turn it off.
Come on.
Sorry about it.
What kind of drives your mini-batch size?
What do you think?
What do you- OK, let's address the second question first.
Because this can be easily parallelized, right?
If you look back, this kind of two things
are running for each example, but these examples
are independent.
And also, you don't change anything in your parameters
yet, so you can just run it on different kind of cores,
whatever.
So you can parallelize that.
If you do it very cleverly, then on GPUs,
it gives you super, super boost.
OK?
So do you also parallelize the other online things?
Do you just run single examples on different cores?
I think here, you- well, the only thing you can really
parallelize here is maybe some matrix multiplication
in the network.
But itself, naively, you have just one function running.
This is one function, so there's nothing globally parallelizable.
Well, here, you can really say, oh, this example goes here,
this example goes here, and you can compute them parallel.
OK?
And the higher values of n, like the size of mini-batch,
so the high values give you better estimates.
Smaller values, like more updates and turning faster.
There is one thing, actually, in reality
where you need to pay attention while choosing n.
What is it?
Anyone knows what's the limiting factor
of having smaller batch sizes than the full training data
set if you run this in parallel?
Let's say you parallelize everything here,
and you want to run it with n as large as possible.
Is it a hardware or a core?
Memory.
Yes, you're running out of memory.
So if your network is big, and you're
running on a poor guy's A100 NVIDIA GPU with 80 gigs RAM,
and you're running a large model,
then your batch size will be 16, 32, 64 maximum.
Because the network is just, I mean, with billion parameters,
you need to fit it in memory.
And in a batch, if you run it in parallel,
you need as much memory as your batch size.
So this is the factor slowing down.
Yes?
Is that slowing down for the end up
to other data?
It gives you, so like getting rid of settle points,
I don't know.
I mean, I don't know.
I don't think there's a general kind of rule of thumb,
but it gives you a better estimate of the gradient.
So because you're kind of averaging
all the gradients for all the different points,
so then you know much better where
to go for the better loss.
But if it's just a settle point or not, I don't know.
Maybe there's some theory about it.
But I don't know that.
I'm sorry.
OK, any other question?
Great, so we can build this thing.
I mean, we have computational graphs.
We have backpropagation.
All these functions in there are differentiable.
You can plug them together.
You can run backpropagation, and you can
run stochastic gradient descent.
So basically, nothing prevents you now
from building this thing from scratch, if you want.
OK, now we are talking about so far,
we are talking about binary classification, which
was like, yeah, 0 and 1.
But typically, the world is not binary,
or classification tasks in NLP are not binary at all.
And we want to classify maybe into distinct categorical
classes.
So for example, let's try a task of language identification.
So the input will be, again, back of words,
or back of subwords, whatever.
Maybe subwords are better, but let's take it as back of words.
And the output will be, I want to tell whether a document is
in English, French, German, Italian, Spanish, or other.
So we have six classes now.
It's a very simplified version, but why not?
For some cases, it might be good.
And we want to classify it into these categories.
And the thing is, there is no ordering of these.
There is nothing saying, like, English
should be higher than French, or whatever.
There is nothing.
There's different categories.
So how do you want to encode this?
I mean, in the binary, we had negative, positive 0 and 1.
But now, how are we going to encode this into something,
into maybe, I don't know, a number, a vector?
Any ideas?
How can we work with this categorical data?
Yes?
So just have a six-dimensional vector
as output instead of 0 and 1?
We will have a six-dimensional output vector with 0s and 1.
OK, cool.
Was it ringing a bell for everybody here?
Because we had it already.
It's similar to?
One-off encoding.
It's one-off encoding, exactly.
We had the same thing for words.
Words didn't have any ordering, and we just
put them into 60,000 big vector.
And there was just 1, and everything else was 0.
We're going to do the same thing with the labels here.
So one-off encoding, exactly.
And we're going to randomly, or not randomly, arbitrarily say,
OK, this is going to be 1 and 5 0s, 5 0s,
and French is going to be on the second position, and so on.
And the dimensionality of this y vector
is now the number of classes.
Any questions why we're doing this mapping,
one-off mapping of the label?
Yes?
Shouldn't we also set up 1 and 0 to give confidence
for every language and see which is the highest?
But this is the Goldstnder labels.
We know.
I mean, this is like how you present the task.
We're saying, yeah, this is in German.
But theoretically, you're right.
You can put the probability distribution
over these categories and say, yeah, maybe this
is like 80% German and 20% English
if it suits your use case.
But this is very simple.
And it's like hard classification.
You're saying, yeah, either or the other.
We're not talking about language flipping, language switching,
and stuff like that.
So any other question?
I hope this is clear.
This is the same thing as we did with words, one-off encoding
of the labels.
Yes?
What was the probability that there
should be texts that are exactly the same in English
and in German, the same words that you would put
for chart-off text?
How much would you solve for that?
Yeah, so if there's, OK, this is a tricky question.
So if I really want to classify text into languages
and there are two documents that are exactly
the same in English and in German,
then something is wrong with the text,
or something is wrong with my data set,
or something is wrong conceptually with my task.
So I'm not expecting that.
But obviously, there could be cases.
What's the case?
For example, if you were translating just
out of the text language, and if I put the EID in,
it would be done in English, or the actual EID.
Sure, yes, of course.
But you're translating words, which is harder.
You can also translate sentence things.
Yes, yeah, OK, sure.
I mean, this is not an easy task, right?
And mentioning a language identification is not easy,
although we think it's easy.
So there is research on that.
And you have corner cases where it will break,
because you have the same label for the same,
so different labels for the same inputs.
Yeah, so you have to take it as a feature of your data set
and live with that, right?
OK, good.
Any other question, which is not that tricky?
Yes?
Would it be possible to just use a vector with three entries
and then count up and bind it?
OK, good.
So yes, so you would be basically
mapping that to binary numbers, right?
But you're imposing them, then, some sort
of ordering or similarity, because some numbers are
close to each other than the others.
But these are distinct things, and the Hamming distance
should be the same for all of them,
because we want to map them as far as possible in this space.
OK?
Good.
Let's move on.
So how can we solve this?
OK, so we know we have linear functions.
We have the sigmoid thing.
But now we're not classifying into binary, into 0, 1, 1.
We are classifying into a vector.
So how can we solve this?
So I have a possible solution here.
And we can actually have, for each of these languages,
so this fancy L here, for each of them,
we can have a separate white vector.
So for example, the weights for French,
and we can have the bias scalar here for each language.
And then we can just basically do the same thing
as we did before for the binary prediction
and take the input vector, multiply that
for with the particle language weights and bias,
and then pick the highest scoring language.
So it would be like the maximum argument
from all of these six ones that gives us the highest
score for this computation.
Does it make sense?
So basically, we would say, well, there's no, well,
we're not saying there's only two languages
and cast it binary.
But we would say, like, there's six languages,
and each of them has a set of parameters.
And the equation we're using here would be the same.
So basically, projection of the inputs
times the parameters for the language and the bias.
This is great.
So we can basically take these and rearrange them
into, rearrange these vectors into columns of the matrix W,
which will be then, we'll have number
of rows, which is the input dimension, and six columns.
And we would get, again, linear projection.
Oh, this is kind of cool, right?
So we're trimming everything from separated languages
into one matrix.
And it's doing the same thing.
It's a projection from a vector into another vector.
So this would be like the result here.
We would have dimensionality of six,
because we have six languages.
Any questions?
Yes.
What do we do with biases?
Well, we treat them the same way as we did before.
So we have, for each language, we would have basically,
oh, here, what do we do with the biases?
Yes, so we convert the bias into also,
like, a six-dimensional vector.
So everything will kind of work with the dimensions here.
Yeah, thank you.
Any other question?
Yes.
So if I understand correctly, we have
this two-step probability for every language, right?
Exactly.
In that case, we would also need that for all the ways
we just said, oh, the probability is really low,
or multiple tests, the probability is really high.
Yes, I know.
So we're not going to, you're talking
about putting the sigmoid over that.
I mean, the sigmoid, this tells you probability of the,
whether it's, the linear mapping is basically
a projection into a number.
So now, for each language, you're
projecting the input to a number.
And it tells us some sort of affinity,
or how for this language, this input,
kind of what values is it giving us.
But we're not saying the probability at all.
Just numbers.
Because if we do this, the output
will be a vector of size 6 of real numbers.
But these will be, these could be from minus infinity,
oh, sorry, it's not infinity.
This is infinity to plus infinity,
because we don't put any constraints here.
So it just gives us, it's a projection
to low dimensional space.
Nothing more.
There's no probabilities.
OK, does that answer your question?
OK.
Any other question?
Yes.
Then you take the highest one, or?
Yes, I will take the highest one.
I would take like, which one is the highest?
This will be the language.
Why not?
I mean, we can do that.
Is it a good thing to do?
Yeah, maybe there's something better.
But theoretically, we can just make this projection
and take the maximum here.
And we can learn the weights in a way
that it will just work out nicely.
OK?
Yes.
Can we, instead of doing this, like having specific,
it's almost a different model for each language, right?
Mm-hmm.
Yes, exactly.
So can you do different models for each language?
Because if you look at this like that,
then it feels like different models for each language.
If we cram them to one matrix, it's still the same thing.
They are independent.
Because these are kind of independent.
We're going to use something which make them kind
of dependent.
And really, we'll try to pick one, which will be the answer,
and kind of suppress the others.
We'll get to there.
We'll make it everything fit together.
OK?
Yeah, linear regression, but you would then, so linear.
I guess this is for the language.
Like, if the prediction was from 1 to 0.8,
I know what you mean, yes.
I mean, conceptually, you could do that.
But then you impose an ordering on your categories
because you're mapping them to real numbers.
And this is what we don't want to do.
I mean, I think you could do that.
But then you're putting meaning on things
which don't have meaning.
You're putting ordering of values to languages,
while you're just one hot.
I mean, they're just discrete, completely independent.
OK?
Good, let's move on.
So what we're doing is projecting input vector
to the output vector.
So the dimension n was the, what was that?
The vocabulary size, right?
So one hot encoding of back of words.
And the out is the number of classes now.
So recall from the last lecture that we're doing this,
basically, we talked about it already,
with this high dimensional linear function.
So the projection from in to out,
basically, by multiplying by matrix
and adding some bias term.
So we had it before.
And actually, this is a simple neural network.
It's a perceptron, which is simply a linear model, which
is projecting to, projecting weights to, sorry,
excuse me, projecting inputs through weights and biases
to a high dimensional vector, or the number of classes vector.
OK?
So now how to find the prediction y, right?
I mean, we want to find the, what is the language of that?
We don't want to just a vector.
We don't want to have this vector of reals.
We want the highest one.
So we are taking the argmax.
OK?
We're taking the maximum, where this projection is at highest.
Right?
I mean, this would be, we're talking right now about,
like, you pick the highest number in there,
and this is going to be your answer.
So sanity check.
So what is this y?
What is this going to be?
So we have this y hat is a vector of these predictions.
So these are the six values.
What is going to be, if you put it through argmax,
what is going to be y hat?
Exactly.
Thank you.
It's going to be index of 1 in the 1-hot encoding.
So it's going to be the index of the maximum here.
So we can, you can say it's 3, or it's this vector.
These are equivalent, because we did this mapping from categories
with 1-hot.
OK?
Everybody's with me with it?
Argmax is picking the index of that.
OK.
Which is interesting, because, well, it doesn't matter.
OK, we don't have time for that.
Because argmax, I mean, this is a discrete function,
so what is argmax of vector?
Like, what is, makes no sense.
Because this is a vector, so what is argmax of the vector?
Because vector is not a function.
You have argmax of a function.
Yeah, so this is the value of x, where the function is maximum.
But a vector?
So we implicitly assume we're taking this 1-hot encoding
thing and just taking the position of that, right?
So your answer was correct, but we're
misusing the notation for mathematics.
Like, argmax on a vector is kind of, oh, yeah, OK, sure.
We take the maximum index.
OK?
Great.
So now, I think this is important to mention.
Like, we're talking about representations.
And I think this is also, to me, was kind of sort
of revealing this view.
So let's dive deeper before jumping
into how to make all these six models together into one
and why this makes any sense.
So what we are doing here is, while projecting this
into this six-dimensional space, we're learning
some sort of representation.
So first, the vector x, we know the back of words.
This is a representation of the document.
We're representing a document as the average of back of words.
Great.
So the dimensions is the size of the vocabulary, for example.
It's very sparse and so on.
So it is a mathematical representation of text.
We talked about it last time.
On the other hand, the vector y hat
is also a representation of the document, right?
Because we project it somewhere to some different space,
but it's representing still documents.
And this representation is, well, it
has six dimensions, so it's more compact.
And this representation of this document
is more specialized for this task,
because we want it to be for this task.
But it's still, it contains some representation
of the input document, although it's
kind of compressed from all the words into six-size vector.
Everybody follow?
Why is that so?
It's still something about a document,
and we do classification on top of that,
but it carries some representation.
So this is OK, but also the matrix
is some learned representation, actually.
And the matrix here, so we learn it, right?
I mean, when we run the training and do
the stochastic gradient thing, we learn the parameters,
the matrix.
And we can have two views on this W matrix
from either S rows or columns.
So we start with the columns.
So this is the W matrix.
So this is the W. And this size is the, what is this?
This is the size of the vocabulary, right?
So 100,000 or 10,000.
And this is six columns.
And we're projecting the vector through this matrix.
Yes, you have a question?
The vocabulary would comprise all the languages, right?
Yes.
Yeah, that's a great point.
I mean, I just made up something,
but it should be correctly, it should have all the languages,
vocabulary for all the languages if you
want to really do the task.
Actually, if you really want to do
the task of language identification,
you wouldn't use words as units.
You would use character bigrams.
Who knows what is character bigram?
What is a bigram of characters?
It's exactly just two characters in a row.
It's like AA, AB, AC.
I mean, basically you cut everything
into just bigram characters.
And bigram characters are good features
for language identification, not words,
because words are different in different languages,
but we have something small.
OK.
But let's pretend now this is just a vocabulary, OK?
And this is the matrix.
And what we are doing here, we're
taking the input vector and multiply by matrix
and add these constants.
Let's just ignore the bias now.
Let's just do this just the multiplication.
So the perspective from the columns
is that each of these six columns,
and they correspond to language, like English, French,
and so on, is this dimensional vector representation
of this language in terms of its characteristics,
characteristic word unigram patterns, or just bigram,
whatever we have as the features, unigram pattern.
So this is a vector representation of the language
here in this learned matrix.
And if we, for example, cluster these vectors,
we can find similar languages, because they
share the same sort of bigram or word unigram patterns here.
So this is what we learn.
We learn some representation of the language
through this projection.
So this is the column view.
And there are any questions?
Yes.
I didn't understand the last sentence.
How are the same word represented?
Is that what you're saying?
So these will be real numbers.
And each of the language, the mapping to the language
will represent which each of the word, how each of these words
is represented, or some patterns of these words in the language,
in all of them.
So are the numbers in each row going to be similar?
No, in each column, maybe.
So if there were very similar languages,
and you do language classification tasks,
so you would learn this representation for language
classification tasks, similar languages
will end up with similar columns,
because the words in there behave similar.
They have similar weights in this classification.
So the learning will push them, these two languages
being somewhere close.
OK?
Does that answer your question?
OK, cool.
There is another view.
And this is the row view, where each row corresponds to a,
well, it's on the unigram.
So it's a, yeah, it's a unigram, basically, a word.
A unigram, and each word provides
a six-dimensional vector representation of that word
in terms of the languages it's prompting, so in this task.
So each of these words is represented
as a kind of like embeddings, or embedded vector,
over all these six classes.
So this is like learned representation of each word.
All right?
It has a meaning, because the word
will have some projection to all these six classes.
Yes?
For other, you use the average of all other?
No, no, no.
We just said, like, other is also a parameter.
Yeah.
So there is no distinction.
It's just six-column vector matrix,
and we're just putting these classes as such.
OK?
So these are two views.
I mean, I'll give you some time to think about later
on what it really means, but we have a nice property here.
So if you recall from last time, what
is the average back of words?
Basically, we're taking the one-off encoding
for each word in the document, and sum them up, and just
divide by the length of the document.
Right?
So this is what we did, like how we end up
with this one-off representation,
or average back of words representation.
Now, if we look back at this formula,
so multiplying the input by this ways, by this matrix,
and forget about the bias for now,
and plug in here the average back of words.
So we're going to end up with something like that.
So the x, basically, is represented
as this average back of words, and we're just plugging here
and multiplying by the matrix.
So the next thing we can do is let's say, yeah, I mean,
multiplication is, or now maybe I'll make it wrong,
but it is associative.
So we can plug this, get rid of those,
and plug it in here in the sum.
I guess we can do that.
I'm pretty sure we can do that, but I
don't know if it's association or commutativity,
one of those.
I'm sorry.
So we can do that and plug, basically,
the multiplication here and sum over them and do this average.
And what we're doing here, so this is a one-hot vector,
and we're multiplying the matrix by one-hot vector.
This is effectively doing what?
So we have a, let's try.
We have a one-hot vector, 0, 1, 0, 0,
and we have a matrix, which is maybe two rows.
And here will be 8, 4, 7, 6, 2, 4, that's wrong, 2, 3, 9, 9.
So what's going to be the input?
What is this multiplication doing of this matrix?
Exactly.
It's selecting a row.
It's just selecting a row, basically, because everything,
so we multiply 0 by 8 plus 1 times 4 plus 0 plus 0,
and the second will be 0 times 2 plus 1 times 3.
So it's 3 plus 0 and 0.
So we're going to end up with the 4, 3 vector, which
is exactly selecting the second row, which
is exactly corresponding to the position of the one.
Everybody's with me?
Good, because this means we're just
selecting a row from this representation matrix, which
corresponds to the word that position, position di.
So you're basically taking the vector
from this embedding matrix and make an average of them.
Well, these two things come together here.
So this learned representation, oh, sorry,
this representation y and this representation y
have two different views.
One is basically saying, so this is continuous back
of words representation.
One is saying, we just sum word representation vectors.
So this is this one we just saw in the last slide.
So for each word, we're taking its row in the weight matrix
and sum them up together and take an average.
Or we take a back of word representation as before
and multiply by this weight matrix again.
And these are the same, but they give us different views.
And this matrix is also called embedding matrix.
So this is how we map from, let's say,
sparse space or one-hot encoding to embed it
to more dense space.
And we will talk about embeddings and word embeddings
later on.
But this is where it comes from.
Why is it so weird?
We have two views on this learned weights.
And they tell us something about the categories and columns
also and the input tokens as rows.
Yes.
For example, we talked about 0, 1, 0, 2.
In the null situation, is there going
to be a vector that has the length of the vocabulary
of all languages needed?
Some does?
Or like, think about the common word?
Yes.
Yeah, I mean, you have large matrices.
That's true.
You would have like in this, let's come back here.
So for example, if we really want
to classify a language here, so we would have,
this would be the number of bigrams.
It could be, let's say, 10,000.
So it would be like 10,000 dimension vector.
If we multiply into, if we have six languages,
so this would have dimension of 10,000 rows times 6.
And then the vector b would be a 6.
Yeah, why not?
OK, any other question?
OK, good, let's move on.
Now, oops, what was that?
Sorry.
Now, where are we?
OK, so this is like what is embeddings
are and what the projection is.
And I think it gives interesting view on the embeddings.
What is learned in this representation?
So representation learning is centered to deep learning.
So the main power of deep learning
is basically the ability to learn good representation.
So all these projection matrices are learned
and they give us great representation.
But let's come back to the task we had before.
So OK, we have this multidimensional linear
transformation.
So we are projecting from one space to another,
maybe from 10,000 to 6.
But we want to turn it into probabilities for some reason,
because we want to find the best prediction
from these number of classes, for example.
What is the language?
And we want to give it a probability,
because we have in the sigmoid, in the logistic regression,
we had the binary logistic regression,
we had this probability of being 1 or probability of being 2.
Maybe you want to put probabilities
of these predictions on these multiclass classification
as well.
So we want to turn output vector into probabilities
of these different classes.
So remember, we have this vector, this y hat.
Y hat vector would be this six numbers.
And we want to do something better.
So let's quick recap.
What is categorical probability distribution?
So everybody had a background in probability theory
a little bit.
Who hasn't heard of categorical distribution or probability
distribution at all?
Great.
So we have a random variable, which
is defined over k categories.
And these categories are distinct,
and there's no ordering, and so on.
And these are mapped to typically natural numbers,
so 1, 2, up to k categories.
In our categorical distribution, we
would have English would be 1, and German 2,
and so on, so on, so on.
And then each category is parameterized
with probability of this category.
So for example, the probability of x being English
would be, I don't know, some probability like 0.1.
And the probability of x being 2 could be 0.4, and so on.
So we're saying which of these different choices,
what is the probability of each of them?
And there is one thing that the categorical distribution
has to take into account.
These have to be positive, obviously,
as probabilities between 0 and 1.
And there must be one constraint on this whole thing, which
is if this is a probability distribution,
there is one condition or one definition.
Yes?
They have to sum up to 1.
They have to sum up to 1, exactly.
So all of them sum up to 1.
So basically, then, if we had a vector over our six categories,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, then it has to sum up
to 1 to be a probability distribution
over these categories.
So I just want to bring this terminology here.
But I guess this is clear case.
The question here is that how to turn a vector, unbounded vector,
in this, let's say, six-dimensional space
into a categorical probability distribution.
So now, the question is, we have, again,
our six, which is a vector.
And each of them could be from minus infinity to plus
infinity.
How to turn it into a categorical probability
distribution?
Any ideas?
You first.
Oh, OK, using the softmax.
You know the answer already.
OK, good.
So I want to try something super naive.
But if you know the softmax, this is the solution.
Yeah.
Any other?
OK, so anyone who hasn't heard of softmax
but has an idea, like, creative, like how to turn this vector
into probability distribution.
AUDIENCE 1
Add up all the values and then divide each one by the other.
OK, you would say you would sum up
all these values and then basically normalizing
each value by this sum.
This is great.
There is a catch.
What is the catch if you do that?
AUDIENCE 1 Negative number.
Negative numbers.
Yeah, it will break negative numbers.
OK, so you hate negative numbers.
AUDIENCE 1 I just take the absolute value.
You could take an absolute value
and divide it by the sum of that.
And I think it will work, actually.
I think it must work.
Because you take, let's say, this,
put it into absolute value.
So xi absolute value over sum of j xj.
OK, good.
I think it's actually, it will be sufficient to do so.
AUDIENCE 2 But it would lose the minus, right?
You would lose the minus, right?
Exactly.
It's bad.
It's the opposite, yes.
So basically, you would lose half of the information
you would have in the value.
OK, so we need something else.
But this is a great progress.
Because this, we need to make it.
OK, so the catch here, how to make any number positive
number.
So we're simplifying the question here.
How to make any number, how to turn something
from minus infinity to plus infinity into 0 to infinity.
Yes.
AUDIENCE 3 You could just use the lowest numbers
to starting point, set it at 0.
Yeah, you can set a baseline.
But it's just arbitrary.
Because it depends on the values.
AUDIENCE 3 I mean, like, take the lowest number
from the vector, like, that's a negative 10.
Let the lowest number say, OK, we add 10.
Yeah, exactly.
You can put it sort of a bias in a way, like threshold,
and then just add up.
But it's depending on the values.
And you want to do it a function like values independent.
Any other idea how to turn this into?
AUDIENCE 3 You could just have a power value.
You can put a power value, like xy
squared.
AUDIENCE 3 These two, or the power of the number
that we can add in here.
Oh, 2 to x.
Yes, I think you're on a good way.
It should, yeah, exactly.
You can do that.
Yeah, and maybe we're not going to use 2 to power x.
But we might use something different,
which is nicely differentiable.
So 2 power x is great.
Anything else we can use instead of 2 power x?
We just nice derivatives.
e power x, exactly.
Yeah, we're getting somewhere.
OK, so this is great.
This gives us positive numbers.
This is even greater, because it gives us
differentiation, which is just the same function.
And what we end up here now, so if we replace this,
this absolute values with this e to x, we found a softmax.
Congratulations, great job.
No, I mean, come on.
I mean, you can think about it like,
there's a reason why softmax looks like the softmax.
If I should just show you the equation, like, OK, whatever.
But if you come up with the idea, like how to build it,
then it has a meaning.
So we're putting everything.
It's a nonlinear rejection from minus infinity
to infinity to plus here.
So this is the exponentiation denominator.
And the denominator is just normalization constant.
This is great.
OK, so what is missing on the picture here?
So we have a softmax, which kind of creates
the probability distribution.
This gives us the probability distribution
over any real vector.
This is important, by the way, to remember.
I mean, you should know softmax.
If you leave deep learning for an LP and come to someone,
it's like, I don't remember softmax,
but I can look it up on Wikipedia.
No, I'm sorry.
You should, I mean, no, this is easy.
But you should know that.
What's missing here for us?
Because we want to plug the softmax somewhere later on.
What is missing on the picture?
We need to do something with the softmax.
As with any other function, we are plugging into our functions,
into our complete functions.
Derivative.
Yeah, we need the derivative, exactly.
We need the derivative for each of these position
to the arguments.
And actually, I didn't look.
I don't know.
Take it as a homework.
Because the Wikipedia solution was kind of ugly,
and I hadn't time to do it by hand.
So there is a derivative, obviously,
of this function with respect to each argument.
But it wasn't like this.
It didn't look straightforward just to put it here on Wikipedia.
So maybe you want to try it by hand.
But there is a derivative, obviously.
Great, so we have this softmax function.
What else?
Yeah, so softmax, actually, we typically
use softmax in different setup, also
with this thing called temperature, temperature T.
And if you ever play with ChetGTP or some APIs from ChetGTP
or GPT-4, there is a parameter called temperature.
Have you seen that before?
Anybody heard of temperature?
You know why it's temperature?
Because of this.
It's just basically, it's putting.
And this is coming from physics, as far as I know,
because it has some meaning on the entropy of the universe
or whatever.
But it's basically dividing each of these constants
by this temperature.
And the meaning of that is that, for example, the input
of softmax would be 3, 0, 1.
And if we use no temperature, the output of the softmax
is going to be like that.
So this is a probability distribution.
Everything is between 0 and 1.
And as we see, 3 will be the biggest.
0 will be somewhere low, but not 0.
And 1 will be somewhere low, but not as big as that.
If we use high temperature, this is getting more uniform.
And why is it in ChetGPT?
Because you can put temperature on the sampling, basically,
of the next word, something like that.
So high temperature means more randomness
in the sampling of the next word, while low temperature
means basically almost certainty in the distribution.
So the temperature is just a parameter
which has an influence on the output of the softmax.
Any question?
Great.
So we have a softmax.
We're going to plug the softmax somewhere.
That's for sure.
But we had a loss function for the sigmoid.
So the loss function, what was the name again?
Binary cross-entropy was the loss function,
was these two logarithms and things like that.
But what are we going to do for the softmax?
Well, we're going to use a categorical cross-entropy, also
known as negative log likelihood.
Remember this, please.
This is central to machine learning
and negative log likelihood.
What you're doing, yeah?
I'm minimizing negative log likelihood.
OK, good.
What does it mean?
Yeah, so it's a categorical cross-entropy.
OK, what does it mean?
So this is it.
Basically, we have, again, so we have the y vector
is the vector of the distribution of the class's
labels.
And now we have two options.
So this would be basically a one-hot encoding.
So 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0 would be the hard decision.
But you say, maybe you want a distribution of languages.
So it could be anything, actually.
I mean, we can have like, it could be 0.5 German and 0.5
English, and the rest would be zeros.
Maybe.
Why not?
I mean, as long as this is probability distribution,
we're fine.
But typically, we use one-hot encoding for the labels.
And the output of softmax, as we just saw,
will be something like this.
So maybe this would be the output of the softmax.
So some distribution which sums up to 1.
What we are trying to do is to make
the difference of these two distributions
as small as possible.
So this is a probability distribution, very spiky here.
This is a probability distribution.
And we want to make this distribution
difference as small as possible.
Why?
Because we want the model to predict
what is in the gold standard data.
How to do that?
We're using this negative log-likelihood,
or cross-entropy loss, which has this very nice formula,
or very ugly formula, depending on perspective.
And it's, yeah.
So it's basically iterating over all these categories
and computing log of 1, multiplying
by the value of the other.
And so why is this so?
What is this coming from?
I mean, maybe you could remember this one.
Yeah, I guess you can remember that.
But why is this?
Where is this coming from?
I mean, why is this so?
Like minus logarithms from one, the other.
There is a meaning.
So typically, you will find this as you learn it.
And this is a little cross-entropy loss.
Think about it.
We want to find a distance between two distributions.
So how do you find distance, or differences
between two distributions?
Anybody who has probability theory,
how do you compare two distributions?
Is there a way, if you have one distribution
and another distribution over the same values,
how do you measure the difference
between two distributions?
Is there a way?
Exactly, KL?
Divergence.
KL divergence or divergence?
Yes, so KL divergence.
OK, good.
How do you compute KL divergence?
Anybody knows how to compute KL divergence?
It's been a while.
I know, I'm sorry.
Yes, but if you go to KL divergence,
it's an expectation over a function of one variable.
And there's some logarithm in there.
And it's like, oh, it looks similar.
OK, yes, because this is coming from the KL divergence.
So this is optional slide.
I don't want to scare you off, because I scared off last year
everybody here.
So I'm not going to go through this.
But this is the KL divergence over two probabilities
over the same random variable with the same range.
And this is as an expectation of the PY.
And here's the function of the random variable, which is QY.
OK, so yeah, this is the definition of KL divergence.
And then if you do the math and logarithms and blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, you end up with two things.
You can decompose this into two things.
OK, what is this?
Anyone knows this from probability theory?
What is H typically?
So this is the entropy.
So you compose this KL divergence
into entropy of Y. And this is expectation
of the other thing.
And if you do the math here and make this explicit,
the expectation here, you end up with this formula.
This is exactly coming from there.
So basically, you want to compare two distributions.
You use KL divergence.
You decompose KL divergence into two parts.
And one part doesn't really depend on the predictions.
So you just get rid of it, because you cannot optimize it.
And take the part you need to optimize.
And this is going to be cross-entropy.
OK, so there's a reason why this looks like how it looks like.
But you can also remember the formula.
If you do it for two, if k is 2, you will end up with,
surprise, surprise, surprise, surprise, surprise, surprise,
surprise, surprise, surprise, surprise.
Oh, Jesus, it's long.
You will end up with this.
So this is the cross-entropy for two variables.
We don't use sum here, but it's the same thing.
Just spit out exactly.
OK?
It's coming from the KL divergence.
Oops, that was too slow, too fast.
OK, and I think we'll actually finish today, maybe,
hopefully.
So this is like optional slide, but that you know it's
coming from somewhere.
There is a meaning.
So we had this linear functions.
OK, I'm sorry.
I need just six minutes, and we're through it.
Is it OK?
Cool.
Good, so now it's coming to final.
We have the linear layer.
We put a softmax on top of that.
Did we do that?
I guess so.
No, the softmax will give you probability distribution
over these outputs of this linear transformation.
Linear transformation, six-size vector, softmax,
turn it into probability distribution,
and you pick the maximum.
Or you know the probability of each class
from the predictions.
The whole thing, the whole fun of deep learning
is that you can stack things together.
So what you can do is, well, this looks ugly, right?
It's not.
Stay with me.
So we have, again, our input vector and the weights,
and this is the linear transformation.
So we have one linear transformation
as we had before.
What if we take this and do another transformation here
with another set of parameters, and then compute a loss
and make predictions?
So we would basically inline the first.
This would be the first linear function
into another linear transformation.
And we have more dimensions here.
So this is the input dimension.
There will be the output dimension.
And of course, to make this multiplication work,
we have these matrices and biases vectors.
D1 is the dimensionality of the first function,
and then there's the other function.
So can we do that?
We could be stacking things together
and having more projections, basically.
So we would basically project our high-dimensional space
into another space, and then we can project from this space
to yet another space with the hope
that we will end up with a great representation of the problem
that the classification will be easy.
There is one catch with that.
I mean, so first question is, are you with me on this?
We can stack things together and have some linear functions
on top of each other.
Does it make sense?
And the dimensions have meaning, is there?
I mean, meaning in terms of they have to match.
So this is great.
But what happens if you do linear transformation
after another linear transformation?
What do you end up with?
What will be the output function?
So you can basically put them together
and get one linear transformation.
Exactly.
If you do linear transformation one after each other,
you will end up with one linear transformation in total.
So it will still be linear.
So it won't solve the problem of nonlinearity in the data.
I don't think we talk.
Did we talk about nonlinearity in the data or not?
I don't think so.
OK, we should address that.
Yeah, sorry.
It's a glitch in the screenplay as well.
But the idea is that, OK, we can stack them together.
And in order to learn better representation, not just
linear representations, what is linear representation?
Just projecting something on maybe on a wall in 2D.
But all the distances will be still the same.
But we want to learn better representation,
which kind of tears maybe the dimensions apart
or the instances apart.
So the trick here is that we add a nonlinearity in here.
So we take the output of the first, let's call it layer.
Why not?
Because it is a layer.
And push it through some nonlinear function.
And then the rest is the same as before.
Yes?
What's the y?
Where's the y?
What is the y?
x is the input.
Yes.
And y is the label.
Yeah, so this is the same setup.
We have an input.
And this is the GALT label.
GALT label as we had before.
But we just, this is in between.
The transformation is getting more complicated.
Here it was just two linear transformation
on top of each other.
But they don't give any added value
because it will be still linear, like two matrices
after each other.
But here we're adding some nonlinear,
excuse me, nonlinear function in there,
which we typically call also a activation function.
And it's doing some nested things in the space.
So you project somewhere and push it
through some nonlinearity, which will do
some weird things in this space.
So everybody's with me on that.
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
Yes, I guess this is correct.
This should be T1, exactly.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, great catch.
Great catch.
Thanks a lot.
Yes.
I copy pasted it and then, yes.
Yeah, that's correct, exactly.
Well, let's come back here.
So this I have to fix.
But we're plugging in the activation here.
And the activation definitely will be, yes.
I mean, now the dimensions are correct.
So it will be applied to a vector of this dimension.
And the vector comes out.
So we're not doing any transformation here.
We just apply this on each element
of this vector coming out of this layer.
OK, any questions?
Good.
So what is this nonlinear function could be?
What is a nonlinear function?
If you say ReLU, don't say it.
If you say something else, say it.
tanh.
tanh, yes.
OK, well, we already had a nonlinear function before.
tanh is great.
So tangent hyperbolic, which maps everything into,
oh, how is that?
Maybe like that.
So between minus 0.5 and 0.5, is it correct?
I hope so.
Is it minus 1 to 1?
OK.
No, no, no, let's make it right.
So minus 1 and 1.
And we had another one.
We had something very similar, almost very similar.
We had a sigmoid.
Exactly.
So it could be a sigmoid, which maps everything, basically.
And this is, as I said, this is, here's
coming up what's coming out of here.
It's a vector.
And we're applying this on each element independently.
So we can use tanh.
We can use sigmoid.
They used to be popular.
We have something else you were saying.
No, you were saying ReLU.
OK, we have ReLU.
So we have ReLU, which is very weird actual activation
function, because it's saying just, yeah,
everything which is positive will stay the same.
For it will be like the input will be the output
if this is a positive number.
And if it's negative, it will be just 0.
So basically, we're kind of like breaking
the function in the middle and saying,
or you can say it will maximum of the input or the 0.
So OK, this is great.
What do we need to compute for this thing?
I mean, everything has to be, we need
for every function we plug into the network, we need what?
We need derivative.
So what's going to be derivative of ReLU?
0 and 1?
Yeah, exactly.
So the derivative here will be 0.
And here the derivative will be 1.
It's beautiful.
Like we have this thing at the 0 minus.
And this is a catch.
Yes, what's this?
It's the continuous.
Yeah, you cannot do it.
Exactly.
So what you're saying is that's why
we don't need to have continuous functions,
because this is not continuous in a way like it's
differential at every point.
Because here we're kind of breaking it.
So we arbitrarily choose saying like at 0
is going to be 1 or 0, just by definition.
We don't care about it.
Because the chances it will be exactly 0 is super low.
But if so, you can say, yeah, let's let the derivative be 1
or 0.
Yeah, yeah, like a design choice.
You say, in my implementation, I'm
going to use derivative of 1 for everything which
is greater or equal to 0.
But it does not affect that much.
It doesn't affect that much.
Exactly, exactly.
And this is the ReLU.
ReLU is like one of the most widely used nonlinearities
in deep learning and natural language processing so far.
So it has nice derivatives, nice implementation.
It's very fast, because it's just the identity function
or just basically one liner.
So it's super fast as well to compute.
And we're going to plug it on many places.
Any question?
Great, we're through.
Made it.
So binary classification as linear function
works in words.
Yeah, we hit it.
So cross-entropy logistic loss, important to remember.
Then mini-batch SGD is very important.
Actually, everything is important,
except for the child divergence.
If you want to sound smart in a bar, you can learn this well.
And then we have the stacking and multilayer perceptron.
OK, thanks a lot.
See you in a week.