Okay, I think we should start. So welcome to the second lecture on deep learning for
NLP. Happy to see so many of you here, which is great. And today, okay, so any questions
to the last topics, anything which came to your mind and you would like to ask? This
is great. Any organizational questions, which we didn't talk about at whatever, Discord
Noodle and stuff like that. Everybody's happy with how things are so far. Discord works
for you. Okay, cool. Great. So you might have asked, well, what about the exercises and
homeworks? So this is in doing, I guess the first exercise will be ready next week, because
we have a task force preparing them. And the homeworks, so what we discussed so far, there
will be roughly two to three, maybe three to four homeworks overall. Last semester,
we had six and it was an overkill, it was just too much. So we thought like three, maybe
four homeworks will be the best thing to do. Okay, so these were the things. So stay tuned.
And today we're going deep and not like deep learning, but we're going deep into the basics.
So why? So let me start with sort of motivation. And I'm going to ask you, who of you, because
there's some people who had some machine learning, so who of you knows stochastic gradient descent
and back propagation? Raise your hand. Okay, that should be like, yeah, a half or third.
Nice. Who of you ever implemented this thing from scratch? Okay, cool. Wow. That's, that's
great. I'm gonna ask the rest, why not? So those of you who know these things, why you
haven't implemented them from scratch? It's a really curious question. Yes.
Okay, they're existing frameworks and they make our life easier. Exactly. Any other,
anyone had a different reason for why, why not doing this from scratch and relying on
existing frameworks? So I tell you mine, one reason was that, and the second was like,
I found it super complicated. Like why, why the heck should I do this? You know, the mathematics
and stuff. It's like, I don't understand it at all. So I'm going to use what's out there.
And actually understanding things under the hood makes you actually understanding things
better and implementing things makes you that understand even more. Right. So who, so those
of you who implemented it from scratch, was it, was it a great exercise for you to learn
how things actually work under the hood? Was it? Is there somebody who, who kind of hesitated
there? Who kind of said like, well, I shouldn't have done that. It's not the case. So that's
great. So the goal of this lecture is to go deep, deep into the core of deep learning
and even not even touching deep learning and neural networks, but understanding the mathematics
behind and how things can be implemented from scratch. So you can, after, after this lecture,
you should be able to implement the backbone of deep learning and training neural networks,
basically by our own and understanding mathematics behind. That's the goal. Okay. It's, it's kind
of challenging. So I don't know how, you know, hopefully it'll work out. So I'm not a mathematician.
I'm a computer scientist. I used to hate mathematics before I kind of understood that mathematics
is just a, it's a weird language, you know, and they have like so many weird kind of,
so to say, speaking of the same thing in very different languages, as we will see. Okay.
So if you hate what you see, you can leave. That's fine. No, but I guess there's some,
there's a deep need for understanding. So let's dive deeper. And what we won't be covering
here today. So we won't cover the abstract mathematics. We won't cover set theory. Okay.
But if you want to understand mathematics, what I learned from mathematicians, it's like,
you have to understand set theory because everything is, can be expressed in terms of
sets, which is the assembler of mathematics, you know, but it kind of sucks because it
doesn't give you any advantage of being faster. Like if you program something in assembler,
it's faster than in doing in Python. If you do mathematics in set theory, yeah, who cares?
So, so you should know something of set theory. So we have sets, sets have elements, there's
no ordering and we have ordered tuples. That's enough for us to know. We won't cover number
theory because we know there are some, you know, there's some natural numbers and there's
real numbers. So we can, we have real numbers. This is given. And there's this weird thing
like infinity. So yeah. Okay. That's, that's a weird animal, but we kind of assume there's
infinity and as a reason for things, we won't cover sequences and limits, right? So you
should kind of know what sequences of real numbers are and what's are the limits because
limits are the backbone of derivatives. Okay. So everybody knows what a limit is. Is there
anyone in the room who doesn't know limits? Okay, great. Great. So what is important to
know? Okay. What is these weird symbols? So R squared, this is the set of real numbers
and it's basically a tuple of, you know, two, two real numbers. So a vector or a tuple,
two dimensional vector. Okay. So this is like the simplest thing that we start with.
Okay. And what, what are the problems we're going to solve? Well, what are you interested
in in the first place? So we need to learn how to minimize functions, you know? So this
is basically, we need to build the tools in order to train and understand neural networks.
And one of the part of that is minimizing functions. So what does it mean? We want to
find the minimum of any function. What I'm showing here is a function in like, it could
be y is something, something of x, right? So this is the plot. This is the x axis. This
is the y axis, just a standard thing. So what is the minimum of any function? How do you
find it? Yeah. So you can say, well, I'm going to look, you know, I'm going to have a look
at this chart and the minimum is right here. I can see that. Well, this beautiful,
but you can't do that, right? Because you don't see the function. You have the prescription
of a function and typically you cannot plot it. I mean, if it's easy function, you can do it,
something which you learn in high school. So you can do, you know, all these derivatives
and secondary about this and blah, blah, blah equals to zero. Yeah. For easy function, that's
easy. That's what you did, I guess, in the high school or in some mathematics. But for complicated
functions, you will see it's not trivial and it could be super cumbersome to actually try
to find the minimum. So what can we, how can we solve this problem is, well, okay, if I ask you,
here's a function and find me the minimum. What, as a computer scientist, what would be like the
first thing you will try? The most stupid idea to try to find the minimum of a function.
You can evaluate a function and you find the output value. What would be like the super
easiest thing to try? You are first. You would try exactly. You would. No, no, no. Don't laugh.
I mean, you would try a random guesses, right? So you would say, okay, let's pick this X. Yeah.
Okay. Why not? Let's pick this one. Yeah. Let's pick this one. Okay. Does it guarantee anything?
Yeah, not really. Any other idea?
You can look at the neighbors, which is a law. You start with a random.
Okay. So you would, I see, you would start here and then just look at neighbors and then see.
Okay. That's clever. That's already clever. Something even much worse. Like brute force.
I would try all X values and see, okay, for all X, where is the minimum? Yeah. That's the brute
force search. It could work. It can't work for unbounded functions. If this were like
to infinity, well then I'm doomed. I cannot try all the real numbers, but I could. So this is like
the most stupid thing to try would be a brute search. So we should do any better. The random
thing. Why not? I mean, I guess it should be something in a, how's it called, the genetic
algorithms are using random kind of function optimization. Why not? We should try something
better and the neighbors. Yeah. That's a good idea. We're going to utilize, we're going to
utilize the curve of, you know, the, the kind of how the function looks like the curve. So,
but first what is the function? So we're using the Euler's notation, which is, yeah, we have some
arbitrary, but somehow standard naming convention. So we're saying X, the input, Y is typically the
output and F is the number of the name of the function. So we write something like that. Right.
I mean, this is not rocket science, right? This is Euler notation. What we are saying here is that
we have this function from R to R. So it's a mapping from one set to another, and we call this
domain and the other we called codomain. Right. So this is like a little bit of terminology. This
shouldn't be surprising. I mean, most of that shouldn't be surprising to you, but I'm trying
to cover everything to have everyone on board so that we are, if we are talking about something
that you've heard it. So, so this is clear. We're using these functions all over the place.
Now we have a thing when we have two functions. So we have this function F from reals to reals,
and we have a function G from reals to reals. We might stitch them together. Right. We might
compose them. And this is the very weird operator, which is kind of saying I'll take the, so this is
the circle operator, the function composition. And it's saying I'm first evaluating on F,
and then I'm passing that to avoid the G. Okay. So it's like nested function. You call,
you put an argument into the G, but you first evaluate F and then turn to G. So basically
nested function. What could be a nested function? For example, Y is, I don't know,
a two times X square. So this is one function inside and this is the other outside. Okay.
What can be misleading here is this kind of very weird operator, this, the circle. So this is how
people somehow describe function composition. And you see like, what's coming first, G or F.
I never actually, I don't remember. I never remember. So I have to look it up on Wikipedia.
So if you see the circle operator, it's function composition. And some people are using that for
describing nested functions. I think this is much clearer, right? I mean, you first evaluate
the inside and then the outside. Okay. Everybody's with me. Awesome. Good. So we know what function
is at least one function from real to real. So single variable input and single variable output.
And now let's move to some geometry a little bit. So what is a line? Okay. What is a line? I mean,
line has a definition. It's very cool. So in a Cartesian plane, lines are characterized by
equations and every line is a set. Okay. Here we're coming to the backbone of mathematics,
a set theory. So a line is a set of all points whose coordinates X and Y satisfy a linear equation.
So this is why it's called linear equation, right? So we have X and Ys and we have some W1, W2,
and W3, which are called coefficients. This again, shouldn't be surprising because everybody
should somehow know from the high school what is a linear function. So this is a linear function
and linear function describes a line. It's a set of points. Okay, cool. And they have some
properties. Okay. So this shouldn't be surprising, right? Everybody's on board with me? Lines is a
set of points and it looks like that. So this is a line. Very good. We don't typically use this kind
of set oriented definition of a line, but instead we're using the so-called slope intercept form.
So slope intercept form is what we know as a basically a function of a line, which is Y is
equal a times X plus b. And this a is the slope and this b is the intercept. So this is a simple
linear function of one variable, one random number, one real number in and real number out.
And if we plot a line here, so this would be like some of our lines, for example, Y is,
so a and b would be some actual real numbers and we would have this line.
What is interesting is what is slope. So it has a meaning. This slope has a meaning. And if I
ask you what is a slope or steepness of the curve, I'm thinking in how, if I'm staying here,
how steep things go and how I perceive steepness is not a real number, but as an angle, right?
I mean, it's natural to me kind of see steepness of angles between zero and 90 degrees.
If you drive a road, there's like 11 degrees steepness, then you pay attention to how we drive.
And there's actually a cool relationship between this number, this coefficient, this slope
and the angle here. And if you come back to trigonometry and pick a triangle here, then
the rise over run is the tangents of this angle, right? So there's a relation between the slope
and the angle, and this is tangents, right? It's kind of cool because then I can understand if I
see a slope of a curve as a, it's a real number. It could be anything. It could be between
minus infinity to plus, well, could be infinity? I don't think so. So something between almost
minus infinity and plus infinity, but I can transfer it into an angle and then I see,
okay, well, this is like this going that up and that down, because if you know tangents function
then, or Arcus tangents, then you can transfer between these two.
So if we talk about the slope of a function, then it's a coefficient, like the slope coefficient,
but it also has something to do with the angle. Okay, any question?
Sounds great. Everybody's with me still. It's a high school mathematics, so it's no surprise. I
mean, we shouldn't be doing rocket science here, but building up, you know, really from scratch.
So we have lines, we have functions, and now what we want to do in order to minimize the function,
we want to approximate a function by a line at a point. Why is it good? Well, because it helps
us to find a, you know, to find a cool way to find a minimum of the function later on.
But how can we do approximate a line at a point? So let's say, let's pick a point c here,
and I want to approximate, let me come in here, and here I want to approximate a function
by a line. So this would be like a tangent. Okay.
And how can we do that? Well, you can pick a little bit different
you can pick a little bit different, sorry, this is, yeah, you can pick a little bit different
point nearby and just make this difference smaller and smaller and smaller and smaller
and smaller and smaller using trigonometry, and you end up with this limit. So this is a definition
of the derivative of this function f at point c, right? So we pick this point, and here
this is the, we can approximate by a line. And this derivative at this point is telling us the
the slope, right? It's telling how steep we go. Okay. So derivative is the best linear approximation
of a function at a point, and it's telling us how fast the function changes there.
Okay, everybody's with me? Any questions to derivative? So who hasn't seen derivatives before?
Great. So this is no surprise, right? But just, you know, think about it. Yeah, I mean,
I can understand the slope. I can approximate a function by the line, and the line is the
best approximation of the function at that point, and I'm using the derivative for doing so.
And it's telling me how fast the function here is coming up, and I have the exact number,
and this will be something like, this function will be actually exactly the derivative at point c,
times, how is it? Oh, sorry. Is it like x f derivative f c times x plus f c? Is it possible?
Like Taylor expansion, this is correct?
It's minus c, I think.
x minus c, exactly. Thank you. Yeah. So let me just do it again. Oops. So this would be x minus,
oh, what is this? Oh, come on. Oh, yeah. What did I do?
Okay. Sorry. So it would be x minus c plus f at c, right? This is the Taylor expansion of a
first degree polynomial of Taylor expansion. So this is the exact, and this is the slope, right?
You remember the function, we used to have this as a, so this is telling me the slope.
So it's telling me how steep is the function changing, or the line
approximating function changing at that point. Any questions? Great. So now we have the derivative,
and we know what's derivative of the function at the point. So, and we have the definition,
and remember, so we have derivative, which is giving us the value at point c. So it's always
bound to certain value. If we want to compute a derivative here, we would need to compute a limit
again, and just, well, it's boring. So maybe what we want to do instead is to have a function
which takes a differentiable function f as input and produces another function
at output such that, well, the other function evaluated at c equals to the derivative of f
at this point. What does it mean? So an example, let me see, maybe I have an example later on.
No. So an example would be, we have that, so f is, I don't know, x square, and what's the
derivative of x squared? Okay, what's the derivative of x squared? What is f prime?
Say it loud, yeah, say it loud. 2x, yes, thank you, 2x. Right, here we have a little bit of
this c and x and so on. So basically we want to, so this would be the function f, then we would have
g such that it's 2 times c, because we are changing variables here, right? We would say,
okay, the function evaluated at c is 2 times c, which is this derivative, okay? But we typically
don't change variables, so we typically say, yeah, well, actually the g, the derivative, sorry,
the derivative of f is 2 times x. So this is what we typically do, like, we don't care,
this is like one variable and the derivative is another variable and we call them x,
although they are different kind of things, a little bit formally. Okay, so everybody's with
me, like, what is the, so we can compute now, so this is cool, we can now compute
derivative for each point of this function. So what we plug here will give us derivative
of this function at this point, okay? So this is like derivative computing function,
right? Why I'm saying this? Because then we're coming into the hard part of mathematics,
which is the notation, and the notation is awful, I'm telling you. Because this derivative
computing function, you can write it as d to dx, and this is not a fraction, this is just one thing,
right? So this is not a fraction, this is just how you say, like, d to dx, and then you plug in the
function and compute the derivative of the function, like here, so you say, you know,
derivative of this function f, but then the notation is, like, inconsistent, it's horrible,
because you can write df over dx, but it's not a fraction, or dy dx over dx, and they mean all the
same thing. This is the derivative computing function, and you can write it in many different
ways. Here you have to choose x, although maybe there's no x in the function, here you have to
choose y and x and so on, so it's really ugly. So what you need to understand, that all these
are somehow equivalent, and it's just this horrible notation, which makes it kind of clumsy,
if you don't know what's behind, okay? So this is one lesson learned, if you read a paper about
derivatives, they will use, like, 20 different ways of writing this function, and they might
be mostly equivalent, so it's arbitrary decisions, like speaking 10 languages about the same thing, okay?
Any questions to this?
Let's move on. So we know how to compute the derivative of the function, okay? You're still with me,
why we need this? We want to minimize the function, so we want to find the derivative, because it will
tell us something about the function later on. Well, if the function is easy, like that one, like
x squared, yeah, that's fine. How about we have something more complicated, like sinus of x squared?
How can we compute a derivative?
Yeah, what do you have to do to compute a derivative of this function?
So it consists of two functions, one is sinus and then the other is derivative.
Exactly, yes.
So the inner function and one is sinus.
Right, so we have a compose function here, and there might be some special treatment of that,
and we will, it has a name, and it's called a chain rule in English. So there's a chain rule,
and it's saying if we have two functions which have derivatives and they're nested,
you know, so first f x is inside g x, or f is kind of the input to g, then we
take the output of f x, plug it into the derivative of g, and multiply by the derivative of f x.
This is the chain rule, okay? Everybody heard of this chain rule before? How to make a derivative of
nested functions? If not, make it your friend. Now, chain rule, okay? So you take, basically,
you evaluate the function f x, make it to g, and make a derivative of g, and multiply by the
derivative of the f x. This is the chain rule. And by the way, here we're using this prime thing,
like f prime x as a derivative, and not this d dx of f. So we have two different notations.
So here, I'm showing you the Lagrange notation for derivatives of function. I think you know
this from physics, right? If you do physics, you know, they're using like this prime. Is it true?
Anybody had some physics before? Well, I used to have one before, so this is what people are,
I guess, using. So the prime. I'm going to show, again, the same nested function like the chain
rule when we were using this kind of ugly notation of the nested functions. So you've
seen it at least once. And this is the same. So basically, we're saying, okay, I'm first computing
f, plugging it into g, you know, the derivative of g, and multiplying by the derivative of f.
So these are equivalent, right? This is the same thing, just written in different language. Here,
we're using this operator, the circle thing for function composition. It's the same.
And we have one more, which is the most awful notation I've seen, but it's just, it's like,
you know, alt API. It's been here for 250 years, 300 years, and nobody wants to ditch it. So we're
still using this API and writing derivatives, you know, using this notation, which is the
Leibniz notation, 1700-something. And again, we have a function composition f from f and g
has input fx. And then using this fraction, which is not a fraction, for derivative of h,
then the chain rule is multiplying these two things together. Okay. So basically,
all of them are equivalent. Yes. Yeah, that's a good, that's a nice, maybe I had three and I just
like, no, it doesn't fit the slides. No, that's typo. So thanks, I'll fix that. Any other question
or comment? So I guess we can do like a little bit walkthrough example, because it's important
to understand the notation and what we mean by computing this nested derivative. So it's super
important for us for minimizing functions. Right. So we have here a composed function, which is y
is e to sin x squared. Okay, cool. So it's a composite of three functions, and we can just,
we can just give them names. Let's give them names. Okay. So we start here. So the x squared
will be function h and the output of that will be v. Okay. Then the sinus thing will have name g.
And the input of the sinus is x squared, which we kind of said it's v. Okay. So it's v,
sinus v, which is the sinus. Okay, cool. So we gave it names. And then the exponent function,
the e to something is this function. And we said this sinus x squared is the u. Okay. So what we're
just doing, we're giving in names. So it's easy to see the chain rule. Okay. Everybody's with me
with that? Cool. Just giving names, arbitrary names. This is my decision. I said like, okay,
this is going to be called u, and it's going to be called g, and it's going to be called h and v.
So then these three functions have derivatives, which we can compute. So,
and here comes the ugly notation. I'm using both. So here's this Leibniz notation,
here is the Lagrange notation. So the derivative of function f, which is e to u,
is, what is it? What is derivative of e to something?
E to something, exactly the same. Yeah, this is great about it. So, yeah. So this is the derivative.
E to something is e to something. So the derivation of that is a beautiful function.
And now, okay, so we have the derivative here and some plugging here, because u was
sin x squared, so I'm plugging in here. So we have the derivative of y of the function f,
or I can write dy to du, you know, using this Leibniz notation. Okay. Everybody knows how we
did this. So we basically took this function and make a derivative. And e to u, derivative of that
is e to u. E power u. Okay. Cool. The next function was the u is g of v, and it's a sinus.
And somebody, somehow you learned at high school, like derivative of sinus is cosinus.
So we have now the derivative is cosinus v, and then we plug in the v. So this will be cosinus x
squared. Okay. So we kind of, this is also, we have derivative of that. And then the derivative
of x squared. Okay. We had it already. So it's 2x. Right. So we know. So now we have derivative of
each of these functions. Okay. What is interesting here, that each of the derivatives is using
the output of the previous function, right? Because x squared was the function before.
And here, sinus x squared was the previous function. Right. Yes.
I don't understand why we don't use the chain rule now.
We do use the chain rule. Well, we are computing the.
We say that e to the power of u is,
the derivative of e to the power of u is e to the power of u. Yes. So we're assuming that
u is. We're kind of substituting and making this function simple. That's the point. Because
they're composed. Right. They're simple functions composed together. And before you apply the chain
rule, you have to understand each of these functions and their derivatives to the input.
This is the first thing you. I mean, if you do it by per hand, you say, okay, sure, I know what
is e to u is. And then I'll go deeper. Okay. I'll ask you in five minutes. Okay. For that. Right.
So. So we now know all these derivatives for each of these functions. And now. So this is
repeating again from the previous slide. We computed just before. And now we can use the
chain rule. And the derivative of the whole function at point a is the product of these three
derivatives. Which we computed before, evaluated at a particular point. Okay. So x is a. I'm
avoiding this function. Then this function times this function. So this is the chain rule,
basically. I mean, you would do it like naively, but we do it like explicitly here by applying
really the chain rule for these simple functions. Okay. Does it make sense now? Great. Everybody's
with me now. Still. I know it's after lunch and mathematics after lunch is really terrible. I'm
really sorry about it. I'm recording this on, I'm putting it on YouTube so you can re-watch that.
And there's billions of sources on the internet to do this. I'm doing my way here, which I hope
will kind of enlighten some of us and help us to understand more. If you know it already,
the better. So you get a different view or maybe you're kind of reaffirming your knowledge. Okay.
So everybody's with me here. We took simple functions, make a derivative, and then just
make a product of three of them to get this derivative for the whole thing. Okay. Great.
So now we know how to make a derivative of a complicated function, because if you look
at this function, well, this is not x squared. This is something very weird. It's actually 3
minus sin 2x over x. Can you make a derivative of this function? 3 minus sin 2x over x, just
per hand. Probably. It will take some time and you would have to do this for each of the function,
take a derivative and then make a chain rule. Right. So now we have a really good way how to
do it in a structured way. Okay. That's the point. And now we want to find the minimum of the
function and we don't want to go like the brute force and we're going to take into account the
slope of the function at each point. So what we want to find is such an x that minimizes this
function. So this is the, we call it x hat with a hat here. This is some sort of estimate. Right.
And we're going to use gradient optimization. And what we need for that is that we can
evaluate the function for any x. Right. So we can evaluate it at any point we know what the value of
the function is and we can evaluate its derivatives for any point as well. Right. So now we are much
clever than before because before that, for the brute force, we just needed what the function
values at any point. And we can just go one by one and try and find the minimum. Now we know more
about the function because we know not only the value at each point, but also we know the slope
of the linear approximation of the function. How is it going to be helpful? Quite a lot.
Because we start somewhere, we pick a random value of x. So let's, I don't know, let's start here.
Okay. Now we evaluate the gradient here, not the gradient, sorry, the derivative here,
the derivative, which is the slope of this linear approximation.
And it will be some number, something between here, some positive number. Right.
And then we're going to say, okay, this is the direction and strength of change at this point.
So this was like x1. And then we're going to take this gradient, we just, sorry, this derivative,
we just compute it. Multiply by something, some small constant, and subtract from the actual value.
And we arrive at the next point. What exactly it means? So here we have some positive number,
we multiply by a positive number. So we have some small positive number here.
And we do x1 minus this small positive thing, which moves us somewhere here.
And if this eta constant is small enough, we took a step to something which is smaller
than our previous position. Okay. So we are somewhere, we look, basically,
you know, I have just one direction, and I'm staying at a point. And I only know,
and I only know, okay, in this direction, it's going down.
And I make a step. So the more, you know, the steeper the slope is, the farther I go.
Okay. That's basically it. Because if I'm looking for a minimum, if I'm, you know, if my kind of,
if the slope is just, you know, a very tiny angle, I go just a little bit step,
because I don't want to overshoot, right? If this is big, I'm going a much bigger step.
And I repeat this whole thing over and over. And if I decrease the number of eta,
this is called learning rate, I will find a minimum point. It won't be the global minimum,
it will be maybe a local minimum, but I can come there using much fewer steps than just,
you know, simple brute force search, definitely, or some other methods. Yes?
We already got the derivative, so we can mathematically solve for the minimum one?
Yeah, and no. You can mathematically solve, absolutely. Right? So remember what you just
said. We have a derivative, can we just solve a derivative at high school, like, equals to,
you know, second derivative, you know, the first one equals to zero, then the second,
if it's positive, then it's minimum maximum, right? Yes, for simple functions, absolutely.
I'll ask you in five minutes, okay? Yes?
Talking about 2.3?
Yes.
Isn't it supposed to be like f of x, i plus 1, instead of x, i plus 1?
No, no, no, no, no. Why not? Because we're searching for the x. So we're searching,
we want to find a point where the function will be smaller than at point, so we are at point x1.
Sorry, x1, yes. And if we use this gradient, this function, then the point x2, which will be this
one, sorry, let me see. The point x2 will be smaller than x1, so f x1 will be smaller than f x2.
So we're moving on the x side, and the gradient is telling us where to go,
like, should I go left or right? And then, because you're, basically you're staying on a hill
somewhere, on a slope, and you see, like, well, I have to go this direction, then my function will
be smaller there, so I'm going there. And how much I'm going, this is the strength, you know,
the strength of the slope or the strength of the gradient is how far I should go right now.
I'm changing the x, right, because that's what I want to find. I want to find this x here down.
So I'm changing the next x where I'm going to evaluate, okay, I'm here, what's my function,
what's my derivative, okay, I have to go here again. Does it make sense? I'll try,
so I have an example on the next slide, so maybe it will help again. You have a question?
What is the u? It's just my variable, I just randomly assigned the u to this gradient at the point.
Here, it's this one, it's eta times u.
Yeah, okay, so I want to control how far, how long the step will be,
because the gradient for the function will be always the same, but maybe I want to just,
you know, make shorter steps, so to say. So I'm still taking the gradient into account,
but maybe multiply to some small constant. So maybe the theta will be in something like 0.001
until 1, right, so I'm taking much smaller steps. It's empirical constant, it's just,
you can set it up, it's a hyperparameter, and it's telling like how large step I'm taking
given the gradient. Does it answer your question? Okay, any other questions?
Great, so this is gradient descent, and now we can, you know, how can we do that? Yes, okay,
so let's start, we start randomly, and let's start here, so this is point x1.
I'm coming, so this is where I am, I compute a gradient here, so the gradient will be maybe
sorry, not really, maybe like that, it's not even better, but it's a line, you have to trust me,
okay, so this is a line, and what's the slope? Is it positive or negative here?
It's negative, exactly, so I have negative slope, and then the update rule is xi plus 1 is equal to
xy minus this theta times, let's call it u, right, the gradient. Since this will be,
this is negative, so we'll end up with positive, and I'm gonna, the next step will be this,
plus the size of the gradient times some small constant, so I'm gonna move
to the right. Ah, cool, this is great, this is what I wanted. I'm here,
so doing the same step. Doing the tangent here, so the gradient is still negative, okay, cool,
and the gradient is bigger, so which means the next step will be not the same as here,
but maybe a little bit larger, a little bit now here. Oh, now I'm here, and my gradient is going
to be positive, so the whole thing will be here. I'm substracting a thing, and then I got the
gradient is smaller, so maybe I'm jumping right here, okay, and then maybe I will just jump before
reaching the minimum. Does it make sense? Sounds easy. So what if we start here?
What's gonna happen? Yes? We find a local minimum. Which one?
Yeah, maybe this one, right? If we start here, we maybe have no chance to reach here.
Well, we might, actually. If we have super large learning rate, we might just, okay,
here's my gradient, and the next step, and I'm gonna just overshoot completely here,
given this learning rate, and I might just jump left and right. That's why this learning
parameter is so crucial, because it tells you, are you going tiny steps? I mean, you can. You can go
really, really, really, really tiny steps. It will just take a lot of time to minimize the function,
or you might be overshooting. But here, typically, you would reach a local minimum.
Is it a good thing or a bad thing?
We want a global minimum. So if you reach a... So everybody knows what's a global minimum,
local minimum? Yeah, so global, it's like there is no lower point for the function,
and local is like, yeah, I mean, some neighborhood of this point, this is a minimum.
We want globally, I mean, we want a minimum of the function, we want a global one.
Maybe sometimes the local one is good enough. Sometimes we're just happy with local minimum,
right? But if we have a convex function, so convex function is something which is
like that, then using this gradient-based optimization, we are guaranteed to end up here,
in the global one. If we have function which is like that crazy, then, well,
you end up with some local minimum. Okay, any questions?
Gradient-based optimization or derivative-based optimization for 1D function? Yes?
If you have zero, you're getting in trouble. Yes. Or, well, you might have, if you start,
let me just delete this. So the question was, if you have maybe this function,
and you start exactly here, so the derivative will be zero. Yeah, you're screwed. I mean,
yeah, start again. Or, well, this is, this was the chance that you hit just basically the maximum,
the chance is slow. What might happen is that you will end up in some sort of valley,
I'm sorry, this is not a function, like that, and then there is like nothing happening,
nothing happening, and then maybe there's a minimum. This could be a function.
So you start here, go down here, and now the gradient will be zero, and you're stuck here.
You don't find a minimum. It can typically happen. So zero gradient, bad thing. This would be like
super crazy gradients, almost infinity, also bad thing. So you want to be somewhere in the,
you know, in between. Okay, any other question? So the algorithm stops when you reach a level
where every x plus, x i plus one is equal to the last x i, or? Yeah, the algorithm stops when
you decide to run over compute. So you can, you know, either you're, you're really not decreasing
anymore, or you reach a number of steps for which you're kind of repeating the whole thing.
It's a design choice. You can always check like, well, is it my previous step, is it
still higher, then I continue. But if your previous step was like lower, then you stop, maybe. Yes?
You can do random starts, exactly. You can just, you can do several random starts,
you know, you can start maybe, oh, maybe here first, and then if it fails, and then maybe here,
and then you can try several runs with several random seats and find which is one of the minimum.
You can do that.
Yeah, you want a global minimum, but maybe you have to sacrifice a global minimum, go for a
local minimum in some cases, which we will see later on in training neural networks, okay?
So this doesn't guarantee you convergence. You can try sampling and stuff like that,
but the functions we'll be optimizing are much more complex, complicated, okay?
Any other question or point? Yes?
I think it's called stochastic, I think it's called gradient descent.
I would call it gradient descent, because you take a gradient or derivative,
and then you minimize a function based on derivative. I would call it gradient descent.
It's not stochastic gradient descent, it's not stochastic. Stochastic has a reasoning gradient
descent, and stochastic gradient descent is typical for machine learning, and training
in machine learning, sort of. Because the stochastic comes from sampling a random point.
We're not there yet. This is just taking derivative, minimizing function, okay?
We're not talking about deep learning today at all, which is a good thing, because typically,
when I see lectures on function minimization on training with gradient descent, it's mixed with
neural networks, and then it's like, oh, this layer, and here, oh, this is just, wow.
You can completely decouple these things. You can minimize a function, and then we learn in
the next part how to compute a gradient nicely, and then you just use it for deep learning.
Okay, so let's move on. Now we had function of one dimension to another, but obviously,
the word is more complicated, so we have functions from n dimensions to single number, okay?
An example of such a function, well, I have a beautiful one. Anyone knows name of this function?
Never mind. I think it's called Rosenbrock function. It's a very famous function,
which reads like that, so there's two hyperparameters. You don't have to remember.
This is like a nice function, because it's somehow shown to be hard for optimizing.
Why is it so? Because it looks like a banana, sort of, banana valley, and here's a minimum at
one, one is the minimum, and some techniques, you know, which we are using kind of fail to
find this minimum easily or fast enough and so on, so this is a very famous function.
By the way, if you want to have these plots, I put, so this is from Colab,
and I put links to this Colab plots to the lecture slides to the latex, so if you want to play around
with that, just go to the latex source, and you can find the links to the lecture slides.
So if you want to play around with that, just go to the latex source, and there's a Colab,
which I shared, so you can open it. So this is a nice function, two variables,
x and y, and then, you know, we have 3D. Typically, we have much more dimensions.
Now, we're coming from the simple derivatives to partial derivatives.
So what is partial derivative? It's directional derivative, so it always takes the direction of
one of the dimensions, right? If we have two dimensions, there is one derivative in the
direction of the one axis and derivative in the direction to the other axis, and with respect to
a single variable. So now the terminology or, you know, the naming conventions are kind of hard, so
we're using this weird symbol partial for the derivative. So partial derivative of f with
respect to x2, this is how we write it, and this is how we read it, and if you had this function,
for example, so this is x1 squared times x2 plus cosine of x3, so we have three dimensions.
Can you visualize a function of three variables? No, not virtually not, because we need like the
fourth dimension for actually showing the output, right? So what we can visualize are two inputs,
and the output is like kind of the surface, so we can kind of visualize it and understand
what it means if you have three inputs, three minor dimensions and more. I can't do that.
You know, human imagination is really bound to the world, three dimensions. So, and now,
how we do this kind of partial derivatives is basically we take each variable at a time
and treat the rest as constants, right? So for example, the partial derivative with respect to x1
will be, so this is a constant, this is zero, so it'll be x2, and then derivative of x1 squared
is 2x1, so 2x1 x2, okay? And so on. So who hasn't heard of partial derivatives before?
This is great. So partial derivatives, you know, it's, everybody knows that.
Okay, good. So this is how we compute the partial derivatives per hand,
and then we have a beautiful thing, which is called a gradient. Okay, so here's the example
again, and we end up with derivative metrics or a vector, which is called a gradient of f,
and this kind of ugly symbol is called nabla, or a gradient. So nabla is basically a vector
of partial derivatives for each dimension. Okay, so we have three dimensions, and this is
derivative, partial derivative with respect to the first dimension, to the second dimension,
and third dimension. So here, the derivative of this function will be basically vector of these
three small functions. Okay, any questions? Good, because here the terminology is also kind of
confusing, could be. So, yeah, okay, so what the properties of the gradient is that for any of
these functions and every point x, the gradient points in the direction of the steepest extent of
f at the point x. Well, basically the same thing as with the one dimension. So the gradient, or the
derivative of one dimension is saying like, okay, here's my, so here's how steep my function
goes here at this point. Now, we have, for example, in two dimensions, so the gradient is telling me
I'm staying in a point somewhere in a hill, and the gradient is saying me, or not in a hill, in a valley,
and the gradient is telling me, okay, you have to go that far, this direction is the steepest
kind of, steepest grow of this function in two dimensions. This is what the gradient is telling
me at every point. In two dimensions, it's easy to visualize, you're really sitting in
somewhere, staying in the valley, and just look, okay, here's the steepest estimate. Sometimes we call
the gradient, the function is here, so this is the gradient, but this is not a real number. And sometimes
we call it the vector of concrete numbers computed for the particle input. So this is something
you need to somehow take the context into account, because the gradient could be a vector of numbers,
which is basically the steepest extent at the point, or it could be just, how can I compute that?
Does it make sense? Yes.
So the steepest extent at the point of multiple different extent, and also the point of the steepest extent?
Yeah, the gradient is the way, is the steepest extent at the point, like the one. This is the
vector saying you, okay, you're here, this is my kind of the valley, and here, this is direction of the
steepest extent. Right? Yes.
That's also just local, right?
Yeah, yeah, it's, I mean, you are at a point, and at a point, there is one steepest extent.
Could be a different point pointing somewhere else, right? So it's local, exactly. It's a local
change of the function.
You're using the same method for finding a minima.
I'll go there. You're kind of, have you, okay, you're always like two steps before, that's great. So,
yes, and exactly, because
now we can use it for finding the minima of the multidimensional function, because the gradient is just a,
it's the same thing as for one dimension, but we have it for multiple dimensions. So, we can find a minima,
or we can find a minimum of multivariate or multivariable function, and so we're looking for a vector,
or a position where the function has a minimum. So, we do the same thing as before. We start
somewhere random, so random vector, we have n dimensions, then we compute the gradient at this
point, so now this is the nabla thing. We have still the eta, this is the learning rate, and we update
a step and go somewhere next. And after enough iteration, or some stopping criterion, we have the
minimum as we wanted. Okay, so because, I mean, and now you can really visualize it, like you're
staying, oh, maybe you have an example, right? You're staying somewhere, so this is the Rosenberg
function, okay? You start somewhere here, so, which is like, this is a 3D and this is 2D.
You're starting somewhere in this banana woolly shape, and you're in the middle of the mountain
somewhere, and you say, like, okay, so I cannot play a theater like the banana thing, but you know, you
have to trust me, there's a banana valley here, and I'm staying on the side of the
mountain, and saying, like, what is my biggest slope here? So, it's to the mountain. Okay, I'm not
going to up, I'm going the other direction, which is the minus, I'm going down here, and I just go down
to the woolly. So, I did this large step, because the gradient was huge here, so I just jump here,
basically come here to the next little bit of hill in the middle of bananas, I'm saying, okay,
what's the, you know, the highest steep, okay, so here I'm going to differ the other direction,
downhill to the woolly, and the gradient is getting smaller here, so I'm getting this
next step, and compute the gradient, and x net, and here I'm in the woolly already, which means the
gradient kind of vanishes, it's smaller and smaller, maybe almost zero, because it's almost flat.
So, at each step, I'm getting very small, tiny, forwards to more minimum, more minimum, more
minimum, and then I stop here. Is it the final solution? No, this algorithm didn't make it, the
final, the true minimum is at 1.1 for this function. But the gradient was so small here, that
my stopping criterion told me, like, yeah, I had, like, 100 steps already, and now the changes are
so minimal, I'm stopping here, right, so this is why this function is hard to optimize.
And it's known for being hard to optimize using standard techniques.
Okay, so is the general idea clear? Why are we using the gradient, and what is it telling me?
Any questions?
Great. Okay, so we know how to minimize a single variable function, we know how to minimize
multiple variable functions, so we had this gradient. What's still missing?
We know how to do the gradient descent, but what we didn't touch, really?
Yeah, the step size is the learning rate, it's a hyperparameter, yes, we touched it a little bit.
You can make it smaller, exactly, yeah, we didn't touch it, but there is an even much harder part,
is the, yes,
yeah, the global minimum, I would kind of like, yeah, it would be nice to have, but maybe that's
not, that's unnecessary, the global minimum. No, the point is, so the point is that,
what happens when the functions are super heavily nested, like very nested deep functions, so to say,
right, because what we saw before was the Rosenbrock, beautiful function, you can do it by
hand. Okay, example, we want to minimize this function with respect to w0, w1, to wk. Now,
please, who said it, can you write me a partial derivative? Okay, we need a gradient, right,
we need a gradient for the output with respect to all these dimensions, so we have k dimensions
and very complicated function, well, it's not complicated, it has a name,
and we want to find the gradient. Now, can you, can you, yeah, you can, it's wild, you know,
you can do like, okay, so it's a sum, then the logarithm, so it's like one over, okay, then,
oh, then the sigmoid thing and the, right? Depends on everything, like depends on the k,
but you can do that, but it's kind of, it's getting nested, you don't want to do it by hand.
Anyone remember, you know, anyone knows what the function is, actually? It's, I didn't make it up,
it makes sense, it's one of the, one of the functions we can use in deep learning later on.
So, I think this is, this is binary cross-entropy loss for a log-linear function of k variables.
It's very shallow deep network, in a way, it's just one layer network and a sigmoid on top of
that. We come to that later, but this is, this is the hardest, this is the easiest function you
might be optimizing and it's still hard to kind of find the derivatives. Yes?
No, why should it be a recursive?
Oh, good spot, okay, wow. No, okay, so you know what? I wrote it with the exp, you know, I wrote
it like the exponential function, but it didn't look so hard, so I made it look harder using the
e number, so this could be, yeah, let's, yeah, like that, this is exponential function, good catch,
okay, cool. So, we want a mesh, we want to compute the complicated gradients, right? We want the
partial derivatives for complicated functions which are nested. So, we need chain rule for
multivariable functions and it's getting very nested now. So, there are some rules which we
should maybe know or not or look it up, but there's rules how to do this partial derivatives
for two functions. So, let's say we have,
we have a variable t and two functions depending on the t, so h and g, and then there's one function
z which takes these two functions together, and yeah, so this is the final function, right? This
is a nested function of two inner functions depending on one variable, and we want to find a
derivative or partial derivative of the final function with respect to this, kind of, the single
variable, and we're going to use it, we're going to use this chain rule for multivariable functions.
I mean, there's a proof for that, I'm not going to go deeper into that, but just, yeah, this is how
it is, this is how it works, you can prove it. And it looks ugly, why? Because we have this partial here,
and we have the dx, and what is x, what is y, what is... This is what I meant by, you know,
thousand different ways of writing partial derivatives, because you can write it as well
as like that, so you say it's partial derivative of f, so you're switching z to f to t, and then
using the function names instead of the variable names, and it's correct as well.
So that's why, I guess, most of the material of learning multivariate calculus or multivariate
optimization is just hard to grasp how the author, like, what is, why partial of f and not
for the output function, so because it's arbitrary, it's just one way, you know, to look at this, like,
this is Spanish, and maybe this is French, and they're saying the same thing, it's just a different
kind of naming conventions and stuff like that, so be aware of that, right? It's notation madness.
But this is how you compute a compose function and the chain rule for that, so there is some
multiplication and plus. And then if we have more variables, it's getting more complicated, so we
have blah blah blah. I'm gonna skip it right now, because, I mean, these rules might be important to
look it up, because they later on, we will rely on them, so you've seen them before, but I don't
want you to remember this, I mean, something that you perhaps not know, you don't need to
remember, but know about it, okay? So we have a chain rule. Why was the chain rule good, actually?
Why was it good, the chain rule? Because we could, like, split the function into multiple parts,
and then multiply them together. There's some plus as well, so we will be multiplying and
stitching things together to get a gradient. Okay, cool, let's try it. So let's try an example.
We have still 25 minutes, so I think we'll finish on time. Everybody still with me on board?
It's very ugly mathematics, but I think when we survive, you know, you'll be equipped with,
you know, understanding. So we have a function, so e here is a variable, okay? This is not like
the Euler's number, this is just a variable. e is a plus b times b plus one, so we have two variables,
and we want to compute a gradient with respect to a and b. So if I'm going to ask you,
can you compute this by hand? Yes, easily, that's super easy. So you have the expression,
blah blah blah, and then gradient e to a is b plus one, and so on. This is like high school
mathematics, easy. Okay, well, but let's pretend it's a more complicated function and do something
much more fancy. So we're going to add, again, some intermediate variable and function names.
So this is our function, a something something times something something. So we're going to call
this function f1, and it will have two parameters, r and s, and this is r times s. So basically,
we're just substituting. So this is going to be a product of two things. Then r is going to be our
first parenthesis here, which is a plus b, and the s will be the second parenthesis, b plus one.
Okay, everybody's with me? I mean, it's the same thing as we did before, just substituting and
giving in names, and making, you know, it's small functions. So it's going to be a composition,
basically, of addition and multiplication. Okay, so how can we represent it nicely, in a way?
We can use a thing called computational graph, where we basically say we have notes in the graph,
and this pink or red, so these pink things are the input variables, and these are the
intermediate functions, and they compose to the output function, right? So everybody understands
this graph, how it works? Basically, here I'm saying, okay, r, my function is a parameterized
by a and b, and it was my a plus b function, right? So it was like the first parenthesis, basically.
Kind of this, this one was the second parenthesis, and this is the multiplication.
Okay, everybody understands the graph? So it's a direct, you know, okay, a and b will be some
concrete real numbers, therefore, the r, s, and e will be also concrete numbers. So how do you
evaluate this graph? How do you, if you're given a and b, how do you evaluate the e function? How do
you go about it?
Yeah, you can, exactly, you can, you need to use the topology of the graph. So you say, oh, s depends
on b, then I evaluate r, and then I go to e. Or you can use something different. You can say, oh,
give me e, but e says, well, I don't know r and s, so recursion, okay, give me r. So recursion,
you can say, oh, give me e, but e says, well, I don't know r and s, so recursion, okay, give me r.
Oh, I know a and b, cool, I'm coming back. Oh, s, I need this. Like, basically,
recursion and let it compute itself, like, you know, by calling the children of each node.
This is, and this is basically a standard computational graph. So if you ever program
a calculator, this is most likely what you end up, end it up with, like small functions
stitched together. So it's a direct acyclic graph, but it's not a tree, as we saw before,
because there could be like this diamond shapes. And each node is differential of the function
with arguments. Okay, cool. And the leaves here are the variables or some constants.
And this is the function composition. So the arrow is saying basically, yeah, I need this
to compute, you know, these are the arguments. And r and s are parents of b and a,
of, sorry, r and s are parents, so this is parents of b, and b and a are children of r. Okay,
so this shouldn't be any surprising, this is good. Why is this good? Okay, so let's start. We have
this graph, and can we do something cool about it? So we can now compute each of these numbers,
right? We know what s is, we know what r is, and we know what e is, right? We can do that. We just
say compute everything, forward pass, the topology of the graph, or just recursion, okay?
So we have these numbers. This is great. What's next? So now, because our goal is to compute
the gradient of this function with respect to, so partial derivatives with respect to a and b,
but we start at the top. So we start, we want to compute a gradient for each node
with respect to e, so the output. And we start here, so the partial derivative of e
with respect to e is one. This is something weird, but this is the starting point, like,
it makes sense also from calculus perspective. So you start here and saying, okay, this is one.
Why is it so? Because if you change e, how much is going to e change? Yeah, once. This is
the starting point. So, okay, this is the global output. So the global output is e with respect to
node output, and node output is e as well. Yeah, this is boring. So what should we do next?
For this node, we can compute the partial derivatives with respect to the argument.
So the arguments of this function f1 are r and s. So we're going to compute partial derivative of e
to r, or with respect to r, and partial derivative of e with respect to s. Can we compute that?
Can we compute what is derivative of e to r? So our function is r times s, right? So what is going
to be the derivative with respect to r? s, exactly. And what is going to be derivative of e to s?
r, yes, exactly. We just do the simple function and compute the derivatives here. We can do that.
So we know how to compute these things. By the way, these will be real numbers, right? I mean,
this is just how we compute them, but at the end of the day, these will be some real numbers.
All right, so yeah, let's move on. Oh, by the way, we know what s and r is, because we just
computed them already before in the forward pass. So we're just going to reuse the computation.
We don't have to compute them again. You know, we started here. Oh, okay, this is going to save
some time. Everybody's with me in this step? Local derivations with respect to the arguments
of the function. Now we're moving next, and we're saying, okay, let's look at the children
of this e node. So let's start maybe with r. And again, I'm going to compute the global
derivatives, so the partial of e with respect to this output of this function, with respect to r.
And now what's kicking in is the chain rule, right? Because I know that e is a compose of f1
and r is in there. So I'm going to use the chain rule and just basically multiply these partial
derivatives. So this is where the chain rule of multivariate calculus comes in, and I'm using
that for computing this sort of gradient, this partial derivative, excuse me. And you might be
wondering, oh, I'm computing partial derivative of e with respect to r. I have it here already.
Yeah, here it makes no sense, but later on we'll see it will make a lot of sense. But now,
actually, I can reuse the same value here, but I'm just going to compute. What I need for this
computation is the parent, it's coming from here, times the local derivative from here.
This is the chain rule in praxis. Okay, so I can compute it. Very cool. So I'm moving next,
to next child of e, and I'm going to do the same thing. So I'm going to compute
partial derivative of e with respect to s, which is the parent times the local.
This is the chain rule. Okay, everybody's with me? Why do you do this? And it's also nice to
graphically, I'm taking like the derivative of the parent, multiply by the path, and this is how to
get the derivative of this point. This is pretty cool. Okay, sounds great. So what's the next step?
What are we looking at now? Where should we go? What should we avoid next?
So, yeah, we started on top and got this thing, then we computed the local derivatives
of this function, of this node. We're here, get a global, here get a global,
so maybe we should go deeper here and compute the partial derivatives of this function with
respect to its arguments. So again, this function f2 of a and b is a plus b.
Okay, so, and now the parents are a, sorry, the children are a and b. So what is going to be the
derivative of r with respect to a? What is the partial derivative of r with respect to a?
If this function is this one? It's going to be one, sorry, yes, one, exactly, because b is a constant,
so it's zero, and a is going to be one. Okay, good. What's going to be the derivative of r with respect to b?
One as well, yes, exactly. So this is a local function, we can how to compute the derivatives.
This is very easy. So I ended up with these derivatives, and okay, this is cool. I'm going to
do, I'm going to go deeper now, and I'm taking the child of r, which is going to be a.
And now I'm going to compute again the same thing, so global output with respect to this node output,
and this node is already the input, so this node output is given. And then again I'm using,
okay, what I'm using here, so dE of, with respect to r, which I computed before, okay, I'm taking
just the derivative, you know, the parent thing, and I'm again multiplying by the transition here,
by the local derivative. So basically I'm always taking the parent's global derivative
by multiplying the local derivative. That's all I do, all the time. And here, voila, what we have,
partial derivative of E with respect to A. This is what we wanted, this is, I mean, we wanted to
compute a gradient, this is one part of the gradient, right, this is one of the variables,
and we have the gradient of the output given the input. So this is cool. Let's finish.
So the next step is, obviously, we're going to look at the children of S node, and here again we have
a partial derivative of S with respect to B, which is going to be, okay, what is this function, f3,
B plus 1. So what is this going to be equal to? One, exactly, very easy. Okay, so we have that.
And now what's the last point in our recursion, how we travel in the graph, is the B. And now
we're going to compute, okay, so we want the global with respect to this node, and here this
node has two parents, right. So what I'm going to do is to use this rule for, chain rule for
multivariate functions with, you know, multiple parent nodes, and basically I'm taking here
the one parent times the transition,
plus the other parent times this transition derivative, and stitching them together. So
this is the multivariable chain rule. And this is how I ended up with the gradient.
Oh, it's very kind of complicated, clumsy and so on, but are you still with me? Now everybody
kind of could follow what we're doing here? Very tiny steps. We are interested in the global
derivative with respect to something which is on the nodes. And the way we got there,
just applying the chain rule on each of these sub nodes, and going by the next children,
the next children, the next children, and now, voila, we ended up with the gradient of this
function with respect to A and B. This is the gradient of the function. And we, and basically
these are numbers now, because we had, you know, we had A and B were real numbers, these were real
numbers, this was real numbers, all the gradients were real numbers, so we ended up with a vector
of real numbers. So we kind of avoided the gradient of this function at points A and B.
In a very weird way, but at the same time, in a very cool way. Because we are clever.
You know, we didn't do it like, oh, you have to compute a gradient per hand and make it like
formula. We are just transferring first from the bottom up, computing all the outputs of
each of the nodes, and then from the top to bottom to find the gradients in order to get the
gradient of the input nodes as the result. This is what we wanted. And by caching, yes, I get you,
by caching the intermediate values, we're just reusing them all the time. Yes?
I just wanted to ask, what's the WRT?
What does it stand for?
W, with respect to, okay, sorry. WRT is with respect to. Okay? So we're having
global partial derivative with respect to node output. This is what it means. Okay.
Any other question? Is it, maybe it doesn't spark a joy, but this is how basically how
everything works under the hood. It's called, what's it called? I don't know, maybe we'll get to
that. Okay. So now what is actually, so we did just very tiny, tiny little things for each of
the nodes. We build a computational graph and then computed a gradient. So a generic node in a
computational graph can have multiple parents here and multiple arguments. Right? So this is what we
have locally. And maybe it goes somewhere here to the output. And this function, what we need to
compute is that the, you know, if we have the output here will be E, not the Euler's number,
but just E as a maybe error. Then we need to take all the parents of this node, all the parents and
multiply by their transition derivatives. Sorry, it's not transition derivatives, it's derivatives
with respect to this function output. Right? That's what we did. It's just, we're assuming up
over all parents of this node and their global derivatives times this, the local derivative.
And it's chain rule for this node. Right? And then we can compute also for each node,
we can compute again their local derivatives with respect to its children. Right? And we're
doing recursively that in the topology of the graph. And we end up with all the global gradients
to each node, including the inputs. So which means if we want to implement this, each of the nodes
must be a function which we need to compute the output value of this function. Yeah, it makes
sense. I mean, function typically has to output a value. So we can do that. And we have to know
how to compute a partial derivatives with respect to its function parameters. So if we have function
of a, b, c, d, we have to know how to evaluate the function for a, b, c, d, and how to compute
partial derivatives with respect to a, with respect to b, c, and d. What we just did
is called backpropagation, or reverse mode differentiation. And it has two parts. So one
is the forward computation. Basically, we compute all nodes output, and we store it there because
we're going to use it for gradients. And then we started from top and computed overall function
partial derivatives with respect to each node. And that's it. This is how you find a gradient
of various super complicated function, including what I showed before. Yeah, I mean, this, can you,
sorry, can you turn this into a conditional graph? Yes, yes, you can. It's just stitching
functions together. So you say, OK, I have a function which is sum of this. This will be a
product. There will be a logarithm. Then this will be arguments, and so on, so on.
I mean, it's not trivial, but it's fairly easy to get a graph of this function,
and then compute, basically use the backpropagation to compute a gradient for every input.
OK, so where did I stop here? This, backpropagation. So recap, we can express any arbitrarily complicated
function from multiple dimensions to one dimension as a computational graph. We can do that,
absolutely. We can parse the function as humans and make it a graph. And this nodes will be maybe
is a function, which you know how to make a derivative with respect to its inputs.
And then for computing gradient at concrete point, we run the forward pass and the
backpropagation. And when we are caching the each intermediate output of each node,
we avoid repeating computations. And then this is like efficient algorithm
for finding the gradient of a function at a certain point.
Any questions?
Will you be able now to implement minimizing a function of, let's say, the Rosenbrock or this
kind of very nasty function? Will you be able to do that? I guess so. I think you have everything
you need to do to implement it. Well, there's tricks. You need to find, you know, you need a way
how to compute this, how to build a graph, the computational graph. Yeah, but if you're doing,
I don't know, like in Python or object oriented, you make a node and stitch them together, like
parent node relationship. So you can build a graph. Then it's easy. You need a topology or
you can take each node, each function and make the topology per hand. You say, OK, the ordering
of the nodes is like that. So you know where to start with. So you would say maybe for this input,
you would say, OK, the topology will be A, B, R, S, E. And then you know how to avoid,
you know, in a loop. So that's also easy. That's possible. So I guess, you know,
that should be possible to do. Is it? I know. And then the devil is in the detail,
you know, how to make it efficient and bug free and so on. But basically, this is it.
So we can quite efficiently find the minimum of any differentially nested multivariate function.
This is what we learned today. We can find, we have multivariate nested function,
very deep, very complicated, you know, different paths and so on. So it's not a tree. It's really
like a graph. And we can find the minimum. How? Well, we have this gradient descent,
which takes you at each point to the best next solution. It's local, locally, local move.
And then, so this is the easy part, is the gradient kind of descent, like, OK, I need a
gradient here and I'm coming the next step. How to compute a gradient for this each point? Yeah,
we're using backprop. So you can effectively compute the gradient automatically without,
like, writing on the paper this complicated function and what's the analytical solution
to this, you know, to partial derivative with respect to that partial derivative.
You don't need that. You just need all these tiny functions have to be differentiable. You have to
know how to create their partial derivatives. But that's all. And the function composition will just
work out of box. We didn't touch neural networks at all, which is a good thing. I think it's a
really good thing because it comes with a lot of, you know, a lot of terminology and a lot of kind
of their own naming conventions and matrices and things like that. And I think it makes it super
complicated to understand gradient descent and backprop, because backprop is just a general
way of computing gradients for multivariate functions. It has nothing to do with neural
networks. It just works for neural networks to train them well and effectively. But you can do,
you know, if you do, I know, where would you like minimizing functions, like in physics and
something, you know, did you do any function minimization before somewhere? Where?
Math? OK, yeah, yeah, OK, cool. Like numerical mathematics, right? In numerical mathematics,
you have multiple ways of minimizing function. I think this is actually called conjugate gradient
descent. Mathematically correct, maybe. You have numerical methods, and now you have one which is
kind of very good for multivariate functions, and you can find a minimum. Yeah, that's cool.
It will be super useful next lecture for training neural networks, because neural networks are
just complicated functions, nothing more. OK, any question?
Very good. Thanks a lot. I'll see you next week.