Okay, we're complete.
We're sold out.
That's great.
Welcome to Deep Learning for NLP, 2023 edition.
My name is Ivan Habernal, and this is Martin Dutek.
I'll introduce ourselves later on again.
Come in, yes, come in.
There's still free seats.
So you have to be creative, but you'll find.
This is not the biggest room at university,
and this is not definitely the best room
for actually seeing something on the screen
just from the middle, I'm sorry about it.
I complained, and they said, I don't know,
something like, yeah, we're short of lecture rooms
or whatever.
So there is only one cool thing about this lecture hall
is it has air condition.
So in summer, we love it.
I can guarantee you, okay?
But that's the only advantage of this room, I'm sorry.
Okay, so let's get started.
Can you see something at least on the slides?
If you can see anything on the slides,
take your note, iPad, whatever you have,
and you can download the slides
and just have a local copy so you can read locally.
I'll show you where to get it.
So, okay, let's start with some motivation
while we're here.
So deep learning for NLP.
Let me ask a question.
So who has studied something with NLP,
natural language processing?
Raise your hand, natural language processing.
Okay, cool, thanks.
Deep learning.
Wow.
Okay, cool, why are you here?
Okay, wait.
Yeah, that's it.
Machine learning, it's deep learning, yeah, okay, cool.
So why are we here?
What's your motivation to be here if you studied already?
So those people who study deep learning and NLP,
why are you here?
I studied deep learning, specifically for NLP.
Okay, is there something like specific deep learning
for NLP?
Well, I hope so, I hope so.
But times are changing.
Any other motivation to be here?
Because I listened to podcast with Richard Socher.
Okay.
And I was like, yeah, I want to know more.
Oh, that's cool.
Okay, so you listened to podcast with Richard Socher.
Okay, Richard, Richard Socher, Socher, he's German.
Okay, cool, so the motivation why to be here,
there's so many things, but this is it.
GPT-4, is there anybody in the room
who hasn't used JetGPT or GPT-4 or JetGPT?
Anyone haven't heard of JetGPT?
So I don't think we need more motivation for this course.
We need to understand the thing.
We need to learn it.
After this course, you should be able to build it,
but not to train it.
Unless you work for big companies like Google, Meta,
or the UKP lab, or my lab.
No, well, we don't have so many resources,
but the goal is to learn more about this
and understand it as much as possible.
So we stitched together a little bit of roadmap,
and this is something which will update a little bit,
but here you have a little bit of overview
what's coming up to you, so you can look it up later on.
And we're trying to pack as much as possible,
and we'll have two guest lectures at the end,
and we'll have some buffer as well.
But this is something which roughly will be around.
So first, logistics, what we're gonna do.
So we're two lecturers, and I'm the first one.
I'm Ivan, nice to meet you.
I'm leading the TrustLHLT group,
which I'll introduce later on.
And it's my pleasure to introduce you also,
Martin Tutek.
Say hi.
Oh, okay.
And Martin is a postdoc at the UKP lab from Irina Gurevich,
and we're jointly basically running this course
with a couple of other people, the tutors,
so Martin, Mingwu, Doanam, Yanran, and Hatice,
who will be helping us with the exercises and homework,
so I'll get to that.
So, and we'll be splitting the lectures, basically.
I'll take the first six lectures,
then Martin will take over and take the rest,
like seven until 12, and then we'll have this guest lecture.
This is the plan, roughly.
Great, any questions so far?
That's not a case.
If you wanna sit down,
we have really a couple of places somewhere,
but you just have to be creative
and somehow push the people a little bit.
Sorry, yeah.
So let's move on.
Okay, so this is a live course, excuse me.
So we're doing live lectures,
but also we have a couple of online resources
to make it more kind of bringing to the 21st century.
So obviously, we have Moodle.
I'll be, the user interface from 2007 is still here,
so I think it's cool again, like the 90s.
So we have Moodle.
It's horrible, but it's official and it works,
so go there and sign up for Moodle,
because all the announcements will be done there.
There's discussion forums,
so you can ask questions there as well.
We'll use Moodle mostly for the exercises and the homeworks.
The lectures are, this is the next point,
lectures are on GitHub.
So all these PDFs are open source on GitHub,
so you can download the PDF, the LaTeX code if you want.
You can just use it whatever reasons you want.
This is Creative Commons by license.
And we also bring it to the 2023,
so I set up the Discord channel.
So sign up to the Discord.
I mean, all these links are in the slides as well,
so you can download the slides and have the links.
Go to Discord, which brings the user experience
really to 2023, and we'll use it for basically,
I don't know, like addressing your questions,
maybe some announcements.
It's more unofficial, but don't be nasty, okay?
So it's like your typical Discord channel.
I don't know what you do on Discord,
but you can use nicknames, I don't mind,
but just behave wisely.
You can reach us on one of those things,
but typically not on Discord on the weekend.
So if you ping me on Discord,
the day before the exam, it's gonna be Sunday.
I'm sorry.
Also, we're gonna, I mean,
the plan is that we record the lectures
and put them on YouTube, right?
So I'll post it somewhere to Moodle then,
the link to the YouTube lectures.
And the thing is,
you know, it's better to participate here
because you can make it more interactive.
At least if you have questions, you can ask here.
And also on YouTube, I mean, I'm using microphone here,
so you will hear me,
but you won't hear the questions from the audience
or the discussion from the audience,
which is kind of another great experience.
So the idea is to put it on YouTube for your reference,
if you wanna watch it later,
maybe just to refresh a couple of things.
So, and because we're on YouTube,
you know, subscribe, like.
No, I mean, it makes me happy.
You know, if I see a like,
you know, if I put something on Moodle,
it's like, ah, yeah.
If I post it on Discord and I see like a like,
you know, my brain starts, you know,
I get, how's it called?
Endorphins, you know, release,
and it makes me happy, you know,
because it's social media in the works.
Anyway, so YouTube channels, it's the same thing, you know.
Anyway, but we're not doing it
for the sake of getting likes on YouTube.
So resources, we'll, okay,
there is no textbook for the whole course.
There's two reasons for that.
Deep learning for NLP or deep learning,
the field is evolving so rapidly that, you know,
if you write a textbook two years later,
you can use half of it.
Second, we're using freely available resources mostly.
So everything we use, you can get for free legally.
And basically the top-notch research
in natural language processing is also open source.
So basically the community of research in NLP
is kind of centered around the Association
for Competition Linguistics, shortly ACL,
and they run a couple of conferences,
and the ACL conference, NACL, and so on.
So you'll see citations to those conferences
and all the papers are kind of freely available there
in the anthology or archives.
So we're gonna use basically public resources.
If there's something which you need to read,
I'll let you know.
Most of the links, the references are just
that you can really go to the sources
and get more material if you're interested in topic.
Any questions?
Good.
Exercises and homeworks.
So we have exercises,
which is something that you do on your own,
and you should deepen your understanding of the matter,
and this is not great.
This is something for you to take it
from a little bit different angle
and try something hands-on,
which is related to the topics we're discussing.
If you wanna use JetGPT for exercises, do it.
I'm fine.
Will you learn something from using JetGPT for exercises?
I don't know, but it's a nice experience.
Use whatever you choose you want.
If you wanna cheat the whole course, you can do it easily.
That's fine.
Maybe except for the exam.
I'm not sure.
I haven't seen so many people cheating on the exam
because I use the same exam.
Can I say it?
I used the same exam over maybe two years, maybe,
and the distribution of errors was most of the same.
So that's fine, but don't cheat.
I mean, it's up to you.
You have to know why you're here.
Then we have homeworks.
Yeah, this is maybe a bigger issue for homeworks.
So it's basically some programming exercises
where you really, really, really get your hands dirty,
and you'll be doing something, some programming.
It's a bigger class, so we have groups of two.
So you have to pair up with somebody
will post the logistic exactly on Moodle.
And this is graded.
And if you achieve over roughly 70% of the points,
you will get a bonus for the exam.
It's not much.
So basically it's for you to get them dirty hands
and try something, code something.
And the bonus is just a bonus.
I would recommend to do it anyway,
because you learn something.
If you wanna use GPT for that, I'm fine.
But maybe you won't learn that much.
So if you do it only for the bonus points,
then I would say like, let it go.
So this is not set up yet.
How exactly, how many exercises and so on,
exercises and homeworks, because we're just starting
and we have the team ready with tutors.
We're meeting this week to set it up.
So there will be an exercise, I guess, next week,
the first one, and then the homeworks will follow, okay?
Any questions?
Yes.
So the exercises will be roughly weekly.
Homeworks will be overall, I guess,
four or five homeworks in total.
So not a weekly basis.
Some will be bigger programming things, some shorter.
Another question, yes.
No, do it on your own.
So it's just single.
These are mostly like theoretical
or you just read something and make up, you know,
trying to address an issue
instead of just really programming the project, okay?
Anything else?
Good.
Final exam.
Save the date.
It's Monday, July 31.
So 31st at leaked visa.
If you've never been to leaked visa, it's not really nice.
The Mensa is as good as here,
but they have this huge lecture hall.
So there are four rooms, but it's one.
And it fits, I guess, you know, a thousand people or so.
So we'll be there.
Yeah, come in.
And it's just a standard exam.
So you register to come and yeah, okay.
The language, so you might have noticed
this course will be held in English,
at least for me, from Martin as well,
the guest lectures from Timur as well.
And maybe Thomas will do it in German, but I don't think so.
I think everything will be in English, okay?
So the final exam, the questions will be in English as well.
And you can answer in any meaningful language you want.
So English or German or something else,
which we do not understand.
I mean Czech, Croatian, and Timur speaks five languages.
So you can choose your language, okay?
But we don't speak Chinese, I'm sorry.
So the, you know, how big the exam,
so the exam basically, I think it took like an hour.
Was it an hour?
It takes an hour and it should be fun.
I mean, people kind of get, you know,
if you ask people from previous years, they will say,
yeah, it was kind of fun, but hard.
So don't ask, yeah, I mean, it can be easy, right?
I mean, it makes no point, but it should be,
it should make sense.
And we tried to, we tried hard to make it somehow realistic.
One thing is that I don't have exams
because we reused the exams from last year.
Don't ask me for exams, you know, from last year.
I'm not sharing them because it takes a painful lot of time
to create a new exam.
So maybe we'll reuse a part of that.
So if you ask me, oh,
what is it's close available from this lecture?
I say, I don't know.
And that's true because I don't know,
because we'll do the exam June
and then we'll see how much we covered
and what's kind of makes sense to ask you
or what we're kind of expecting, you know,
that you should understand.
But the same thing we were saying in the lectures,
like what, you know, what are you learning and why?
Why is it important?
Okay, any question to the exam?
Good, so it will be standard paper writing exam.
You don't need anything, no calculator, nothing.
Okay, so this is not online.
It will take some time to grade the exams,
a couple of weeks in summer
because you're a larger crowd.
Obviously, this is not only my course or mine and Martin's,
so it should be more interactive
and your feedback matters actually.
So, you know, whatever you like or dislike, tell us.
Put it on Discord, write in the forums, send us an email.
Any questions you might have, yeah, come in.
Any questions you might have, you can approach us easily.
The email addresses are there as well,
so if you want to send us email, that's fine.
What we're trying to do is to post some anonymous feedback
forms just to get feedback, you know,
because it's important, like you never know
whether you covered everything well or not,
so you're trying to make it really more open source,
you know, which means build it yourself,
so your feedback matters.
And we'll take it into account.
And the same for slides, so if there's issues,
typos, whatever in the slides, it's LaTeX,
so who, okay, who doesn't know LaTeX here?
Just, I'm curious, who doesn't know LaTeX?
Fine, okay, cool, so the majority, great.
So if you see something wrong in the slides,
who doesn't have a GitHub account?
GitHub account, everybody has one?
Okay, that's brilliant, okay, cool.
So whatever you see is wrong here,
just open a issue on GitHub, any feedback issue on GitHub,
pull request, whatever, that will be really awesome.
All right, and I think we're through mostly.
I'll shortly introduce my research group.
Martin, if you wanna leave, then you feel free
because you have a pretty tight deadline, so thanks a lot.
Say hi to Martin, see you in five lectures.
Okay, so a little bit of introduction, who are we?
And Martin will introduce himself once he starts
his lectures later on, and I'm gonna introduce
a little bit of my group.
It's called Trustworthy Human Language Technologies.
What does it mean?
It means many things, but mainly,
we are dealing with privacy.
So we're looking into privacy-preserving
natural language processing.
What does it mean to protect privacy of you?
If you're part of the data somewhere
and we're training with your data,
can we protect your privacy if it's natural language text?
So it's also a little bit tricky.
What we're using is differential privacy,
and deep learning is definitely the tool of the day,
graph metrics and so on.
So this is our research.
If you're interested in what we're doing,
just go to the website and look at the papers.
We have maybe some talks as well.
And the second part is argument mining that matters.
So what does it mean?
Well, if you argue,
if you argue on the internet, mostly it doesn't matter,
but if you argue in front of the court on the case,
maybe it matters more.
So we're looking into arguments at the court,
so how people argue in front of the European Court
for Human Rights, for instance,
and we're trying to analyze the arguments,
the patterns from the legal perspective as well.
So this is more interdisciplinary research,
legal NLP, legal argument mining,
which means also,
if you're interested in doing master's thesis,
or if you're interested in doing a heavy job,
like a student research assistant, just get in touch.
We have a couple of postings.
We're desperately always looking for people
who are motivated to learn something
and do something for research.
Talk to us.
We have a couple of postings.
Check out the website.
We're just looking now for at least three persons now
who can do some coding
or people who actually speak more languages
because we're doing, for the ECHR project,
we need people speaking French, I guess,
or maybe other languages,
and doing some data analysis there.
So get in touch.
Any questions?
Yes.
Are the trust NLP, is that part of UKT
or is it a different path?
That's a great question.
Whether we are part of UKP or not.
So yes and no, officially not.
So this is like independent research group
and I'm independent research group leader.
So I'm sort of independent by definition,
but we are cooperating closely with UKP,
which means we're sitting, we're sharing some offices,
we're sharing hardware,
and we're closely collaborating on research projects as well.
But I'm independent of UKP,
but we are really on good terms.
So Martin is basically postdoc at UKP.
I used to be a postdoc at UKP before and so on.
So, but we're independent.
Any other question?
Anyone wants to get a job?
No, not really.
Oh, come on.
Okay.
Later.
I'll convince you.
Okay, good.
Let's move on.
Let's move on to the actual content.
So let me just take it down.
So the actual content of this lecture
is not about the history of deep learning
because everybody knows it from you.
It's not about the perceptron,
which everybody starts with like,
oh, how can I even build a perceptron?
And you know, it's not about that.
And we're taking a twist a little bit here
and we're starting from the end.
We're starting from some NLP tasks and their evaluation.
And why is that so?
So why should we learn this?
Why should we do this?
I mean, it's important to ask like,
why should I learn something about NLP task?
I want to build tools.
I want to build GPT force and this is cool.
So I don't care about the tasks.
Well, my perspective on that is that deep learning
is just a tool, it's any other tool.
And we need to understand why we need this tool
in the first place.
Why do we need it?
What are we going to solve it?
And how do we know?
This is the right tool for our task.
Like, is it a good hammer?
But if you're not hammering nails, then why hammer?
So we need to understand what the task are we solving
and whether we're good at it or not objectively.
So we're kind of starting to set up the scene.
Why do we need this?
And we'll start with sort of like typology of the tasks.
So what is a task?
Why are people talking about tasks and benchmarks?
What does it mean?
So basically, basically very, very kind of course typology
working with text is that either you do text classification
or you do text generation roughly, roughly, roughly, roughly.
Okay, there is more flavors to that.
And we'll see at the end,
maybe you can cast everything as one task,
but roughly and historically you can classify texts
or you can create text, generate text.
So let's start with the classification a little bit.
And I'm gonna go through,
let's say some typical tasks and their data sets.
So then once you see them later on, like doing, I don't know,
doing master thesis, going to the industry somewhere
and seeing, oh yeah, yeah, this is this task.
It rings a bell.
So you know it exists
and it's well-established in research and the practice.
This is the goal, you know, what's there?
Which tasks are typical?
You know, what people are trying to solve.
So let's start with something which is super, super,
super simple to solve, at least theoretically.
And it's the sentiment classification of movie reviews.
Okay, so those of you who did NLP
and maybe some deep learning,
who of you did something with sentiment analysis
of reviews or movies?
Okay, not many.
Okay, great.
So what did you do?
You used exactly this data set.
Okay, cool.
So what did you build?
Ensemble learning.
Okay, wow.
That's wild.
Okay, good.
Yeah, random first.
Wasn't deep learning.
And I didn't use any like a complex word
or anything, it just was back and forth.
Okay.
Okay, cool.
Anyone else who did it?
You raise your hand.
So what did you do?
Classification model for tweets.
So what did you do with tweets?
Like sentiment for tweets?
Okay, great.
So my question is like, why did you do it?
Why tweets?
Why classification of tweets?
Yeah, it was false.
Okay, good.
Yes, okay.
Somebody told you to do it, so you did it, right?
Okay, so you didn't ask like,
well, yeah, I mean, that's a fair reason, right?
So you didn't ask like, why the heck should I,
like, what is sentiment analysis Twitter?
You know, I don't care.
Yes, you have a point.
For tickets.
Oh, for tickets, okay.
I see a movie of your angle having to prioritize the ticket.
So if the customers are more angry,
then you would try to prioritize it higher.
I wouldn't do it the other way.
I mean, I would really put, you know,
the anger one put on hold and, you know,
just relax and I'll get to you.
Okay, okay.
Happy customers.
Okay, that makes sense.
So exactly, so sentiment,
so let's thank you for your input.
So sentiment classification of movie reviews.
Basically it's a binary classification,
mostly of reviews from IMDb.
I'm talking about this particular paper from Andrew Maas
and others from ACL 2011.
This is the IMDb data set, right?
The IMDb data set, which you download somewhere.
And it's, here's an example.
I look into that and it's like,
I think the shortest review there.
Read a book, forget the movie,
which is negative, obviously against the movie.
And basically you have negative and positive labels there.
What you need to understand,
what you need to understand to classify the review
of a movie into positive or negative sentiments,
like bad movie or good movie,
is a semantic compositional it is.
So how words work together in their meaning,
and also if the movies are long, the reviews are long,
how one part from the beginning is related to the rest,
because you have long dependencies in the text.
You need to, maybe you need to understand,
maybe not, it's just maybe a few words like ugly and so on.
But here, there's no such a word.
Read a book, forget a movie.
So you need to understand what it means.
It's not easy.
Like there's no word signaling like
this is a negative thing.
You need to understand the contrast between movie and book.
What does it mean?
Like forget the movie.
And so on.
So anyone did digit recognition or MNIST?
Who does know MNIST?
What MNIST is?
Okay, what is MNIST?
If all the most basic imitators are in traffic.
Exactly, exactly.
So for computer vision people,
MNIST is just a bunch of digits,
and you classify the image of the digit
into the actual digit.
And everything you try in deep learning
for computer vision, you have to try on MNIST.
It's like the litmus paper.
So IMDB is sort of for NLP, the MNIST.
You should try it on IMDB to see whether it works.
You have new model.
If you don't try IMDB and claim this is really great,
or it used to be like that at least.
It's like a standard data set,
which you pull out of box and try something.
How is my random forest working on IMDB?
81%, 83%, 86?
Something like that.
86% accuracy, I would say.
Something around, I mean if it's 50-50,
then you're like oh, that is bad.
So the question is, why is it interesting?
Why was it interesting?
Why sentiment of movies?
Why is it interesting?
Why people start using movie reviews
for predicting the sentiment of the text?
Why movie reviews?
Probably because of the bunch of data,
which is already labeled.
Nice, yes.
Very opportunistically, there's a bunch of data somewhere
which is labeled.
How labeled?
What does it mean?
I don't know how IMDB rating works,
but probably like one to five stars.
Exactly, somebody wrote the review
and say like it's one star, four stars, five stars.
So people say, yeah, okay,
so everything which is one star is negative.
Everything five stars is positive.
You scrape it from the internet
and then you have a data set for free.
That's one reason.
Any other reason why people,
yeah, so this is like very opportunistic.
Okay, so it's like, it's a variety of language there
from different people, that's what you were saying.
Yeah, that's a great point.
So one of the pioneers of this data set
or of this task was Lily and Lee
and they had a paper in 2004
on classifying reviews on Twitter.
And she gave a talk and she said
the reason why they started with the movie reviews,
one of the reasons was a variety of the language
and she said the beauty of language.
Because these reviews, well not this one,
this is really short and kind of really to the point,
but most of movie reviews are kind of poetic
and nice to read and very kind of figurative language
which 20 years back was considered something
super hard to understand for machines.
So they say like, well if a machine
can kind of understand the sentiment
of this long review in this kind of figurative language,
this would be an achievement
and it was fun to read them as well.
So there's different motivations why people do it.
Like you have to do this for customers.
Satisfaction, yeah, that's a clear goal.
Somebody is just curious and is like,
yeah, this is a nice language so we should understand it.
And then somebody, and you have data for free,
so absolutely, this is the killer, exactly.
Okay, any questions?
So where do you get the data?
Where do you get it?
Yes?
You can scrape IMDB, exactly.
How do you get the data in 2023?
I mean this is great, this is a great answer,
but you can, there's easier way.
Hugging face, exactly.
So hugging face is a collection of now,
what is it, 28,800 something data sets
which somebody did the dirty job for you
and collected and put it there in a nice format
so you can just take it out of box
and run your random forest thing
and just don't care about what's the language,
beauty of language and labels and so on.
Which is great, but you have to understand what's behind
if you're serious about it.
So you go to the Hugging Face data set
and you download through API or whatever
so you can get data sets.
So and as I said, like the IMDB data set,
well you have to be really sure
if you talk about data set, you cite it
and maybe link what exactly,
because IMDB you can scrape anytime you want
and you have different data set.
But you have to compare apples to apples
so everybody should use the same data set
if they're comparing systems, right?
Okay, any questions to sentiment analysis on movies?
So the IMDB data set, the litmus paper.
You should somehow remember there's a thing
like IMDB data set because everybody's using them.
Cool, let's move on.
So there's another task which is called
natural language inference.
And the standard paper for natural language interest
is the SNLI, the Stanford Natural Language Inference task.
What does it mean?
We have two sentences.
And these are somehow related to each other.
And either they're related as an entitlement
or contradiction or they're neutral.
And these two sentences are called a text and a hypothesis.
And the text is here in this example,
a soccer game with multiple males playing,
with basically, yeah, come in.
So it's basically describing a scene, right?
There's a soccer game with multiple males playing.
And the hypothesis text is some men are playing sport.
And the goal is when you hear the text,
so the text is true, is the hypothesis true as well?
So if I tell you a soccer game with multiple males playing,
is it true that some men are playing sport?
Yes, it's true.
If there's a soccer, you know,
if males playing soccer somewhere,
it's true that some men are playing sport, right?
Does it make sense?
So this is entitlement.
If the second sentence would be a soccer game
with multiple males playing,
and the sentence would be, yeah,
a butterfly is sitting on a flower,
it would be like neutral because there is no relationship.
If the second sentence would be some women are playing sport,
it would be contradiction
because we have multiple males playing, right?
So we have three kind of three different labels
for two sentences, how they work together.
So the standard paper is the SNLI paper,
and it's almost 600,000 of these sentence pairs.
So they took a lot of money, hired some persons
like crowd workers on Amazon Mechanical Turk,
and let them write these kinds of things
and collected a bunch of almost half a million
human written English sentence pairs.
So it's really a huge data set,
and they do some in labeling for balanced classification.
So it's balanced data set.
So, and the difference here between the IMDb before
is that, yeah, sorry, it's really low,
so you can't see that, but just, you know,
open your local slides and just follow.
That IMDb was for free, right?
You scrape it from the internet,
you get the stars and call it a day.
Here, you have to pay people to do it.
And I think they paid a lot of money
to create this data set, 600,000 pairs.
How many of these pairs can you write in an hour?
How many pairs can you write in an hour?
What you're gonna do after writing 60 pairs of that?
You're gonna hate it.
You know, you're gonna hate a job because it's terrible.
I mean, it's not fun.
So that's why you need a lot of, you know,
a large pool of people and just, you know, kind of scale up.
Half a million sentences is a lot.
Which brings me to one sort of side step,
and it's the gold standard data.
So what does it mean?
It might have multiple meanings.
So many data sets are annotated by experts, you know,
and it could be super costly.
And in these examples, each example is annotated
by multiple annotators.
So annotator is somebody who's kind of annotating the data
saying, well, contradiction, entitlement, or neutral,
or positive or negative on the tweet
because tweets don't have any labels.
And then the final label is decided.
So the final gold label.
So the gold could be, could mean, okay,
so several people agreed on a label for particle instance.
So this is like the gold truth.
Or the gold can mean it's costly because, you know,
you have to pay a lot of people, these experts.
One example here is that we, so I put this reference here.
We were annotating legal decisions
from the Court of European Human Rights
with six law students over a year.
So how much did it cost?
Any estimate.
How much we paid for annotating a data set,
which is now publicly available in this publication.
How much did we pay?
Any estimates?
50 to 100,000.
50 to 100,000 would be great.
I know, it's way too much.
No, 20K, roughly.
It's a lot of money.
20,000 euro, whew, okay, a year of work.
You know, so it's costly because you need these experts.
We need lawyers or law students
to understand the legal language
because I couldn't understand anything, you know,
so I couldn't annotate anything.
So that's why it's called gold-labeled data.
So it's super costly to produce good data.
It's easy to get it from Hugging Face data sets, right,
for free.
This is great.
So appreciate somebody who did some annotating.
Anyone annotated here something?
Anybody did like some human annotation study?
No one, okay, great.
If you have a chance, do it.
Do it, because then you will understand
how terrible that is to annotate data.
No, it is, it's boring.
The worst thing you can do is annotating something
on the internet, like social media.
So for example, annotating posts on Facebook,
whether they're toxic or not.
Not only are you gonna hate it, but it's gonna hurt.
It's true.
It's just how much stupid it is out there in the world.
That really hurts.
If somebody, you know, if OpenAI is annotating their data,
they're outsourcing it to somebody else,
paying low wages, I'm recording on YouTube, I don't care.
They're paying low wages and let people for low wages
annotate toxic comments or even maybe pornography.
It's a really bad thing.
Annotating data could be, you know,
could hurt you like sickly.
Anyway, but if you have a chance of annotating something,
do it.
Just, you know, understand how time consuming
and interesting the task is.
How do you make sure that you have good quality of data?
So basically you compare, if you have like, I don't know,
like three people for the same example,
you're gonna compare them together
and make sure that, you know, the chance,
if they agree on the label, it could be by chance.
So if you just taken, let's say, an average agreement,
it will be maybe bigger than the actual agreement is.
So there are a couple of measures for inter,
so-called inter-annotator agreements.
And there's few measures like Cohen's Kappa,
P, Kripa and so forth.
I don't want you to remember all of them,
but I want you to remember that there's actual measures
for agreement computation among people,
among annotators, you know?
So if you annotate a data set and you ask for quality,
they should have done something
as internet data agreements.
And there's some metrics and they have meaning.
So it's important to know how, what does it tell?
Well, it tells us also like there's a subjectivity
in the task, you know?
And if this is completely subjective,
then maybe it makes no sense to run machines on that, right?
Okay, any questions to gold standard data?
Great.
Second question is a side step.
So who creates these tasks, why?
I mean, so we had this kind of example of a movie reviews
because it's, you know, poetic and fun.
So mostly researchers,
mostly researchers are interested in doing some tasks.
Sometimes companies saying, well, I wanna, you know,
I wanna improve, what was that, the customer experience.
So if somebody is calling me angry,
I need to solve it and I need to prioritize things.
Yeah, so it's fine.
So there's different stakeholders in the game,
but these tasks I'm presenting today,
just mostly researchers,
because they are interested in some phenomenon language.
For example, a sentiment,
because it's just an interesting thing to observe in data
and to which extent we can solve them by tools.
So basically it's also setting up benchmarks
for automatic machines or for machines
to kind of tackle with that.
Are we able to say whether an email is a spam or not?
It's solved, right?
I mean, it's not interesting anymore.
20 years back, it was kind of like interesting.
Yeah, can we decide automatically if it's a spam or not?
And also the data sets created and sharing them,
it was popular with machine learning in NLP.
So basically you start creating data sets
and they become sort of like standard benchmarks.
What is the standard?
It's defined by the community.
So the community somehow is interested now
in doing IMDB data sets, sentiment analysis,
and everybody's using that.
Nobody is pushing you to do so,
but you kind of feel like this is the standard data set.
And obviously you're sharing data set
and comparing them your new system
because you have new network and say like,
oh, I'm better than a random forest on IMDB.
So 87%, I have like this new kind of thing, GPT-5.
It's gonna be like 99%, whatever,
but you have to do it on the same data set, okay?
So the tasks are classified
into various arbitrary taxonomies
with mostly agreed upon names.
So for example, sentiment analysis is sort of a task
and it's part of text classification
or sentence classification, document classification.
The SNLI, the Stanford Nature Language Inference
is a sort of sentence pair classification.
But these are arbitrary names,
so you can call them differently and it's fine as well.
So there is no like set in stone taxonomy of tasks,
but people kind of converge into seeing,
ah, yeah, this is a document classification.
Okay, any question to this?
Right.
So let's move on.
And now let's say
we are going deeper into a sentence
and we're interested in finding entities
or so-called main entities in a sentence.
So we have a predefined types of entities
and we wanna locate them in the sentence.
And here's an example.
So the sentence goes from, you know,
top to bottom.
UN official ECOS, ECOS, sorry, heads for Baghdad.
So this is some news from 2002, I guess.
And here we have the UN is labeled as organization.
ECOS is probably some person
and Baghdad is the definite location to sit in.
So how to model this task?
Because it's not like saying,
well, this is binary decision over the whole document.
So how can we model that?
And well, this is a question.
How would you model that?
How would you label this thing?
If I want you to find entities in a text
like organization, person, location,
how to annotate such a task?
So the only thing you see is a sentence, right?
And the sentence would be like a plain text, basically.
No new lines.
You have a sentence.
So what do you need to do first?
Oh, one, two, three, okay.
You.
Okay, so you're assuming you have some somewhere,
a list of all these organizations
and you want to create the data set out of it.
Yeah, maybe I would say you have news
and you have nothing else.
So maybe it won't work.
Any other ideas?
So you.
Exactly, we should first tokenize a thing
because here you see the tokenization,
so splitting into words.
So we have to say UN is a word, official is a word,
ECOS is a word, and so on,
and the dot is not a word
because we are going to label the tokens.
Okay, this is one first assumption
we need to take into account.
Then the second thing, we have the tokens,
so what are you gonna do?
Then it's easy, yes?
Get the base of the tokens
and then do part of the sentence thing
because all of the things that are not going to take
are nouns here, and take only things
that have a scope that are nouns.
Oh, okay, so you're saying you can take only nouns
and annotating nouns and ignoring rest.
Yeah, I mean, you can do this as well.
I would say it's much easier.
So you tokenize, and then assign each word,
or each token, let's be more concrete, a type.
So we're gonna say the UN was organization,
ECOS was person, and Baghdad was something else.
What we are using here is so-called BIO tagging.
It will be on the next slide as well.
And we're saying each of these words has a label,
so these are the labels, right?
And the O label is, it's not zero, it's O,
and it means like, maybe it's a zero.
No, it's O actually, it's BIO tagging.
So it's like out of entities, so there's nothing.
So each word, every word that is not the entity
is assigned with O, and we're assigning these I minus org
and I minus per and I minus log
to these tokens, which are the entity, okay?
It looks weird, but I'll show you why.
Yes?
Why isn't it B?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So why isn't it B?
So you know something.
So what is I and what is B then?
B is the gain, okay?
Exactly, that's interesting observation,
and I'm full with you.
So what we have here that if we had, say,
a longer entity, which would be, I don't know,
a word entity, a person, okay, Angela Merkel.
So if we had a text, something, something,
Angela Merkel, something, something,
and you would annotate it as a beginning of person,
and here this would be inside person,
like that would be your understanding.
And I guess it's not wrong,
and actually this is how I understand as well,
but I look into the original paper of this,
you know, this annotation,
and what they did was something else.
They said if two consequent tokens are the same type,
whenever two entities of the type
are immediately next to each other.
So it wasn't the Angela Merkel.
It would be, what could be like two entities
of the same type next to each other?
Without comma.
Austin, Texas, okay, so Austin, Texas,
blah, blah, blah, Austin, Texas, blah, blah, blah.
I would put comma here actually,
and it would be all, and the problem would be solved.
If there is no comma, then you would,
based on this original understanding,
original description of BIO tagging,
you would say this is E location,
and this is B location, right?
And it's kind of not intuitive.
How I would annotate it would be,
yeah, there's a beginning of location,
and here's another beginning of location, right?
This kind of makes sense, right?
I mean, here we have beginning and inside,
and then it would be Os maybe, and Os, which is clear.
Here, it's kind of awkward, but this is how they define,
and I got it wrong for a long period of time.
So there is many flavors of these BIO encoding,
and there is also others called below,
below, and BoA, and so on.
So just that you know, it doesn't matter
how you define the task, it has to be unambiguous.
So if you have two consecutive entities,
you have to make sure that this will be clear,
like what does it mean, what labeling means.
Whether this is B log and I log,
or B log and B log, and so on,
it's a matter of the actual data set and actual task.
But as I said, there is a standard data set,
so this is the, sorry, coming back, the CONELOT 2003,
they have four entities, person, organization,
location, and MISTs, like miscellaneous,
and they use this BIO encoding in the way
they describe here, so this is from the paper.
Kind of, yeah, their decision, basically.
Okay, any question, yeah.
By hand.
They took the, so the data set for this task
was taken from the Reuters corpus,
which you had to buy back then,
the license, you bought the Reuters corpus,
and they let people, maybe their authors
or somebody from their department annotate it per hand,
the entities, a lot of money back then, right?
So now you can download it for free,
like it's basically public domain, the data set.
It's been here for 20 years.
Any question to BIO tagging?
Okay, that's great.
So keep in mind, namely the reorganization
by BIO and sequence labeling.
Let's move on.
Superglue, okay.
So superglue, it's a popular benchmark,
well, three years, four years old now.
Collection, it's a collection of benchmarks.
It's not just a single task,
like name of the recognition or SNLI.
It's a collection of various tasks in English.
There's also multilingual superglue,
but this one is just in English.
And the goal of superglue is to provide
a simple, robust evolution metric
of any method capable of being applied
to a broad range of language understanding tasks.
So glue means general purpose language understanding, GLUA,
and super means just they took a glue and make it bigger.
So it's superglue, but everybody knows that.
So you should know as well.
Superglue or glue are just a standard task
for language understanding.
So if you see a paper or somebody is writing,
oh, we got human performance on superglue,
then you should know, okay,
superglue is a collection of different tasks,
and we'll show a couple of those in the next slides.
So it's like one data set which has multiple sub-data sets
of different kinds, okay?
And one of them is RTE, recognizing textual entitlement.
So what is it, textual entitlement?
We have binary classification,
and we have a text and the hypothesis,
and we have to say whether the text entiles the hypothesis,
yes or no, which means if you read the text
and the hypothesis, would you say the hypothesis is true?
So the text here would be Dana Reeve,
the widow of the actor Christopher Reeve,
has died of lung cancer at age 44
according to the Christopher Reeve Foundation.
This is the text.
The hypothesis is Christopher Reeve had an accident.
So if you read a text, would you say
the hypothesis is true or not?
It's not, so it's false, okay?
And now we say, oh, text and hypothesis,
I've seen it before.
I saw it in the natural language inference task.
So is it the same thing or not?
So Stanford SNLI basically adapted this,
recognizing textual entitlement.
So RTE is somehow older,
and only just a binary classification,
and SNLI was three ways,
so natural entitlement and contradiction.
So this is a very similar task,
and who defined the task?
Just the researchers.
They create a data set and say, like, this is RTE,
and then came people from Stanford and say,
oh, this is SNLI, it's a little bit different,
so we call it differently, right?
But this is the standard textual entitlement.
Any questions?
Okay, good.
Then, so this is part of SuperGLUE.
One of these tasks in SuperGLUE
is recognizing textual entitlement,
and what you need for this is, again,
understanding the semantic of one document and the other,
and how they relate to each other.
Whether if somebody,
if somebody,
yeah, if somebody who died on cancer from a foundation
has something to do with somebody else who had an accident.
So you need to kind of understand this connection, right?
So the model, if you wanna solve this task,
you need to understand this, how this works together,
some sort of word knowledge, I would say.
So another data set in SuperGLUE is coreference resolution,
where you have a sentence with a pronoun
and a list of non-phrases from the sentence,
and you have to determine
the correct reference of the pronoun.
So the example makes it clear.
The text reads,
Mark told Pete many lies about himself,
which Pete included in his book.
He should have been more truthful.
And the question is whether he is Pete or not.
So again, Mark told Pete many lies about himself,
which Pete included in his book.
He should have been more truthful.
And I'm wondering, wait a second.
I see my line right here.
Should be true, right?
I mean, he is Pete, isn't it?
It's Mark.
Mark told Pete, truthful.
Yeah, truthful, okay, yes.
Yeah, so the hard thing about this course,
it's like right after lunch.
And if you had Goulash with Pumas,
it puts you basically on random performance here
on these logical tasks.
But thanks for correcting.
What do you need for solving this is everyday,
common sense knowledge, common sense reasoning.
So this is a hard task for machines,
as you just saw for humans too sometimes.
So this is a reference resolution
Winograd Schema Challenge,
one of part of this, part of super new.
Any question?
Good.
And then we have, I'm showing, I guess,
the third from Superglue is BooQ,
which is a Boolean question answering.
So each example is a short passage
and yes and no question about the passage, yes.
So example, the question is,
has the UK been hit by a hurricane?
And the passage is, great storm of 1997
was a violent extra tropical cyclone,
which caused casualties in England, France,
and the Channel Island, blah, blah, blah.
And you have to say whether it's true or not.
So has the UK been hit by a hurricane
after reading this paragraph?
And the answer here is yes,
because there was like the great storm
and casualties in England, so okay.
So you need to understand that extra tropical cyclone
is a hurricane.
And then you have to understand
that UK is England and so on.
So a lot of kind of common sense understanding and reasoning.
So this is a task.
Non-factoid information or difficult entitlement
like inference to solve.
So this is what you need to know
or the machine needs to know in order to solve this task.
Okay, any question?
Yes.
Is it an entitlement or not?
Okay, this is a cool, yes.
Yes and no.
If you turn this into a statement, not a question,
the UKP has been hit by a hurricane
and this would be like the text
and this would be a hypothesis,
then it would be entails or not.
See, yes.
But you're asking a question.
So maybe when you ask a question,
you might give an example here as well.
So it's not maybe obligatory,
but you know, you kind of,
but it needs the same thing, yeah.
That's a good question, yes.
I don't think so.
I think it's just binary, yes and no.
It's a zero one.
So I guess it's not graded, but I haven't checked.
So you can have a look at the paper
and see whether they kind of take it into account.
I didn't check.
Yeah, it's a good point.
Okay, anything else?
Here, let's move on.
So the last one from squat,
sorry, last one from superglue is the multi-RC,
multi-sentence reading comprehension.
So what does it mean?
You have, again, a context paragraph,
you have questions or a question about a paragraph,
and then you have a list of possible answers
which are true or false.
I don't have an example here because it's super long,
but you see it's getting more complicated
because each possible correct answer,
so multiple possible correct answers,
so you have a list and each of them could be right or wrong.
And then answering each question,
they are independent of each other,
so you have to evaluate them by one.
So you have, I don't know,
an example paragraph about the hurricane,
and then you have like five statements or five questions,
and you need to have all of them correct,
and they kind of can be tricky.
And answering question requires drawing facts
from multiple context sentences.
So there's not only like single sentence in the document
but multiple, and you have to combine them together
in order to answer the question.
So it's getting more complicated.
You need really like reading comprehension,
so you need to comprehend the text,
and that's basically what you do also.
If you learn like second language and make a test,
there's also like reading comprehension
which you need to understand the language
and blah, blah, blah.
So this is multi-RC, kind of challenging task.
Any question?
Okay, cool.
And we're finishing,
I don't think this is part of superglue anymore,
so superglue was for these tasks different, there's more.
So you can have superglue is like maybe 10 tasks together
or maybe more,
but these were like the prototypical examples.
Now we're getting to question answering, which is a squat.
So I guess this stands for Stanford
question answering data set
because it was done by people from Stanford.
And here's an example.
So here's in paragraph,
other legislation followed
including Immigration Bird Conservation Act,
the treaty prohibiting the hunting of frite and gray whales,
blah, blah, something super boring from Wikipedia.
And then the question is like
which laws face significant opposition?
And you have the reference.
You have the paragraph
and you ask questions about this paragraph.
The point is these questions are kind of unanswerable.
You cannot answer them from this text,
but they have like plausible answers, which are incorrect
because there is this kind of a lexical,
the same words are used in this paragraph
as in the questions.
So it kind of tricks the machine to make shortcuts
and see, yeah, well, the answer should be later laws here,
but it's wrong.
Or here, what was the name of the treaty?
And if you just don't pay attention
and just, you know, keyboard spotting,
then you say, yeah, yeah, yeah,
it was this Bald Eagle Protection Act, which is wrong.
So it's kind of hard task for machines
not to jump on these, you know, quick keyword spotting
and just, oh, this is the answer.
So this is really interesting
because squat, the first version,
it had these issues like, you know,
keyword spotting and you can answer even like
without reading a lot of this paragraph.
Questions?
Yes.
Who exactly writes the question?
Does the same people who have to read the text
and then put down the answer,
or is there another entity?
So I guess, so the question is who writes these questions?
It was done by crowd workers.
So who knows the word crowd worker?
So, okay, what is crowd worker?
Somebody who didn't speak at all.
Who didn't speak at all and who's crowd worker?
Okay, so what is it?
Yes, crowd worker.
Exactly, so a small task for people on the internet.
So somebody is sitting at home and saying,
I want to earn $5 per hour
because I have to earn money somehow.
And then this is labeling cats and dogs and toxic comments.
And all these tasks are writing questions
about paragraphs on Wikipedia.
So the best, the biggest platform is Amazon Mechanical Turk
where you can, if you're living in the US,
I think you need social security number,
you can sign up as a worker.
If you want something to crowd source,
universities, researchers are just going there.
You have thousands of people
who are kind of get paid for this tiny job.
Maybe, you know, and you say, well, the task is,
here's a, you know, a paragraph from Wikipedia,
write a meaningful question about it.
And the person says, okay, wow.
Which laws facing the single positions or something like that?
I mean, you instruct these people to write it, right?
So crowd workers is sort of scalable thing
of annotating or creating data sets.
This was done by crowdsourcing.
Yeah, the whole data set.
Okay, any other questions?
Good, okay, so we've finished text classification
and now,
all right.
And now let's move on to text generation.
So what is text generation?
Well, I'll give you examples and you know what it means.
So machine translation.
Machine translation is still hard, even like in,
so I took this picture two months back in Tenerife
and there's a menu which says news of the month,
which is wrong already.
You know, this is translation of,
I guess from Spanish to English
and the translation to German is even longer,
nachricht in des monads on the menu.
I don't know, I don't wanna eat nachricht in des monads.
So yeah, so machine, and obviously they did like,
they use Google translate to translate this,
but if you don't have the context of the menu,
it will just, what's the news of the month?
Yeah, it's nachricht in des monads, of course.
If you don't know if it's on the menu, right?
So it's still hard problem.
And there are a couple of standard data sets
for machine translation.
So the task of machine translation,
obviously sentence input, sentence output mostly,
one language, another language.
And there's very many standard data sets from the WMT,
which used to be a workshop on machine translation.
Now it's called conference on machine translation,
but they're using the WMT shortcut for data sets.
So WMT 14 is for example, very famous data set
for English, German translation on like general topics.
So machine translation, what is so hard about it?
What is hard about machine translation?
Like conceptually?
Some words mean different things in different contexts.
Some words mean different things in different contexts
like nachrichten, of course, yes.
Anything else?
Anything which is like, sorry, you?
You.
Yeah, you have like a simonins and homonins
or words that have multiple meanings
or two words that mean the same things and.
That's true, you have multiple meanings
and homonins, simonins, but if you understand language,
you can translate to the target language.
I mean, I can speak English, but you know,
and I'm calling the message of obviously,
but some things in my mind are homonins as well.
Good, yeah, maybe the sound words don't exist.
So what do you do?
You have to explain them or say it differently, okay?
Anything else, like what is the real,
what's the issue of machine translation
if you wanna do it properly?
And if you have different structures,
some of them use words like beginning and homonins.
That's fine, but that's fine, but you can do that.
I mean, sure, I mean, you speak,
I guess you speak also like multiple languages at least,
so you have to learn these difficulties, yes, but.
Say it?
You can say it in German as well.
Okay, I'll let you just sometimes think about it.
Yes, okay, last attempt, sorry.
Yeah, that's true, yeah.
It's okay to say something in one language
and it sounds weird,
but if you do like proper translation with all these things,
you can translate idioms and they will work mostly or jokes.
The point is you have so many different options
to translate one thing
and you can't tell which one is better, mostly.
So there is one example from this book from Philip Cohen,
the translation of, sorry, I don't speak French.
Okay, can anyone read this?
Who speaks French?
Yes.
Thank you very much.
So here's so many translations here of that in English
and here's how people assess that
whether it's correct or wrong
and there's no agreement what's a correct
or not correct translation
because you can translate the same sentence
in so many different ways, right?
I mean, if you speak French and English,
you can kind of do it for yourself.
I can't, but they mean the same thing
but a little different,
there's a little bit of twist of that
and it's just hard to say what's correct and what's wrong
because you can say the same thing in many different ways
and maybe all of them are correct, maybe not
and people don't agree on that.
So people disagree on what's good.
I mean, some are clearly bad or correct
but there's disagreement, so it makes it hard
if you wanna do it with machines, right?
You wanna show an example and this is hard
on top of what you just said before, which is correct.
So, as I said, machine translation is hard.
We have standard data sets
and the evaluation of machine translation
or evaluation of generation is hard, as we will see later.
Any question on machine translation?
Okay, good.
So, now we have document summarization
or abstracted document summarization
which means you take a long document
which, for example, here in this CNN Daily Mail
standard data set for summarization,
you take a document which is 800 tokens long
and you wanna have a summary
which is roughly 50, 60 tokens on average.
So basically extracting the most information
but not extracting very badly in the tokens but rephrasing.
What's the gist of this document?
And it's hard.
Why is it hard?
You can, because you don't know
what's important in the document.
So we have multiple kind of scenarios
because everybody understands
something different in a document
and if I show you a news article and ask you,
can we write a summary?
I can guarantee you from 100 people here
I will get 80 different summaries,
100 different summaries mostly.
So it's also kind of complicated how to evaluate
but there's a training data set
which have some human-labeled summaries
and there's tricks how to do summarization,
how to do evaluation.
So it's a thing, it's a task, document summarization.
Why is it important?
Well, because people are lazy
and you wanna write the article.
Well, now we have ggpt so everything is solved
but maybe before you had an article
and you would just want to write a summary for the web
like short snippets, what the article is about automatically.
Why not?
So clear?
Any question?
Yes.
How would you validate it?
Because the machine could be like the same,
not like with different words.
How would you validate it?
What do you mean?
So there's a metrics for saying
this is a good summary or not.
And this is what you use.
You have some examples and you compare,
you have some documents and some summaries
written by humans and you let your system create summaries
and then you compare your summary
with the gold standard summary and there's metric
to say like, well, this is the same or not.
There's metrics to that
which has some flaws, we'll come to that later.
Okay?
Good.
And the last thing about generate,
there's so many things about generation
but the last one is the person not chat.
So dialogue.
So basically you have a dialogue
and you wanna do, predict the next returns.
So this is like the chit chat.
So you have two persons and they say,
hey, hello, how are you today?
Oh, I'm good, thank you.
How are you?
Oh, great, thanks.
My children, I just about to watch a Game of Thrones.
Oh, nice, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And the task could be, yeah,
just create the next sentence in this dialogue
because you maybe you're programming Alexa,
Amazon Alexa and you wanna entertain people about things.
And in this data set, they kind of create also personas.
So you know that person one is somebody who liked the sky
and blah, blah, blah,
and person two is doing something else.
So this is one of the data sets you wanna train
on just chit chat dialogues, right?
Yeah, it could be fun.
I mean, dialogue research, it's fun.
Then came chat GPT and just, oh, it's hard.
Okay, so this would be generation.
Now the thing is,
we did this distinction classification and generation,
but basically you can turn everything into generation.
How?
Well, you just tell it what to do.
So here's an example, translation English to German.
The input of your model could be verbically.
Translate English to German, that is good.
That's the input to the model.
And what you're expecting, this is good.
Yeah, this is machine translation, cool.
So nothing has changed.
Text in, text out.
How about here?
Nature language inference.
So NLI and MNLI means multilingual MNLI.
And you would write to the model.
MNLI premise, I hate pigeons.
And hypothesis, my feeling towards pigeons
are filled with animals.
And what you expect the model to output
is a word called, it's a word entitlement.
So it's not saying like zero, one or two, the label,
but it's basically spinning out the label as text, right?
It's doing basically the classification by saying,
if this were a tweet, you would say,
no, it is very toxic.
It was the hotline call.
You would say, hotline comment, period,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
Oh, I hate you, T-Mobile, blah, blah, blah.
And you would say, and you would finish maybe sentiment.
And the model would always put text saying negative.
This is how you turn basically classification
into the generation, but it's the same thing, right?
You can do that.
There's no basically difference, right?
Does it make sense?
Is it really like, oh, well, why should I generate text
because I can classify?
But there's models like GPT text in anything out
and you can do classification with them as well.
The very same way.
You just create a task as you say,
oh, premise is that and that, hypothesis is that and that
and spit out the decision.
If you do it to try with GPT, you know, try it.
What's the sentiment of this tweet?
And you write a tweet and GPT will spit out
maybe something longer, but maybe just, yeah, negative.
This is how it works.
Any questions?
This is important to understand.
Like you can turn everything into text from text to text,
even like regression, just outputs a number.
Yeah, prompting.
Yes, yeah.
No, no, it's just a different word from prompting,
but prompting is, it means something, zero shot,
one shot, blah, blah, blah, from things.
Yeah, this is prompting.
You can turn everything into text in text out.
That's important.
Okay, great.
So we know what we need to solve.
How good are we in that?
That's another question.
Okay, so let's move to evaluation a little bit.
And since most of people have here some, you know,
deep learning, machine learning and so on,
so I'm gonna just go quickly
and don't spend so much time on that.
If you have questions, just ask.
So we have these data sets, we have these tasks
and we wanna do some proper splitting on training
and validation and tests.
So basically we have training and test data.
So training, this is where we train our model and test data.
We never train our model on test data, never.
If there's one thing you should remember
when you leave the university,
never train your model on test data
because you train the model on test data,
the model will remember test data,
then you show, oh, I have 99% accuracy on test data
to make your boss happy.
And then you deploy somewhere and it just fail
because you can't, you know,
you just completely messed up your evaluation.
So these have to be like put into safe
and never ever touch before the final thing, okay.
This is really important.
So then you play around with training data and validation
so you can split it and, you know,
validation for hyperparameters tuning, okay.
So is it something that everybody kind of is familiar with
or somebody, yeah, okay.
This is a standard common sense.
So train that split.
Sometimes your data is small.
So you do cross-validation, which means you do K-fault,
sort of K-fault cross-validation.
So you split the data into K chunks.
And then for each chunks, you do train on some part
and test on the other part, right?
So you basically do five,
here's a five-fold cross-validation.
So some, you know, in first fault,
this part is test data, this part is and so on, so on, so on.
So cross-validation is a thing,
standard in machine learning.
To be honest, you know,
all these data sets we saw before,
like IMDB, SNLI, SuperGLUE and so on,
they have fixed frame depth test.
They don't do cross-validation.
For which reason?
Because you can really compare performance
on the same test data and on the same validation data.
If you do cross-validation randomly,
then you, oh, there's some randomness.
So, you know, you don't want to do it.
If you have small data
and you're playing around with new tasks,
maybe you want to do cross-validation.
Any questions?
Yes.
Yeah, so the standard tasks,
they have this frame, frame depth test.
They don't care about cross-validation
because in cross-validation,
yeah, you have to do some random splits
and the randomness will be different
from one person to another.
So it's better to have fixed, right?
Okay, any other question?
Okay, so I'm just, I put it just for reference there.
Cross-validation is a thing.
But now let's look into an evaluation
of test classification.
So classification is easy because we have,
let's, if we have two classes,
we can call them, we call them positive or negative,
or you can map everything into these two classes.
And then the thing is you can, the predictions here,
you can put them in a thing called confusion matrix,
where it, what it means is that it's a table.
So here, these will be numbers.
And then it's basically saying how many times
in my test set, something which was actually negative
was actually predict, it was predictive as negative.
And you make a, yeah, plus one here.
And then you collect the table for all your test data
and get a confusion matrix.
So one thing to remember is that, you know,
the ordering of columns here is arbitrary.
You know, it doesn't have to start with negative here
and positive here.
You can just flip them and flip the rows as well,
which will flip the true negatives, false positives,
false negatives, and true positives.
So it's super messy.
So anytime, I mean, you don't have to remember exactly
what is true, well, maybe it's not a bad thing to remember,
but I don't remember it either because you can flip that
and then just, yeah, what's left, right?
It's true, negative, I don't know.
So Wikipedia is your friend.
But just, you know, be aware of that.
So this is just one example how to do that.
So an example here would be, we have an classifier.
So here's an example of some disease detection.
So some binary task, negative and positive.
I do have a disease or I don't have a disease.
And these are the columns on the confusion matrix, right?
So it means that from, in my test data from 168 plus 33,
negative examples were classified as negative 168
and positive as 33.
So this is the confusion matrix, how much confused I were.
Any question to the confusion matrix?
Is it clear to everybody?
It's something you should spend some time kind of,
you know, working around and understanding
what confusion matrix is to understand
how to make evaluation,
but it's also not a rocket science.
So any questions, confusion matrix?
Okay, good.
So you have the confusion matrix for the binary task here
because we have two classes.
If we have three classes, I'll show later how it looks.
So one measure here is the accuracy.
So what is it saying?
It's only how accurate I was.
So the predictions which were correct over all predictions.
This is super fancy formula with some and blah, blah, blah.
Yeah, so basically you take the diagonal
of your confusion matrix
and divides by the total number of things.
So basically this is an identity function,
which means my prediction was something
and my gold label was something.
And if they're equal, this is plus one.
So this is one, and if they're not equal, this is zero.
So I'm computing all the matches here
and divide by all the numbers of instances in my test data.
Okay, and this is accuracy.
So here's the workout example,
which I suggest you to compute
and just play around with numbers.
The accuracy doesn't care about the other numbers here.
So these false predictions, whatever happens here,
it's not important.
You can flip these numbers
and the accuracy will be the same.
So everybody understands accuracy?
Basically how many times I go to drive in the test set?
That's as simple as it is.
And it's between zero and one.
So 100% is one or 100% is 100% accuracy is the best system.
It works perfectly.
If you have binary tasks and it's balanced data set,
50% would be like the random accuracy.
So accuracy has some issues.
If you have skewed data set, it won't work that well.
So we have another metrics
which are called precision recall and F1 score.
Is there anyone who hasn't heard
about precision recall and F1 score?
Okay, good.
So it's computing.
So what is precision doing?
And now we have an example of precision for class positive
because it will be different for class negative
because these kind of ordering is arbitrary.
So for class positive, I'm here
and I wanna compute a precision for that.
So I'm saying,
whatever I predicted here as positive.
So I predicted something positive.
I predicted positive the correct things
and predicted as positive something which wasn't positive.
So I'm saying how many times
did I correctly predict it positive if I set it positive?
So I'm taking the true positive
over this sum.
So saying like how precise I was.
My classifier is set, this is positive.
Which part of that was really positive?
This is what precision is doing.
Recall is saying, yeah, I have my data here.
So all of this in my data set
is which is positive in my data.
These are actually positive in my data set.
How much I found of them.
So this is the, I take the true positive
and divide by the sum of all of these positive
in my data set.
So I have 500 documents which are positive in my data set
and I found only 100 of them.
So my recall is just one over five.
I didn't find all.
And these two are kind of complimentary
and you can combine them into one score
which is called the F1 measure, F1 score.
And it's this harmonic mean of these two measures.
So you might seen it before,
something to know, to remember and know how it works.
Why is it important?
So it's important because it takes into account
two different versions of your classifier.
You wanna maybe precise classifier,
you wanna maybe more recolor in the classifier
or you wanna combine into one measure.
Any questions?
Great.
So the confusion matrix here is for just for two classes.
Obviously you might have multi-class problem
and here this is taken from the Reuters data sets
which is newswire classification in two different topics.
And here the confusion matrix is basically the same.
So you have the true class and here are the predictions.
And if we are compute to create the accuracy,
so what's the accuracy of the classifier?
It's basically sum of the diagonal.
Oh wow, sorry.
Sum of the diagonal over all these,
sum of all these things would be the accuracy.
I mean what's going, what's right
and over all the instances in my test data.
How would you turn this into precision and recall?
Okay, this is interesting because precision and recall,
we define like true positives, true negatives,
but these were just two classes.
So how do I do it for a bigger matrix?
I have one, two, three, four, five, six classes.
So what I'm going to do?
Yeah, so basically you take class of your interest,
which will be interest maybe and merge the rest
and the rest will be merged into one row and one column.
And this is how you create basically two by two matrix.
This is how you compute it.
And then you compute this for each class
and then you can take an average of these F1 scores
or do some other things.
So this is kind of technical details,
but it might get tricky.
So always report what you do.
I recommend this paper.
If you're interested in more like how tricky
this could be, have a look at this paper
because all these tiny details make a difference
whether you have the accuracy of,
or micro F1 score of 80 or 85 or 90,
make sure you're comparing apples to apples.
Okay, so this is the evaluations.
Okay, any questions so far?
So if you've seen this before machine learning,
it's nothing new, like the same stuff will run over.
Evaluating this generation.
Okay, we're running out of time,
but let me just, okay, seven minutes and we're good.
It's okay?
Good, yeah, we're almost there.
Yes, so evolution of text generation is hard.
Why?
Because you have different metrics
and I'll let me just scare you off a little bit.
So this is just a part of one large table
of different metrics for text generation.
So evaluating text generation is a matter of research
and not all these metrics here,
so there could be like, I don't know how many, 40 metrics
and they have pros and cons.
So it's part, it's basically a research topic.
Classification is easy, match or not match, cool.
Generation, yeah, you can translate it
and summarization and oh, it's hard.
So there's metrics.
I'm gonna show you two of them, which are like super easy,
but you don't have to remember the formulas
because if you were to implement it,
then you better look up the papers.
So one of them, but you should know the name,
is BLEU, B-L-E-U, Bilingual Evolution Understudy.
It's like the first and most popular metrics
for machine translation and it computes the engram overlap
between the reference and the hypothesis.
So you have a reference translation
and you have the hypothesis which is a translation
of your machine translation system
and you're basically comparing how much
there is an overlap of engrams.
What is an engram?
What is a bigram?
There are two characters in each of those
combined as one token.
Two characters, I would say,
this would be like character bigram.
So just standard engram would be two tokens
next to each other.
It's a bigram.
For trigram would be three tokens next to each other, okay?
So you would compare like pairs of words, the bigrams
and how much there is an overlap.
Yeah, it looks easy.
There is one score of the corpus,
but the drawback, it's just a precision based.
So you don't count for recall
and there's an exact engram matching.
So there has to be like exact translation
and in translation, you can use some different spelling
maybe or different kind of wording of the same thing.
So if there is no match, the blue score doesn't work.
So there's another metric which is oriented on recall
and it's rouge.
If you're wondering why all these machine translation
evaluation metrics are frame sounding, I have no idea.
It's maybe the part of the creative.
If you're like, you know, all the transformers like Bert,
Roberta, Camembert, you know, all these on streets things.
Maybe it was fun.
So it's rouge, so rouge.
Recall-oriented understanding of gisting evaluation.
It's a terrible name.
It's similar to blue.
I mean, there's different variants,
but counting in the engram matches
between the hypothesis and reference.
So it's the same, but it's recall-based measure.
So there's different formula and it's just,
it has some other kind of properties, right?
And it's measuring the longest common subsequence
between a pair of sentences.
You have a question?
Does this become order in the engram?
Does that maybe some-
The ordering of engrams, whether it counts,
well, it doesn't matter where the engram occurs, you know?
So you can have the engram in the reference at the beginning
and the hypothesis at the end,
because you can translate a sentence.
Yesterday, I was at cinema, or I was at cinema yesterday.
And you have yesterday at the beginning and the end.
So there's like unigram overlap, which is fine.
So it takes this into account, like,
or the bigram is more like context, contextualized.
Okay, another question?
So remember, blue and rouge are the standard metrics
and they have pros and cons, mostly cons.
So that's why there's already different metrics
which are better.
And it's super hard, I mean, it's easy to hack,
well, it's not easy to hack them,
but if you improve blue score, it doesn't matter.
It doesn't mean that human perception of your evaluation,
of your machine translation, is really better.
So there is some correlation between the blue scores
and how humans perceive the evaluation,
but it's not 100%.
That's why there is research on that,
because you wanna have better translation for humans,
not just because of blue score.
You know, the advantage of the blue score is
you can do it automatically.
You don't need a human to say,
oh, this is better translation than the other.
Eventually, in language generation,
you want humans to look into the generated text.
So, you know, kind of, but it's costly
and time consuming and so on.
So that's why there are metrics.
So there's some caveats of NLP benchmarking.
And I listed like, I guess, two or three,
and then we're done.
So we talked about the gold data paradigm.
So, and it's easy, like we have like one ground truth.
And it makes sense when humans highly agree on the answer.
So if the annotation task would be,
does this image contain a bird,
or is it, is learn a verb,
or what is the capital of Italy,
people will agree, and this is easy.
We have gold standard.
But if, for example, something which is more,
yeah, which is more subjective,
is for example, is this comments on Facebook toxic or not?
Well, people will disagree maybe,
because it's depending on your subjectivity.
And, or understanding of the language.
And we kind of tend to, you know,
kind of get rid of these hard cases
or non-agreed upon things.
But now there's research on that actually
these human label variation is an opportunity,
not a problem.
So this is something which we should maybe
took into account and not just pretend,
oh, there's one gold truth.
So we should have maybe some variation.
This is basically a part of current research
by the group of Barbara Plunk in Munich.
So remember, if there is a gold standard,
well, yeah, somebody has to create a gold standard,
and they took some arbitrary decisions on the way.
So maybe, you know, it was a hard choice.
Human annotators are biased,
because the data sets are constructed
by small number of annotators and humans are biased.
So if you, you know, you go to mechanical Turk,
and at the end of the day,
you have maybe a hundred workers working for you,
all these 600,000 Stanford and allied, you know,
data points was done by, I don't know, 200 workers,
which means you get some bias of these people
into the data set.
So people are biased.
And it has some consequences maybe
if you let the data create by somebody else,
so by annotators that did not contribute to the training set
kind of influences your performance of the model.
So you have some bias in the data,
which is inherent to the humans.
Yeah, take that into mind as well.
We might have artifacts in the, sorry,
artifacts in the data set, so some spurious correlation.
So we created data sets,
which I'm not going to introduce in the detail,
but there was a, so logical reasoning and arguments,
which is, I don't have time to go into detail,
but we have, we had a lot of negations there.
And some other researchers look at our data set
and said like, yeah, if you delete the negation,
basically all the performance of your classifier
will just drop to random,
because the classifiers are just picking up
on these artifacts or spurious correlation in data,
and if they see a negation don't or not,
they just kind of predict the final class,
but it doesn't have to do anything
with understanding the actual task.
It's just picking up on artifacts.
So it's hard to do, create a data set
which there's no artifacts,
and we have to take, you know, think about it,
like, yeah, solving the task or solving the artifact.
So it's important.
Okay, any questions?
Good.
So remember, we have vast amount of tasks
and data sets, data quality matters,
understanding the data annotators
and the task matters as well,
and we should be familiar
with the common evolution tasks metrics,
because then if you read some papers,
you know, all human level performance on SNLI,
you will know what it means,
and you should know what kind of,
who created data set, for what,
and what was the kind of bias in the data as well, maybe.
And getting better scores
is just the beginning of the story.
So getting better blue translation, yeah, nice.
Crunching numbers, cool, but does it do any better?
So take this into mind.
And evaluating text generation is an art.
Having said that, thank you very much.
I'll see you in a week.
Oh, sorry, okay, there is two questions.
Sorry, no, no, no, not yet, two questions.
The practice class is scheduled for right after this.
Oh, okay, so the practice class, nothing today, and more,
so this will be basically hybrid or online,
so there won't be like practice class in person, okay?
That was it?
That's it, thank you.
Thanks.