Good afternoon, everybody.
Welcome to deep learning for NLP lecture.
Oh, this should be six.
So the first typo now.
Great.
Yeah.
Slowly, but steadily.
I hope this is the last one as well on the slides.
Anyway, so welcome to the sixth lecture for deep learning on NLP.
And today we're going to be talking about, oops, sorry.
It's too loud.
Classification and learning.
Word.
Is it too loud or is it okay?
Okay, good.
Learning word embeddings because last time we were talking quite a bit about
word embeddings and language models.
And today, well, what should we learn today?
Um, maybe we want to learn how to solve a problem and the problem is the following.
So I'm going to give you a large corpus of just plain text data.
And I think it's really too loud.
One, two.
Okay.
Maybe now better.
Um, I'll give you a large corpus of plain text data.
Um, let's say, I don't know, uh, news wires or Wikipedia or the internet.
Okay.
And I want to ask you to build a model that will answer such a word analogy tasks.
So I want to solve, for example, Germany to Berlin is like France
to what should be the answer.
Yeah, Paris.
Nice.
Good.
It's a sanity check.
Okay.
So you're here.
Welcome to deep learning.
Uh, number six or men to King is like woman to.
To a queen.
Right?
So how can you build such a model?
If I just give you a large corpus of just plain text data in English.
Sounds kind of challenging, right?
Because you have no labels.
You just want to learn something about reasoning and analogy and something
about words and their meaning.
Right?
So I can promise you, or even guarantee you that after this lecture, at the end
of this lecture, you should be able to solve this task and maybe even like the
code, it's like programming, if you really try hard, um, yes.
Okay.
So, but before we jump on, do that.
So last time we talked about neural language models and, and word embedding.
So just a quick recapitulation, because I thought I'm going to change a little
bit, the depiction of the, you know, the, um, how we kind of, um, draw these,
uh, these diagrams, so they used to be round, but I just changed them a little
bit to, you know, to the squares or rectangles to be more compact, but still,
I mean, this is the narrow language model that we, as we had last time.
So we're trying to predict a, the word that's coming after these three words.
So the black dog and the next word should be barks.
And this is what you're trying to predict.
This is our gold standard sort of data.
And this neural language model kind of has this lookup table, um, for
looking up these embeddings here.
So what is an embedding?
What was that again?
Here?
What was here in these E matrix?
Anyone remember it's, what was the embedding?
So what is an embedding for a word?
Yes.
So for each word, it's a vector with many different.
It's exactly for each word.
It's just a, it's an entry in the matrix and a row in the matrix with some
dimensionality, which is up to us to specify and just a real valued kind of
representation of the one of the encoding word.
Okay.
So, and then this narrow language model to the context together.
So this preceding words as a concatenation.
So stack them after one each other.
And then here, this is what, well, what is this again?
This is what, what is this part?
It doesn't name.
Maybe, maybe it doesn't name anyone remembers what it is or what do you think
it is?
Anyone remembers this part?
Yes.
Yeah.
It's like a multi-layer perceptron or two layer perceptron.
Exactly.
So here, this is the sort of first layer, first linear layer.
Then there is this a nonlinear activation function, which is typically
relu's or something else.
And then there's another linear projection into, into what?
So what is coming out of here?
It's again, important.
What is coming out of here?
The projection, because we're trying to predict a word.
What, so what is it coming out of all this?
Is it, is it a vector?
You, what, what is, what is the size of the vector?
This is the size of the vocabulary.
Exactly.
Because we're trying to say which of these X thousand words is the maximum
should be like the max here.
This will be our, our predicted things.
Okay.
So this is like, we just had a recapitulation from last time.
And again, the green nodes are the train of parameters, which we
very fancy denoted theta.
So the matrix of embeddings and the year, the, the weights and biases for
both layers and the gray nodes are constants.
Okay.
Any question to this, to this diagram?
Good.
So we were going to simplify a little bit because it's like very clumsy.
So we're going to first turn this lookup into something shorter
and we're going to call it.
Just V it's a function which takes a, a takes a one-hot
encoding and produces the embedding.
So this is just a lookup function.
It's shorter and not so clumsy.
Then we also going to kind of clamp together the linear layer.
So remember, I'm going to come back.
Now we have this linear layer and all these parameters where some of like,
you know, independent or not independent, but not part of that.
So we can't them together into just one, one linear layer, like
we just train of parameters, W and B.
Okay.
So it's just more compact representation of the network.
So these are two linear layers and here's still the, the, the
non-linear activation in between.
Okay.
Everybody's fine with that.
So we're just making it simple and smaller.
So it's more compact because we're going to, yes.
Okay.
Can you read what's on the, on the first, on the top?
Yeah.
We forgot a softmax for actually predicting the
distribution over the vocabulary.
Yes.
That's a, that's a great thing.
Exactly.
So in order to really be a language model that kind of predict the, the, the
word after these last linear layer, we want to normalize it into a probability
distribution, which we didn't, I mean, this layer doesn't do any
probability distribution whatsoever.
What comes in, what comes out of this, out of this layer is just
a vector of real values.
Could be anything.
Could be minus infinity to plus infinity over the place.
And we want to kind of softmax to it, to probability distribution.
Right?
So everybody knows what softmax is?
I mean, in the meantime, everybody should kind of remember what is a softmax
because it's really, really important, right?
Which kind of could be a hint that maybe we'll ask this in the, in the exam as well.
Maybe not, you know, but this is a strong signal.
You should know softmax.
Really.
Okay.
So we have a softmax and then this is the loss exactly.
And we're predicting, we're trying to, we're computing the
cross-entropy here, kind of.
And this gets optimized through stochastic gradient descent.
Okay.
So this is the, the neural language model now in its completeness for predicting
the distribution of the next word.
Any question?
Okay.
So before we jump into how to train word embeddings and how to solve this analogy
task, we need to talk about the dot product.
Okay.
So this is a quote from the famous, famous movie.
We need to talk about Kevin.
Everybody knows the movie.
It's a very nice movie, by the way.
So it's a drama from, I don't know, like from the early 2000s.
We need to talk about a dot product and why we need to talk about dot product
because it has some inherent properties, which will be super useful today in this
lecture, and we need to really understand what the dot product is doing, right?
So what is it a product?
Okay.
So let's have a look at the geometry of dot product.
If this is just a recapitulation for you, if you know it, that's fine.
I mean, you can now take a break, but maybe you will get a new perspective
on what the dot product is.
Okay.
So we have two vectors.
So now let's begin two dimensions first.
Okay.
We have two vectors, V and U.
So what is the dot product of these two vectors?
How can you, how can you compute the product?
What is a dot product?
These vectors have several elements or entries.
Yes.
So we can divide each element by one.
Exactly.
We take each, yes, that's correct.
We take each dimension of these vectors.
So there's n dimensions, which is two, and we just multiply each dimension,
each element at these dimensions with the other vector.
Okay.
So we multiply x1 from one vector with x1 of the other and so on.
This is the, this is nice.
What is the meaning of that?
What are we, what are we getting out of it?
Oh, if these vectors are orthogonal, then it will be zero.
That's yeah.
That's a nice property.
Actually.
That's true.
What else can we say about it?
Like any, any like geometric kind of interpretation?
It's also projecting one vector to the other.
That's correct.
We're getting somewhere.
That's nice.
Any other geometric interpretation of the dot product?
It's related to the angle between these two things.
Exactly.
Because if you, if you make it a triangle and do a little bit of trigonometry and
normalization of the vectors, you end up with the geometric definition, or it's
not a definition, it's basically geometric computation of this, of the dot product,
which is a cosine of this theta angle and these two things.
Okay.
So what is, what is this?
Length.
It's a length.
It has a special name also.
It's the norm.
It has even more special name.
Which norm?
L2 norm or Euclidean norm.
Exactly.
So this is the length of the, of the vector.
So we multiply by length, the two vectors and cosinus of this theta.
Okay.
This is pretty cool, right?
So we know the dot product has something to do with the length of the vectors and
also with the angle the vectors are taking to it.
This is nice geometric interpretation.
Who said the projection?
You were the projection.
Okay, exactly.
So it's called, it has many names, like one of them is scalar projection.
Sure.
Coming.
And if you do the, you know, a little bit of trigonometry here and take the angles
and so on, you, you will find that exact, actually it's projecting, projecting one
vector and the other, and it's basically a string of the projection or string of
the association.
Okay.
So this is really nice.
Dot product has many, many names.
This is really nice.
Dot product has many, many views on that and they might have a meaning, which is
great.
Okay.
So then we also had, let's, let's have a look at the product of the, of something
called the unit vector.
Okay.
So what is the, what is the unit vector?
What is the unit vector?
Yes.
Well, no, I mean, actually the norm is just one.
So a norm of a unit vector is one.
It can point anywhere it wants, but it has to be length of one.
Okay.
Exactly.
And you can inscribe it in the, in the circle of, of the radius of one.
So here you and we are, are unit vectors because their length is one.
You know, how can you compute the length of the, of the, of the vectors?
Pythagorean theorem.
So basically it's basic, basic trigonometry or basic Pythagorean theorem.
So they have unit, unit length.
And now let's, let's look at this.
So what could be now?
Okay.
Let me see.
What could be a, a dot product of these two vectors?
So they're unit vectors.
So what is their dot product now?
It has something to do with the angle.
So the angle is roughly 45 degrees, right?
So what could be their dot product?
I'll, I'll give you a second to think about it because I, I have coffee today.
Exceptionally, and it's actually pretty good.
So what is the dot product of these two, two vectors?
Cosine of the angle.
Yeah, just the cosine of the angle.
Exactly.
That's the point because now, since both of them are of length one, we have just
the cosine of the angle.
Okay.
This is cool.
So now let's have a look at the cosine.
What is how the cosine looks like?
Okay.
This is a very fancy function.
Which is periodic after 360 degrees or two pi.
I guess two pi, yes, two pi, but I just use the degrees here.
And now, well, this is roughly 45 degrees.
So 45 degrees, cosine is something zero.
It's a one over square root of two, I guess.
No, two square root of two over two.
Yes.
Okay.
So this is cool.
Now somebody said, well, what if they're orthogonal?
So this is correct.
Orthogonal vectors, unit vectors or any orthogonal vectors have a zero dot product.
And now if you look at this, the angle of the cosine of 90 degrees is zero.
So everything plays out nicely.
Okay.
What could be like the least similar or the most different vector from you now?
Where should it point?
Yes.
Directly in the opposite direction.
Exactly.
In the opposite direction.
So the vector z now is going in the opposite direction.
So, you know, we have 180 degrees and their dot product is minus one.
Okay.
So this is just a recap of trigonometry.
Everybody's with me on that?
Any questions?
Great.
Okay.
So now unit vector is fine, but in general, the dot product is unbounded in real values.
Which means now we have two vectors, u and v, and their dot product is, yeah, this is larger than zero.
Right?
Why is that so?
Because they're pointing in kind of similar direction and the angle is less than 90 degrees.
Okay.
So now what if we extend this v vector into something larger?
So what is going to happen with the dot product?
Let's call it w.
How is going to the dot product?
How is it going to change?
Is it going to be what?
It's going to increase.
So it's going to be in relation to u times v.
It's going to be smaller, same, bigger.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Because I mean, we're, we're extended the norm of the vector.
So it increases the dot product.
So u times v, u dot product v is larger than u times v.
Right?
So when we are extending the product, but don't change the angle, it's also changing the dot product.
If we just grow the vector into the infinity, we get infinity dot product.
That's fine.
That's why it's unbounded.
Okay.
Everybody's with me.
Okay, cool.
So now let's have another vector here.
And this is going to be this one.
So how is this?
So it's going to be y.
How is y times u behaves with respect to all these, all these things?
What's going to be the result of the product of y times u?
It's going to be negative.
Exactly.
Because we're across the 90 degree boundary.
So it's going to be on the other side.
So it's going to be smaller than zero.
Okay.
So we're changed.
We basically changed the sign of the dot product.
And now if we finish the argument and just exchange here, or sorry, extend here, the y into something larger.
So z, what's going to be z times u.
So obviously follow the pattern and z times u is going to be in relation to z times y is going to be even smaller.
Because, because everything plays out here.
Okay.
So is it clear what the dot product is doing?
So it depends on the angle and also it depends on the length of the vectors.
And it could be from minus negative to plus negative.
And when the vectors kind of are orthogonal, it's going to be zero.
And then anything else will be either negative or positive.
And it kind of shows the strength of the association of these two vectors.
Okay.
Any questions?
Well, I have a question.
So we talk about, so, well, you know, strength of association and we're moving one vector.
So the vectors are basically dots.
I mean, there is, this is an origin and the vectors are just dots in the space.
I mean, you can pull them as these nice arrows, but they're basically dots.
How do you measure kind of relation between dots in a space?
There's another kind of thing where you can say, well, this is somehow in relation to something else.
Right.
I mean, yes.
Exactly.
You can just look, you know, how far these points are from each other.
So Euclidean metrics, you know, how far are the others?
So the question is, how does the product is related to Euclidean distance?
Yeah.
I mean, if we want to be things together, you know, closer, we can use dot product or we can use Euclidean distance.
So is there any, you know, what's the relation of Euclidean distance with the dot product?
This is a fair question to ask, right?
Because now, you know, here we extend it.
We extended the point here.
So we change also the Euclidean distance from here to here.
So what is the relation here?
Well, actually, it's kind of interesting and nice.
So.
So Euclidean distance, right?
We take one, we subtract two vectors and then complete the L2 norm.
So this is the Euclidean distance.
Everybody's with me what Euclidean distance is?
Very good.
So basically for each, it's a Pythagorean theorem, but in many dimensions.
Right.
So.
Well, we take the square of the Euclidean distance to make this argument more simple.
And so we take this Euclidean distance and put a square of that, which means we get rid of this very ugly square root.
So it goes away and then we just plug here in the definition.
OK, so this is the definition we have for each dimension.
We just subtract and make a square out of it.
Which we can also just rewrite into the product of these two things.
Yeah, this is just a simple algebraic operation.
We we're not doing anything fancy here.
OK, so once we get here, we can just multiply these things together.
So we multiply this with this, this with this and so on.
So on.
We end up with these three terms.
OK, so still this is an algebraic operation.
Nothing very fancy because these are just some real numbers.
OK, once we did this, what can we do with the sum?
Sum has a very nice property.
So we can basically split this into sum of, well, sum of these,
sum of these additions is the addition of the sum.
So we can split it into three and put a sum at each entry.
So we're going to basically split it into sum of that, sum of that part and sum of that part.
So it's still another linear operation.
And what we end up here with, OK, well, this looks like a definition of a dot product.
Oh, yeah, this is the product of u with itself.
OK, nice.
This is another dot product of v with itself.
And this is two dot products, two times the product of u and v.
Wow, OK, not bad.
And then obviously, if we have u and v are unit vectors, so length one,
then this becomes one times one and one times one, which we get two minus two times their dot product.
OK, so there is actually a relationship between Euclidean distance and dot product.
Dot product is kind of more, it's more complex because it could be also negative,
which tells you something about, well, you need to have the origin.
That's the point.
I mean, distance of two points is independent of whenever you shift the origin of your space,
the Euclidean distance won't change.
If you shift your origin, then the dot product will change because you're
measuring the angle to the origin.
But having shown this, we know that if you want to minimize the square of the Euclidean distance,
it is proportional to maximizing cosine similarity, because the bigger this gets,
the smaller this gets.
It's nice, right?
So if you want to move things more together in space using Euclidean distance,
you can maximize, you can try to maximize their dot product.
This is an important observation for what comes later on.
OK, so everybody's with me.
I'll give you a second to think about it.
Anybody?
Yes.
Yes, that's a good point. But you have to factor out, I mean, in general, if you have unit vectors,
then this holds. If you don't have unit vectors, you're changing the length of one of these,
sorry, you're changing the length of one of those terms because you're extending the vector.
Yeah, okay, so this is, if you have unit vectors, then there's equality.
And that's correct. But then you cannot change the length of the vector because it has unit vector.
Yeah, okay, okay, so proportional is like, okay, let's put it like that, proportional.
Yeah, I mean, this is, you know, there's three terms here. And if you change one,
obviously it will change the rest of the product. That's true, yes. But if you have a unit vector,
there's equality. And then maybe you don't want to change the length of the vectors,
but their direction. And that's what matters, basically, the geometry, not the length.
Yes, but it's a good point, yeah. Any other question?
Okay, so everybody now should kind of have more insight into what the dot product is. So it's kind
of strength of the association, has something to do with the angle, with the geometry. And also,
it's somehow related to the Euclidean distance of these points. So the closer two points are,
the smaller the dot product is, because the angle is smaller and the Euclidean distance is also
smaller. Okay, sorry, the closer they are, the greater their dot product is. Yeah, that's the
point, exactly. The far, you know, the more apart from each other, the smaller the product is,
even like negative. Okay, well, that's it for the dot product, and we'll use it later on. But now
we have to move to actually the word embeddings, and how can we get them? So fast forward,
let's talk about the distributional hypothesis, and why is it important, and where does it come from?
So if you recall, one of the word encodings, basically where you have
a vocabulary of some size, let's say 3000, which is super small, then each word is represented as
just almost 3000 zeros, and one is just one. One position is set to one, one sort of one item.
And the point is that there is no notion of any sort of semantic similarity. So all words are
equally similar or dissimilar. What does it mean here in this example? So you have a word nice,
which is represented as this one of vector, and at some position, there is just one,
you know, single one. And you have the same for words pleasant and horrible. The point is,
all of them are, you know, having distance too. So there is no notion like maybe nice
is somehow more similar to pleasant, and less similar or dissimilar from horrible,
but you have no chance to tell apart, because they're all kind of in this highly dimensional
space, and the distance between each of two is the same, right? Is it a good thing or a bad thing?
Well, it depends, but if you work with natural language processing, and you want to maybe
classify movies and represent your document as a bag of words using one-hot encoding,
you want to keep some sort of generalization where if you see something in your training data,
a nice movie, you want to be able to say, well, maybe pleasant movie also has the same label.
You want to generalize between maybe synonyms, but one-hot encoding doesn't
capture any of these synonyms, anything at all. There's just categorical random variables, okay?
It's bad. So it's actually bad. We want something better. Maybe we want something where
the words in some vector space will be closer to each other if they're somehow similar, right?
So this is the idea, and actually it comes from, even from linguistics from as early as 1930s,
35, and it's called the distributional hypothesis. And this distributional hypothesis
states that words are similar if they appear in similar contexts, okay?
So, and it makes a lot of sense. So intuitively when we encounter a sentence with an unknown word
such as the word, okay, I can't pronounce it, vampinjuk, in the following sentence,
I'll read you a sentence and you will tell me what vampinjuk is, okay? So what do you think
is vampinjuk? Think it for yourself. No, okay, so let's brainstorm. What is a vampinjuk?
Okay, interesting problem, Emil. Okay, this is cool. Okay, any other idea what is a vampinjuk?
It sounds like an animal, right?
Form of what? A tent.
Oh, Native American tent. Okay, yes, it sounds like, it sounds a bit Indian,
so it could be a tent. Okay, good. Any other cool idea what a vampinjuk is?
I have no idea, I mean, but it sounds like an animal. Okay, but I'm biased because I knew the
answer already. I mean, there's no answer, it's just made up word. Maybe, I don't know.
Marco saw a hairy little vampinjuk crouching behind a tree. So, although we have no idea
what vampinjuk is, we now know it's, it's maybe it's some sort of animal, maybe it's small,
it's hairy, like a squirrel, and it's crouching behind a tree. So, we know it's a vampire.
Okay, so we infer the meaning of the word based on the context in which it occurs.
Okay, fine example, everybody's using it. I mean, humans just work like that.
Any questions to vampinjuk? So, this is cool. I mean, so, we have a context, and the word in the
context is somehow similar to other words in the context. Because if we replace vampinjuk with
a squirrel, Marco saw a hairy little squirrel crouching behind a tree. Yeah, this is something
we've seen before, maybe in the stories. So, you replace squirrel with vampinjuk, and yeah,
I mean, in the context, it's something like the squirrel. Wow, okay, so maybe we can use it for
representing words, right? We can use the context for representing words. How can we do that? How
can we use context for representing words? What would be like the most simple solution you would
use for representing words in a context? Yes? Take n words left and right, okay, and then?
You're on the good way, so then?
Anyone else? So, this is a great starting point. So, we take some context, n words left and right.
What can we do then?
The words are similar, but yeah, but how do you do that? Like,
distance, we don't have any vectors to begin with. We have just text and vampinjuk here in the
middle. Yeah, I'm with you. Maybe it's like already advanced. I mean, we need something
more simpler. Okay, anyone else? Yes? Oh, yes, okay, you're taking it too advanced. You're
taking it to the end of the lecture. Okay, something even simpler, something very simple.
How can we represent the word using its context? We get a context, two words left, maybe two words
on the right. Maybe extend the definition of the encoding and then the index of the last word.
Okay, so you would extend the one-hot encoding into something
bigger. I agree with you. I would even extend it to some matrix.
Like vocabulary, and I would extend to the matrix. Sorry, you were first.
Maybe the average of the word I'm getting. Oh, okay, you can do that as well. That's
already super fancy. We'll get there. Any other simpler idea?
Okay, so we have a vector of words, and we put one if this word appears in the context.
Yes, exactly. So we create a matrix where we just have here, here would be the words.
Each entry is a word, and here each column is a context, like maybe two words before
and two words after. So we collect for each word all these different contexts,
and then maybe just count how many times this word appeared. So one here would be like one
pinyuk, and here would be context, Harry Little crouching behind, right? Harry Little
crouching behind, and we would just say, yeah, I saw it once. Okay, and here you would basically
construct a word context matrix, and just counting the occurrences of the word in the context. Yes.
Yes, so this is like the most simplest thing. You just count occurrences. What do you do with the
matrix? Do you want to make relative, probabilistic, and so on? It's a matter of research.
So the word context matrices, it's actually a long, long, long line of research in NLP and
distribution semantics. And then here's again the formalization. So each row represents a word from
the vocabulary, and each column represents a linguistic context in which the word appears,
and then each of these entries quantifies the strength of association between word and the
context. So it could be like counts, basically, or could be proper, somehow like weighted counts,
or something like that, exactly. So it's counting and estimating from large corpus.
So everybody's with me? This is a very simple solution to the problem. You have a word,
and then you represent it as a vector, where each of the entry in the vector is kind of
the strength of the association with each of these contexts. Yes.
Exactly. Gigantic is the good word. Very high dimensions is kind of like very decently said,
exactly. Because you will have, if you just do like n-grams, you will have like, so if you just
do like previous and next word, and you have a vocabulary of 50,000, how many contexts you will
have? 50,000 times 50,000. So it's going to be a huge context vector. So this is one problem. So
these explicit word vectors are super highly dimensional, could be even millions. So it could
be like super gigantic. The second is data sparsity. So some of these entries may be
incorrect because we didn't observe enough data points, because of this just, you would need like
super, super, super huge corpus to estimate these probabilities or probabilities, estimate the
counts correctly. So it will be somehow not a good estimate. What can you do with such a high
average matrix is something typically has been done before deep learning in NLP. It's a dimension
reduction techniques, such as singular value decomposition, so SVD. Anyone heard of SVD before?
Okay, what is SVD?
That's fine. Who remembers what is SVD?
Oh, sorry. Yeah, you can. Okay. What is SVD?
Yeah, something like that.
Okay, yeah. Yes, yes. So I guess it's right. I don't remember exactly what it is, because it's
not used anymore as a mainstream tool. But you decompose one matrix into a product of three
matrices, and you use some eigenvalues for that in the middle or something like that. It's very
complicated linear algebra thing. So we don't tackle that. That's great, because we have something
better, which is not so bad. SVD is actually hard to scale. So the algorithm for SVD, it's,
I guess, the bottleneck is the size of the matrix. So, okay, good. So we have something simple,
methods, but they are not the best, maybe. So maybe you have something better. Well, what was
the goal? Okay, so yeah, we want to, we're interested in learning representations of words
in context. Okay, yeah. So count-based matrices, what else? Well, we had something for learning
representation of words in a context, right? We had it already. What was that? We learned
representation of words in a context. Using what? And the language models in neural networks.
Exactly. We had language models in neural networks that kind of took a context, predicting
the next word, and through that, learn the embedding representation. Yeah, we have it
already. We have another way of learning word representation of words based on their context.
Okay, this is what we did. So we learned something here, and we also learned something in this matrix.
So we learned something about words in their context. Can we utilize it for learning
some of these so-called embeddings? So embeddings matrix here. So we can definitely use
neural language models for learning word embeddings. We can do that, but there's,
yeah, there's a price we have to pay for that, and maybe there's better ways of learning these
embeddings. Okay, what is, okay, the interesting thing. So what is, remember now, our counting
base, like two words left, two words right. What we are having here in this language model?
We only have like on the left hand side. So yeah, why? Well, because we said like language
model is from left to right, and we have this Markov property, and we have this count-based
language model, blah, blah, blah. But if we want to learn like the embeddings, so maybe it's,
you know, maybe we can, we don't use that. Yeah, we have another thing here, which is kind of
complicated, or maybe confidentially quite hard. What was that again? If you're doing this language
models, neural language model. There is a language model. So we have a language model,
neural language model. There is something which costs a lot of time to compute.
The softmax, why is it so?
The denominator is a summation over 50,000 items. Super costly, super costly to compute,
but it's fine. Okay, we, okay, maybe we can solve it somehow. All right, so let's move on.
Let's move from neural language models to training word embeddings. So the goal of the
neural language model was to predict probability distribution over next word,
continue it, condition on the previous words. Okay, great.
And as a side product, it learned some useful word embeddings. But the point is,
what if, what if we don't need the probability distribution, but just we want to learn these
word embeddings, right? We just want to learn these, sorry, I'm going back. We want to learn
this. We don't care about what's predicted here, whether it's probability or not. We don't care.
We care about like good representation of words. So, okay, what if we don't need this probability?
So we can do two things, which I already mentioned a little bit. We can just relax our Markov
assumption and we can, we don't have to look in just to the past, but we can maybe look into the
future, left and right. Why not? Count-based, you know, count-based techniques did it as well,
so we can do it too. Why not? And we can just completely get rid of this normalization in
softmax because we aren't interested in probability distribution. Will it make it faster? Yes. Hell,
yeah. Will it make it better? We will see. Okay. So let's, let's do the simplification. So the first
one is we're going to ditch the Markov property. So we will look into the future. Here, so
previously we had like the black dog and the next word was bark, right? Now we say, okay, well,
the target word is in the middle. So we're going to take the context, we can concatenate together
as we had before, and then squeeze it through the, you know, two layers, blah, blah, blah,
and here's still the softmax and we're going to predict the middle word. So it's basically the
same as we had before in the never-language model, but now we don't model like the third word given
the first and the second, but we just model the second given the first and the third.
We can do that. We don't care about left, right. We just take the context. Okay. Any questions?
Yes. You first, you second. So am I getting it right that we're throwing everything away, but
it's not the context, right? We're using the context, but we're saying, well, the context
doesn't have to be just from left to right. Yeah, but it's just the context. Just the context, yeah.
I don't, I don't think I understood your question.
Okay. You had a question.
This only takes one word or two words. Usually the context is a lot bigger.
Yeah, that's correct. But my slides are too small to put like more context in there.
So obviously you could have more here the word and here the word, which go through V and V
and V and concatenate them. And here again, two words V and concatenate, right?
What do you mean? Like the, so you want to take context?
If you take context, I don't like predict the next word, you just take the next X word.
Yes.
For context, you also take the next X word.
And after, so I would imagine you would need a lot more.
Well, if you do it wisely, not, I mean, you can, yeah. So how big the, how big the content is,
context is here, kind of it. So if I take one, two, three, four, five context words and concatenate
them from this, I'm going to have like a large vector, which is combination of five vectors.
Yes, that's correct. Maybe that's fine. Maybe there's a better way to do so
better than concatenation. Right. But I can say, yeah, let's take a previous 10 words.
And after 10 words, theoretically, I can do that. It's like taking a, in their language model,
taking N previous words and predicting the next word. And you can do that in a language model,
because it just grows linearly, not like in the, in the count based language models. Okay.
Any other question?
All right, good. So now we're modeling the middle word. This is fine.
So nothing substantially changed. Now we want to give up the costly probability distribution.
So instead of predicting the probability distribution, we just want to predict some score
of the context and the target word. So what, what could such a score be? Let's say,
now forget about predicting probability of the word. You have a target word and you want to,
you have a context and you want to score it somehow.
And maybe the score is something which you want to predict,
like as a variable. So you want to score word and context.
What could, what could be a score? What is it something like we would,
which scores we would prefer for certain things and which we kind of don't like?
Say again, loud. Sorry. Maybe it's right.
You have a target word that never appears in the context.
Oh, if you have a target word that never appears in the context, then it should be low score.
And if it appears in the context, it should be high score. Yeah. That makes actually a lot of
sense. Yeah. So the idea is that we have a word target word, and if the target word actually
appears in the context, it should be kind of okay. So yes, I want this. And if the target
word doesn't appear in the context, it should be lower score. It's same with the counts and
the count-based metrics. Like there was a zero for words which don't appear in this context.
Okay. Yeah. This is exactly what we want to do. So we prefer words in their true context
and we penalize words in their sort of like untrue context. So for words that don't appear,
how we get this? I mean, how we get words in true context and words in untrue context or
they never been there? We're going to use a very, very nice trick. We're going to use
something called negative sampling. So instead of predicting the probability distribution of the
target word, we create an artificial binary task by randomly shuffling the target word.
And we're going to say that for a positive example, so we have a positive example,
and this is taken from the corpus where the word is actually has been spotted in the context.
Okay. So for example, the and dog and the target word was black. So here the word would be black
and you would be the dog. And this would be a positive example. For a negative example,
though, we would kind of shuffle the word and change it to something else.
And maybe this something never actually appeared in the corpus. So this would be like negative.
And we're going to say, well, this is going to be value one is going to be a value zero.
Does it make sense? So we randomly replace the target word.
Making it as a negative example. Okay. So how do we sample this negative word?
Yes. So we can use, we can put, we can randomly sample it from the, from the vocabulary,
but maybe you want to kind of follow the distribution of words in the vocabulary.
So we're going to estimate a probability distribution by just counting and dividing.
So corpus based frequency or summary weighting. This is not really important, but obviously you
want to maybe sample words that are more common than words that are just super awkward
and just appears, you know, with super low probability, but basically randomly sampling,
resample the target word. So I have two examples of that. Maybe it will be even clearer afterwards.
So here's our network and this is the positive example. And we had it before. So this is cool.
So we have the black dog and the black is the target word and what we're going to do now.
So, you know, okay. So the label is one, right? Because this is the true example. It's like a
positive one. It happened. So, and we're using this architecture as yet before, this is the
neural language model kind of change into predicting the, you know, the middle word.
So we're going to somehow model the context. So before that it was concatenation, maybe it will
be something else. We're going to somehow combine it with the, with the target word, because we need
to plug it together. And then there will be some hidden layers as before. And we've put it through.
Oh, now we put it through a sigmoid and yeah. Why is it sigmoid here? Okay.
Because this is a binary classification, right? We are saying it's either Y is in zero or one.
So we've squeezed everything through sigmoids. So there were from this hidden layers comes a
single real value and we squeeze it through sigmoid. And obviously in sigmoid, if this real
value is positive, then the sigmoid will be, the output of the sigmoid will be larger than 0.5.
Everybody's with me on that? Okay. So if this is coming positive and we have the sigmoid,
oops, sorry. No, no, no, no, no. Wrong. Sigmoid.
So something like that. So if this is positive, then the sigmoid will be over 0.5.
Okay, good. So this is the positive example. Any questions? Yes.
If I get a value of, for example, 0.5, which means I'm not sure which is how do I then...
Yeah. Most likely you won't get 0.5. Most likely.
Something above like 0.6.
Yeah. Then you say it's positive. Yeah. It's like binary...
You say the sigmoid, then I convert the sigmoid value into 0.5.
Exactly. You convert the sigmoid output into the binary. I mean, you use the sigmoid for
in the cross entropy loss, basically, because it gives you information how much uncertain the model
is. And if it's a true example, you want to be as close to one as possible. If it's negative,
as close to zero as possible. So typically the output, the prediction will be somehow like 90
something and or zero something. Yeah. Any questions? Any other questions? Yeah.
You're just learning the embeddings for the first time and kind of...
Do you use embeddings for the first time?
No, I'm learning all of them. I'm learning embeddings for all of these works.
So like, but why is it like,
do you just use embeddings first of all when you're... I mean, all embeddings are then different?
Why are they different? Okay. Because I'm creating...
Why are they treated differently? I mean, they have different function in the model.
I mean, this is the... And doc is just the context. I want to have a context. And this is the
true kind of the true label. Sorry. Yeah. The true label, true word. And I want to combine them
somehow to make sure that if this context and the true label comes together, it comes with one here.
Because there's, I mean, you can combine... And there's a lot of freedom how to combine these
two together. Right. But if you want to, if you just cram them into one vector, maybe it won't
learn that well, I guess. So we have to... This thing will be crucial as we'll see later. Okay.
You have a question?
I wanted to create a task where you can evaluate it and see if it's good.
Yeah.
And make it as simple as possible.
Yes.
And why should we strain the other embeddings from the context?
Because we can just learn them like... For example, this context, it looks good at doc
because there's the fact that there are labels. We also get some extra information.
Exactly. Yes. Yes. You're learning for all of the words from the context at the same time. So it's
like it's extra bonus because you have the framework to do so because everything will
be deprecated and you get here the gradient of L with respect to E and here the gradient of L
with respect to E and here as well. So you just use it as in one pass, you learn more parameters
just by one pass for the target word than for other words. Okay. Because in the neural
language model, you have the same thing. You're learning the embeddings. Just come... Let me come
back here. You're learning the embeddings here for all of the words of the proceedings
words at the same time. Yeah. You do the same thing.
So coming back to the example. So this was a positive example.
And how would the negative example, it will be the very same architecture or the very same thing,
but here I replace the word, what was the black with some randomly sampled word, which is with
and the label is zero. Obviously the with doc, you won't see that at all. So it's random word
somehow makes no sense. And the model should recognize, oh, in this context, this word,
like linguistically makes no sense, but maybe it could be another word. It could be.
So actually I was thinking like, which word should I put in there? And I had no idea,
like what could be a random word? What could be a random word that doesn't have to do anything
with the, the, the, the, and doc. I don't know, like a lecture. Okay. Good. Lecture.
Nothing to do with doc or anything alike. Yes. What? Yeah. I don't know. So one,
one you can doc would be like cat and dogs. You never know. So like church. Okay. No lecture
doc also makes sense. So I, you know, it's really hard to become a big example, which kind of no,
don't make no sense anyway. So there is a word which is obviously wrong. And the network is
trying to punish the network for predicting predicting is correct. So it's trying to learn
that this is, this is not the right word. Yes. What happens with words like the, or a,
which can appear pretty much anywhere. They will learn some, some word embeddings that will be,
that will put them somewhere like more somewhere in the space, which I don't know. I think it's a
good question. Let's let's try it. Let's turn, let's train it. And let's have a look at the
word embeddings of these a and V and so on where they live. Maybe they live somewhere. So it's a
question. Maybe they will have some, some syntactic properties and they will be together because of
syntax. Maybe it really depends on the algorithm on the size of the context, what is in the context
and maybe the algorithm, which is, which is trainable. They will, they will have some
embeddings. You can also use embeddings for all out of vocabulary words as well. I need
to typically put it to, to zeros. Okay. Another question. Yes. No,
I didn't understand the question. Sorry.
I'm sorry. What do you mean by generalize?
Well, they can. Yeah. So whether if you train it on one corpus, whether they will be similar in
the other corpus, like generalized to other corpus or yes, yes. And no, I mean the idea I'll
get you. The idea is to, you learn these embeddings on some super large corpus. So you see like
pretty much everything in the language, which gives you a strong signal already to learn good
embeddings. And then you can use the embeddings later on to adapt to your, to whatever you're
doing in your downstream tasks, so to say. So they have some, they call pre-trained embeddings
because you pre-train, but you can then fine tune them sort of say, and on your task as well. But
the idea is they have some sort of good representation. We'll come to that in the
shortcomings at the end of the lecture. Okay. You had a question or comment? Good. Yes. Yeah. You
have to train it on billions of tokens, like a very super large corpus. Yes.
Yeah. They, they don't. It's just, there's so many things that, you know, like you can, well,
the thing is you can actually train like syntactic embeddings. If you have your, if you
ever data syntax bars before, so you treat the context from the syntax tree, you can do complicated
stuff if you want. This is like the basic one. We just, you don't need any pre-training at all.
We just tokenize the text and have a vocabulary. So there's many things, but there's some, some
embeddings can do some sort of like compositional it is. So if you do like negation and the next
word and sum them up, they will do something very fancy. Okay. So this is a negative sampling.
Everybody's fine with that. We treat it as binary. So we turn our task of predicting the
probability distribution of the missing word into saying, well, this word was here or this word
wasn't here at all. Binary. Zero one. Easy. It's like a fake task, but it's just great for learning
these embeddings because we don't care about probabilities. We just care about these embeddings.
They should learn some meaningful representation. Yes.
Exactly.
Boris, say again, how was that? Like for each context, there are more negative examples than
positive examples. Why, why, why should be the, why, it doesn't have to be the case. It's your
decision because you're sampling the data by yourself. You're taking a true context
and there's a middle word, which is a target word. And if you don't do anything, you only have the
positive example. In order to turn it into negative example, you say I'm flipping, I'm,
you know, changing the middle word into something else. And this is how you create your negative
example. So your data set could be super balanced. You can have the same number of positive,
the same number of negative examples. So that's why typically actually generate more negative
examples than positive examples. Yeah. We'll, we'll come to that. Okay. Can we move on? Right.
So we're moving to one of the famous algorithms for training word embedding, which is called
VirtueVec. So it's a bunch of algorithms and also a software package. It's just, by the way,
it's written in C and it's just one file of C code. And if you look into that, you, you would
be wondering like how much they cram into one, you know, line of one file of C code to train all
these, you know, fancy stuff. It was done by Tomas Mikulov in 2013 at Google. And then he moved to
Facebook later on and so on. He kicked off like this deep learning, a little bit helped, you know,
the deep learning wave, NLP. So the code is there. You can have a look in VirtueVec.C
and you'll be surprised, you know, Python is bad, but C code is even like even worse. It's really,
I mean, they made it for, for speed, right? So it's really, it's really optimized for speed,
not for readability. Anyway, so VirtueVec. VirtueVec simplifies the neural language model.
So this is our, again, our neural language model by removing the hidden layer.
So we just completely ditch this thing. We don't care about hidden layers, which means it's
actually turning into local linear model because we have a sigmoid and here is some features coming in.
So here, this is coming a real value and we turn it from sigmoid and just predict. Yeah. Why is it
so for speed? They just turn out like empirically, you don't need the whole hidden layers and stuff
like that for this particle use case for learning these embeddings. Okay, cool. So it's much faster.
Now, the question is how the heck are we modeling the context here? So we have words before and
words after through embeddings. How can we model the context? What can we do about it? Any ideas?
Yes. Why can you throw it away? Yeah. Why not? I mean, here you're combining
the context and the target word into something and then projecting it through something else,
like some hidden layers and so on. So you're doing like a multilayer perceptron, which gives you more,
let's say, expressivity in functions you can model. Yeah. But it's like your design choice
and it costs something, like it costs compute because you need to train the parameters here
and so on. Right. We were here. So let me just come back here. So you have these two hidden layers.
So we have to learn the weights and parameters and what's the size of these layers and so on.
Maybe you don't need it. And that's the case of this word. So they just basically,
after combination, just go through directly to the sigmoid to save compute.
Less parameters, much faster. Turn out that you don't need it.
Don't you need non-linearity also in the context?
Well, the only non-linearity is, well, you don't need a non-linearity. I mean,
the projection now is, yeah, that's a good question. So all these projections are
some hole in error, are they? I guess so. Yeah. That's interesting. Right. You don't
need a non-linearity here. I'll think about it. I'll think about it.
Why? What is happening here? Because there is no non-linear operation here. So it should be
some linear projection of the words. Yeah. Makes sense. Okay. Where are we? Yes. You asked us a
question. Any other question to this? Like we just completely make it more simple model. Okay. Good.
Yes. How can we model the context? Exactly. How can we model the context of these two words? So
we have this word here and this word here. So what should we plug here? How can we model the context?
The most easiest solution. Exactly. Just sum them. What did you propose?
Oh, there's, sorry. No, this is not one hop. This is embedding vector, which is
er-dim embedding. This is one hop and this is lookup. So it's taking
the vector from here and producing a vector. But you can exactly, you can just sum them up.
Why not? So we're gonna take each of those neighboring vectors and just sum them up here.
We can do average, but it's maybe too complicated. Just sum them up.
Why not? Okay. So this is how you model your context here.
And now, okay. Any questions? Why, why summing up the context? I mean, we've seen it before,
right? Do you remember the average back of words we had? Like you take your, you take your,
all the tokens in your document as vectors, could be one of the vectors, and you just sum them up
and do the average of that vector. Lecture one or two, two, two or three. Okay. So you just sum up
the vectors. If the dimensionality of that is, let's say, I don't know, 300, this will be also
300, obviously. We just sum these vectors together. Okay. And it's called continuous
back of words. Yeah. I think we had it already. The question is, okay, so we have a context
modeled as one vector, and we have the target word also modeled as a vector, which is the,
this is dimensionality, size of vocabulary times 300, maybe. Okay. Does it make sense?
Great. So how can we combine the context and the, and the target word? What is, what will be here
somehow combined? So it's abstract. I mean, I put it like abstract. I give you a second to
think about it. How can we combine these two vectors? And think about like what they're doing,
actually, because we have the true context and we have the false context. So how can we combine,
combine these two vectors together?
A little gentleman, like in the, in the back first. Yeah.
We can concatenate them. Okay. Fair enough. We can concatenate them. So, oops, where am I? We can
concat. Fair enough. Any idea? You were 10 seconds. We can take the dot product.
Any other idea? Same idea. Anything else we can combine them?
We can take the Euclidean distance.
So, okay, great. Yes. Like multiply, multiply as one vector to the other and get a matrix.
Yeah, we're kind of screwed because here we need a real number. Yeah, sorry. Well, actually,
okay, so this is the point. Concatenation is a nice idea, but here we need a real number. So,
sorry, that won't fly. For that, we would need like this multilayer perceptron in between
to squeeze it into one dimension. So it won't work. So here we had the dot product and Euclidean
distance. Okay, good. So they both, I kind of produce real number out of them. So a scalar.
This is great. What we learned also before, what's the dot product and Euclidean distance? Okay,
they have some something in, you know, they are somehow related. Not the same thing, but related.
What is cheaper? Euclidean distance or dot product? What is cheaper?
Why? Exactly. You don't need to square, you know, you don't need to square root,
you don't need to sum all these squares, you don't blah, blah, blah, blah. What is the dot product?
One times the other. So you can even like make it parallelizable. Yes.
You can vectorize it. Exactly. So if you run like large vectors on GPU, you can parallelize
even dot product and whatever. So dot product is great. It's just multiplication and summation.
You can parallelize it easily. Awesome. So it's going to be dot product because Euclidean distance
is also something like the product as we saw before. So maybe dot product is great. Yes. Okay,
good. Well, we have the product. That's a great idea to combine these two vectors.
So we're taking the context here, which is the summation of these context vectors,
and here's the target vector. So I'll flip that, right? I mean, here I have this in the middle,
and here I put the target word on the bottom just to make it clear. So we have the context,
this is the C vector. We have the target word, which is the W vector. I mean, these aren't like
weights in the linear layer, right? This is like just saying this is embedding of the target word.
And we just make a dot product and squash it through sigmoid and then say, well, if this is one,
this is a true context, if this is zero, this is the full context.
So the context words are just one-hot encodings, and they are pushed through this lookup embedding
layer. So the only learning... So this is the final thing. This is the continuous back of
words word to back. This is the thing you can implement in one afternoon in normal programming
language or in two weeks in C++. I don't know, or depending on your choice, whatever.
This is the thing. The only learnable parameters are just the embeddings. This is the only thing
you learn. Everything... Yes, you have a question. Yeah, sorry for getting back, but...
No worries. So the errors from E to the vectors, what exactly happened there? E is just a matrix.
E is a matrix, yes. It's just the row from... Yes, like you mean the V. What is V?
Yeah, that's the... That's the lookup. Yes. Yes. So V is the C times E,
right? The E matrix, which means that the embeddings matrix is... This is a size V,
and this is 300 or something, and you say, well, this is one hot, so 0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0,
and you say, okay, 0, 0, 1. This is my row, exactly. Okay.
Yes.
You are measuring the similarity between the context and the target word.
Exactly.
But that makes sense here, because obviously they are not going to be similar even though
they are in the same context.
That's a question. What is this dot product doing, right? What is it doing? It's doing
some sort of similarity, because you want the vector of the target word to be more similar
to the true context than the... Sorry, you have a context. Okay, so start with the context.
This is a vector. It's going to be a longer vector than the standard vectors, because we
are just summing up all these context vectors. We're not taking the average here. We just have
a sum. So if you sum up several vectors, you end up with a longer vector. Doesn't matter. Yes.
It's weird.
Could be. Could be. I mean, so if I... I'm recording now, so I won't tell it. But if I
design the word to it, I would say, let's take the average. Not just the sum, but the average.
So the average of embeddings could be somehow like the centroid of their meaning, and this
would be the context. But the sum somehow works better. Maybe it's faster. Maybe it's the same
with the average. I don't know.
When you sum, isn't it possible also, for example, different contexts get to the same sum?
Yes, but it's very unlikely. Yes, I mean, you can get to the same space with different
contexts to the same point, but it's very unlikely, because you're in 300 dimensions plus.
So the dimension is really huge, to be honest. So the space is kind of very weird.
So you have the context vector, but let's think in three dimensions, because I can only think
in three dimensions. So let's have the context vector. And then you were saying, oh, in this
context vector, I want to push the true words closer to this vector and kind of push the negative
words on the other hand, like pointing in the other direction. And this is what the dot product
is doing. The dot product is positive. Yes, I'm trying to maximize the dot product. Exactly.
I'm trying to maximize this thing for the true context and minimize for the negative context.
So basically, I have this vector of the context. I want my true word pointing more in this
direction. So minimizing this angle, maximizing the dot product in the true context, and pushing
the false word, the negative word, in the opposite direction. This is what it's trying to learn. So
making this embedding space behave in a way that it learns these properties.
And when I want to do the gradient descent or something, do I take all of that
and derivate it towards the rows of u that I need?
Yes. The propagation here works always the same. So you compute for each. This is different. Each
of the blue ones is differential function, which means you have the derivatives with respect to
their parameters. And then for updating the e, you need the chain rule for multiple parents.
So you sub them up together and get a gradient as well. Yes. So this is just very... I think this is
the nice example why we should understand everything as computational graph. Like deep
learning is just computational graph. And on each of the nodes, you have the gradient. So if you
understand of the propagation on any computational graph, this is the same thing as we had before.
Like there's no difference. Each function has the derivatives with respect to their
kind of children or where it comes from, arguments, and there's no other magic in here.
So this is central. This is why the dot product is actually working here. I mean,
we could try to do the Euclidean distance, but the Euclidean distance is only positive. So it
wouldn't really push far away the negative thing. The negative thing is basically saying,
well, the vector should be completely somewhere else, like the different direction.
So the word2vec is learning useful embeddings and try to distinguish good word context pairs
from the bad ones. So we create a set of the correct context pairs from the corpus. We take
it somewhere and the set here, the body of these incorrect word pairs. And exactly the goal of
these algorithms is to estimate a probability. So this is going through sigmoid. The sigmoid,
as we know, is estimating probability of the true, something which is true, given the context.
And this should be high or even one for the pairs which are from the true context and low,
which is zero for the pairs from the... Right, because we're squeezing it through the... Sorry,
let me come back. This will be from minus infinity to plus infinity.
Excuse me. So minus infinity to plus infinity. This would be the output. But after here,
it's coming just between zero and one. So we're squeezing this negative and positive into zero
and one to make it trainable as a standard binary task. So the network scores one for
true and zero for the negative ones. And yes?
Quick side question. So when you have something like the black dog in CS34,
and you have the black dog a lot in the data set, you probably want to train this more often. So
if it is here more often in the data, does it also train more often? Or is it really nice?
Yeah, okay. So yeah, your question is like, if you have multiple same instances in the data,
when you sample them, what happens?
Like you have the brown dog, which is correct, the white dog and the black dog. It's like
a standard. You probably want the model to involve predicting the black dog or something like this.
Or like train it more on the black dog? Or is it just like anything is fine?
Anything is fine. Anything which is in this context will be taken as the, so the context
will be d and dog. That's fine. So there's context and then there's some objective in between.
So this model doesn't care if you predict like black or white or brown?
We are just, yeah, we'll come to that. We're just super open. It's just an ad hoc notion
of similarity. We just plug in there and don't care. We just predict everything which is in the
context. Yes?
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Good enough. Exactly. How do you evaluate your embeddings? Are good. That's
another question. We will come to that. Okay. Okay. I think I have to move on because we have
something still to finish. Okay. So the loss, corpus y loss of where to exist, as we said,
like this is the formula of loss. You sum for all the instances, the losses, which is predicting one
for correct and zero for incorrect. So this is a standard thing. You don't have to remember that.
The point is, there was one question, like, I know each correct word context, we sample k
negative pairs from the others. So the negative are k times larger than d.
Right? So somebody asked here, like, how many you were, right? The negative parameter. So the
negative things are sampled actually more often because it's a hyper parameter. So it's maybe
like five or 20. You have like so many more negative examples for the network to learn than
the positive ones. So it's a hyper parameter. Works better. Okay. So this is what the continuous
backoff works. Now we can even more relax the context. We can make it even simpler,
like even super simple. What do we like? More even simplification of the context. So we have a
sum of the context vectors and then the product. Right? Can we do it any more simple?
Any ideas? How can we make it even simpler?
So we have two words before, two words after, take the embeddings and make the sum and then
project the target word. Can we make it even simpler, the context? Something even more stupid?
Just one word. Yes. Welcome to skip gram. This is it. You can even like make it simpler where we
say each of the context word will be its own instance. So I'm just modeling the dot product
between the target word and one context word at a time. You're independent of the others.
I don't care about the others. So I'm just basically saying, does this one single context
word occur in the context of the target word? I'm completely disentangling because before that,
we kind of like sum them together and go just directly like jointly, all of them,
all the context words. I'm just saying here, yes, each word. Yes. I just sample more instances
and just train them, have more data. It's two different models. Exactly. It's just two different
models right now. I'm creating, I'm training. Basically, if I have context K, I'm training K
different models at once or not at once. I'm training K different models, one after each other.
Does it make sense what I'm doing here? So instead of summing all these context words together,
I'm just saying, well, for this target word, first, let's have a look at the context word I minus one.
And what is the dot product? And is it from the correct context, yes or no? Okay. Let's have a
look at the C, the other one, like afterwards. Yeah. Let's do embeddings and project. And is it
from correct context or not? And this is zero one. Your first few seconds.
So you decide you use the word in the context, we take the average of all the output from the model?
No, you just take one word, do the forward pass, back propagation, and update the embeddings,
the parameters. Then you take the next instance, forward pass, back propagation,
and update the embeddings, the parameters. Then you take the next instance, forward pass,
back propagation, or you just, you batch it. You do also like a standard mini batch thing.
I don't think so because, okay, so let's, let, let me do one thing.
Let's forget about this completely.
So this is one training instance, one kind of training thing. So I take a word,
I take the target word, multiply and say, this is from, okay, I shouldn't do this.
Is this from, is this true context or false context? That's it. So I don't see any,
any matrices or concatenation here. There's not such a thing, I'm afraid,
but maybe you want to draw something and talk to me later. Okay, cool. Let's do that.
No worries. Okay, good. Any other questions to Skipgram?
First.
So is it true that inverse predicts that the distance to the other distance in the
tantrums metas and skip frame is random?
No, well, it, it, it matters kind of, but you, you have like very small context. You
have just one word context. You say, okay, I'm target word. I have some words around and
just pick one. And this is my context for this one single instance training.
And I do it for other words, but they are completely independent. I'm just saying,
I don't care, you know, whether these contexts, they belong together or not. I don't care.
I'm just taking one word at a time from the context.
So in retrospect, we had multiple input bias.
Yeah. In the, in the, in this, in this, in this continuous back of words,
we have multiple sum together.
Okay. Then it doesn't make a difference where the word stands in the sentence.
No, no, no, no. They're just completely, yes. So it's like back of word. It's a back of word
kind of switch together. So it doesn't make a distinction whether it's like previous or after
just the context likes the back. Yes, that's correct. And our question you had one. No. Yes.
It's the same model, but you, you just, you create different instances and different contexts.
So to say it's, it's skip gram is part of word2vec by the way, it's just a different algorithm. I
didn't say it clearly. So it's still in word2vec where you can decide where you want to CBOV,
CBOW or skip gram. Okay. Any question? So, yes.
So I do something and I can put a condition and then the state instead of concatenate and then
it's just parallelizing. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Parallelizing it's yeah. It could be parallelizing
exactly because they're independent. So you can parallelize. Okay. So basically, yeah,
that's what I'm coming to. Like you have choosing the context. So we have two different
things. This is like continuous back of words. So we take the middle word is the target word
and the M words to each side is the context. And we sum them together or the skip gram is you
create basically two M distinct tasks and each is pairing the focus word with a different context
word, right? This is just wrapping up what we are talking about and skip gram actually are to be,
you know, fun to be robust and efficient to train. And both of them are part of word2vec algorithms.
Any question? Okay, good. So let me just finish quickly. So you can go into subword units because
all these things are just on the word level, you know, and if you have like a morphological rich
language, you have, you have troubles with your vocabulary and stuff like that. So you can,
this is the limitation. Let me skip that because this is clear.
But how about we split the word as a back of character and grams. So we go into subwords
and each of these character engrams has their own embeddings.
And we represent the word as a sum of engram embeddings. It sounds weird. I'll show you the
example. It will show much weirder, but it works in practice for highly morphological languages.
So you take a word like eating and you generate, okay, this is a, you add two special symbols,
one for the beginning and one for the end. And you generate all engrams, character engrams
of size three to six. There's going to be this, this, this, this, this, then length four,
length five until length six. So these are all sub engram, sub character engrams.
And each of them will be now in your kind of inventory of words or vocabulary sort of. And
each of them will bear, will have their own embeddings in the matrix E. And then in order
to find the, the embedding of, of the word eating, you just sum up together the words,
the embeddings of the word, sorry, the embeddings of the engram, character engrams constituting the
word. Why is it good? Well, because it's learning, if you have like out of vocabulary words,
you know, for example, one pinuk, beautiful one pinuk is great. So we have one pinuk,
something like that. And you don't know what is that, but there's this pinuk
and it may be, you know, maybe the embeddings on pinuk has been learned on some different
contexts, like, you know, the, the, the other animal, which is compinuk, and it has been,
you know, seen in your training data and the inuk is part of, you know, learn the embeddings. So
it's kind of transfers some of part of the words. Yes. You can learn much more morphologically
or inform embeddings here. So it's really works for morphologically rich languages.
Finnish, super huge morphology and, you know, like Slavic languages, Czech and so on. So
this work, this works well. Yeah. But here, if I have to work, like, for example,
cool and school, which don't have anything to do with each other, it's going to get a very
sure. Yes. Yeah, yeah, sure. You know, but then you still have the cool and okay. School
and then cool. Yeah. There could be, I think so. Okay.
Well, you have CH here, but maybe the cool will be a shared thing. Yes. But just a part of that
will be shared. And the whole thing, the school also will be part of that because it's shorter
than six or six characters. And maybe these embeddings of the, of the word will be more
representative than these, you know, it's trained this Skibrem as well. So maybe it will learn
better embeddings for the whole word. And the sub words will just, you know, be part of it.
It's hard to tell what's in these embeddings, like 300 dimensions or 600 dimensions.
Yeah. That's a fair point. Okay. Any questions? Good. So what is good about embeddings and what
is bad? I need three minutes and I'll finish. Advantages. So how can we use word embeddings?
Obviously we, you know, each word has now lives in a space of, you know, several hundred dimensions.
So we use this as semantic input to any neural network instead of one word encoding.
And this is an instance of transfer learning where you pre-train or self-train on an auxiliary
task. And once you train them, you plug into more complex model. So we can use them. We will use
word embeddings for anything down the road, like a recurrent neural networks and so on.
So for example, we can represent a document as an average of its words embeddings,
average back of words for text classification. It mostly will work better than just one of the
depending on the task. Very cool. And this is also like word2vec was, you know, why the deep
learning revolution in NLP around 2015 took place. So word2vec has been like, you know,
one of the super, super important contributions to the development of deep learning in NLP.
So we can use this for plugging into neural networks. Okay, good. Semantic similarity
and short equivalent similarity and query expansion. Okay. So here in this paper,
they try to use it for query expansion using word embedding. So if you search for something,
you know, a word, then maybe you want to find a synonyms, right? Or something which is similar
because word2vec will learn some synonyms because synonyms live in the same context.
So they will have similar embeddings. And they said like using word2vec,
continuous back of words embedding approach applied over the entire corpus on which searches
perform, we select terms that are semantically related to the query. Oh, this is, this is cool
idea, right? So you have your database of products, your query term, and even though there
is not exact match, you will find, you know, something which is, which is like embeddings
close in this embedding space. Okay. What can go wrong here? Well, so I tried to search, I think
Reva kind of applied word embeddings last year or a couple of years back into search. And I tried to
buy COVID tests and I typed COVID in there and it gave me two Corona beers, like the thing,
because they use some word embeddings train on whatever news. And these word embeddings
learned that COVID and Corona is the same thing. Obviously Reva had no COVID tests in there, but
had, you know, beers of, you know, Corona beers. So if you type here in COVID, it returns Corona.
Yeah. So query expansion with word embeddings might be tricky because it's not like it's,
you know, word embeddings, if you make a comparison and include in distance or
custom similarity, it's just, it's not, it's not directional. It's just, you know, it's a distance.
So yeah, in this case it failed. I can imagine like, yeah, sure. We have word embeddings much
better for search. I'll put it in there. Yes. Awesome example. Okay. I promised you that you
will learn how to mine analogies with Word2Vec at the beginning of this lecture. So Germany to
Berlin is France to Paris. You can take the embedding of Berlin, subtract the embedding
of Germany at the embedding of France, and it will all put a vector X, which is closest to
parties in this embedding space. This is cool. This is really cool. So you learn something about
properties of things, and you can do this vector arithmetic to find analogies using just word
embeddings or this queen. So you take the embedding of king, subtract embedding of men,
and up the embedding of woman. And what you get is the embedding, which is closest to the queen.
This is, this is pretty cool. Actually, this is pretty cool because in order to learn this,
you didn't need anything labeled, anything, any notion of anything. Just learn good word
representation from looking into the context on huge, huge, you know, collection of examples.
Nothing else. Yes.
So just back to my question, so it isn't able to generalize.
Yes.
So like in the dog example, for example, if I had like a dog that's laying a red dog.
And now yellow is also...
Exactly.
...the same color.
Exactly. Yeah, it will, it will maybe, it will put the colors somewhere in the space closer to
each other or adjectives or depending on, you know, which context you train on, but it will
generalize. And even more than that, it's able to, you know, look into, look around. If you're
testing embeddings, you know, you can, we, we had a syntax based embeddings two years back.
So you can watch this video. Let me just finish very quickly. Limitations, word embeddings. So
the similarity is completely operational. So words are similar if used in similar context,
that's it. We didn't say anything about, you know, they should be similar or same syntax,
and I'll be whatever. Words opposite to each other, like buy and sell and hot and cold tend
to appear in similar contexts. So, you know, they can be in the same space in the embeddings and
it's not a good thing. So that's bad. We have biases in the data. So they, obviously we learn
from data and these data sets reflect the human biases in the real world. So word embeddings
encode not only stereotypical biases, but also, you know, race or gender simply vertical,
reflecting the status quo distribution of gender with respect to carriers or first names. So
this is very cool science paper where it shows like embeddings encode these biases. Like
if you type nurse, it's closer to women. If you type doctor, it's closer to men.
Why? Well, because it's just the bias inherited from the data, because we talk more about like,
you know, this is, this is how, how the world unfortunately is so far. And this is encoded
in the embeddings as well. So keep that in mind. And the last point is, yes, you have a question.
You always have no matter what you do, whatever you train will always learn from the text that it
trains from. It learns from the text. Yes, exactly. The bias will always take no matter what.
So, okay. Yeah, this is a great question and I will leave it to the, so we will have a guest
lecture at the end of this semester from Thomas Arnold on ethics. And I think he'll look,
he'll talk a lot about biases in the data and ways. And one last point, which is really important
that we have, we model like each word has one, has one embedding, but we have words which are
kind of polysemic. So bank could be a financial institution or the side of the river or star
could be in shape or celebrity or stars in the, in the sky. And if you use a single vector for
all firms, this is fine for a model because we cannot like disambiguate the senses.
So keep that in mind. Recap, word embeddings are cool. Self-supervised training of word embeddings
is really a thing. And we use CBO and skip gram. You have a question. So yes.
I was going to say this, or are there solutions for word embeddings? I'm sorry.
You can have a, you can have a look here. You can do like disambiguation and stuff like that
on embeddings, but we will have better models, which are transformers. They take it into account
the context. All right. Thanks a lot. See you next week.